<document>
<exercise>1 After the holidays</exercise>
<exercise>A1 a) Write down as many holiday words as you can. You have got one minute. Who has got the most words?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Organize your words in a word web. P1  WB A1, p. 4</exercise>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<exercise>A2 L 1/1 a) The friends are back from holiday.</exercise>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>Look at their souvenirs. Say …</gap>
<exercise>∙ … who brought them back</exercise>
<gap>There is …/There are …</gap>
<gap>I think this is Rajiv’s souvenir because he went to … /spent his holiday at/in …</gap>
<exercise>b) Listen to the friends and complete the grid. Were you right in a)?</exercise>
<exercise>c) Decide which of the friends’ holidays you like best and say why.</exercise>
<gap>I think Caroline had a …</gap>
<gap>I like Emma’s holiday best because …</gap>
<gap>great time because …</gap>
<exercise>10 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … what they are</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … where they are from.</exercise>
<page id='2'>
<chapter>1/A</chapter>
<exercise>A3 Target task v " Project Prepare a collage about your holidays and present it.</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<sentence>Look at pp.</sentence>
<sentence>Last year, your teacher asked you to collect souvenirs and/or write a postcard from your holidays (or your home town).</sentence>
<exercise>1 Work in groups of four. Put all your souvenirs and postcards on a table.</exercise>
<sentence>Did you have a good holiday?</sentence>
<sentence>That sounds great.</sentence>
<sentence>Oh, that’s too bad.</sentence>
<sentence>Why didn’t you like it?</sentence>
<sentence>Every pupil says something about his/her holiday and souvenir.</sentence>
<sentence>The others ask questions to find out more.</sentence>
<sentence>Where did you stay?</sentence>
<listing>What did you do? had a wonderful/exciting holiday went to Spain · stayed at home · went camping · …</listing>
<listing>stayed with my grandparents · went to the beach · … It was warm/cold/sunny/rainy/cloudy/foggy/snowy/… stayed for a week/two weeks/a weekend/…</listing>
<sentence>Where did you find this souvenir?</sentence>
<gap>I found/bought the souvenir …</gap>
<exercise>2 Together prepare a collage about your holidays and present it to another group. Speaking 1, p. 126 Wordbank Weather, p. 149</exercise>
<exercise>Support ∙ Practise your presentation. ∙ Look at page 126 for more tips.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Give the other group some feedback. Don’t forget to say something positive first.</exercise>
<sentence>Your presentation was easy to understand and you spoke clearly.</sentence>
<sentence>Your poster looks neat and tidy but you should speak up more.</sentence>
<sentence>Your presentation was fun to listen to/ really interesting.</sentence>
<sentence>Your poster looks attractive but it could be a bit more informative.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words eleven 11</footnote>
<exercise>∙ Speak up.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='3'>
<chapter>1/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 L 1/2 a) Think of Caroline’s holiday. Where did she go? What did she do? What was her souvenir?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Close your books and listen to Gillian and Emma. What are they talking about?</exercise>
<exercise>c) Read the dialogue and answer the questions to get all the information about Emma and Caroline’s holiday. Note down your answers.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What did they do/happened?  WB B1, p. 5</exercise>
<sentence>After the holidays Gillian and Emma meet at Westfield Shopping Centre.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: Hi Emma, where’s Caroline?</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: Hi Gill.</sentence>
<sentence>No, she’s writing an email to Sophie, her friend from Manchester.</sentence>
<sentence>Wales.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: Oh, the pony camp.</sentence>
<sentence>Did you like it?</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: Yes, it was great!</sentence>
<sentence>I had the cutest pony!</sentence>
<sentence>His name was Donald.</sentence>
<sentence>He was as white as snow.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: So, what did you do at the pony camp?</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: We really had a lovely time: we cleaned the stables and went for rides.</sentence>
<sentence>It was so much fun!</sentence>
<sentence>We want to go again next year.</sentence>
<sentence>Hey, why don’t you come with us?</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: Well, after the start Donald suddenly stopped and I fell off.</sentence>
<sentence>It was terrible!</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: Well, I really like animals but I don’t think I’m a country person.</sentence>
<sentence>There are no shops and no cinemas in the country.</sentence>
<sentence>I think a mouse scared him.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline rode Daisy.</sentence>
<sentence>London is much more exciting than Wales.</sentence>
<sentence>Nobody could stop them.</sentence>
<sentence>The shops in London are bigger, of course.</sentence>
<sentence>But it was nice to be in the country.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: No way!</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: Yes, and the story gets even funnier!</sentence>
<sentence>Only Olivia and Caroline were left.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: But wasn’t it a bit boring?</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: No, there was so much to do.</sentence>
<sentence>But her pony suddenly stopped, too, so Caroline came first.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: Caroline won the race, right?</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: Yes, but don’t tell anyone, please!</sentence>
<gap>Emma: Well … yes, you could say so. The funniest thing happened!</gap>
<sentence>Gillian: Why was it funny?</sentence>
<exercise>12 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Where did they go?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ When did they go?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='4'>
<chapter>1/B</chapter>
<exercise>B2 Gillian wants to tell her dad about the pony race. Complete her email and use these words and phrases to structure your text:</exercise>
<listing>First … · Then … · Next … · In the end …</listing>
<exercise>B3 Gillian said, “I don’t think I’m a country person”. Are you a country or a city person? Why? Talk to a partner. Wordbank In the country; city p. 149, 151</exercise>
<sentence>To: jfcollins@inter.net.co.uk Hello!</sentence>
<gap>Hi Dad, How are you? I went to Westfield today and met Emma for some shopping. She went to a pony farm with her parents and Caroline in the holidays. She told me about a really funny pony race: first … …</gap>
<exercise>B4 Grammar detective: comparison of adjectives</exercise>
<sentence>‘small – small er – small est ’ ‘exciting – more exciting – most exciting’ Can you solve this puzzle?</sentence>
<exercise>1 Copy the grid. Look at B1 and fill in the grid.</exercise>
<gap>adjective comparative superlative cuter …</gap>
<exercise>2 Find more examples from B1. What is the rule? When do you have to be careful with the spelling?</exercise>
<gap>prett ier … …</gap>
<gap>… most exciting biggest</gap>
<exercise>3 Look at LiF 3 on page 137 for help and write a grammar card. Add the comparative and superlative forms of good and bad to your grammar card. P11  WB B2, p. 6</exercise>
<exercise>B5 Emma and Gillian bought a lot of things at Westfield Shopping Centre. Look at them and compare them.</exercise>
<exercise>cheap ∙ expensive ∙ interesting ∙ cool ∙ big ∙ delicious ∙ cute ∙ nice ∙ good</exercise>
<gap>Support … as long as … / … as expensive as … … longer than … / … more expensive than … … the longest … / …the most expensive …</gap>
<sentence>Example: The scarf is cheaper than the T-shirt.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirteen 13</footnote>
</page>
<page id='5'>
<chapter>1/B</chapter>
<exercise>B6 v Extra: Viewing: Adventure holidays KG organizes adventure holidays for children. George went on holiday with KG to Beam House.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Read the sentences. Then watch the advert and say which sentences are right and which are wrong.</exercise>
<exercise>1 At the summer camp there is a river where you can go kayaking. 2 You can go horse-riding on a KG holiday. 3 KG holidays are for boys only. 4 You can come to KG camps for a day, a week or a school holiday. 5 There are pupils from different countries, e.g. from Germany. 6 You can choose which activities you would like to do in the morning and in the afternoon.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Work with a partner. Are you interested in a KG holiday? Say why/why not.</exercise>
<exercise>B7 L 1/3 George told his friends everything about his holiday at Beam House – except one thing. Read the story and find out.  WB B4, p. 7</exercise>
<sentence>George loved Beam House.</sentence>
<sentence>He likes action and at Beam House you get a lot of that.</sentence>
<sentence>On his first day he went surfing and abseiling.</sentence>
<sentence>The next day, he went on the zip wire after breakfast.</sentence>
<sentence>Later he also took some cool photos of the older kids doing motorsports on the quad bikes.</sentence>
<sentence>At five o’clock everyone at Beam House met to go orienteering.</sentence>
<exercise>10 Anna and Claire. The instructor gave them a “Hey, calm down! We’re a team, remember?”</exercise>
<sentence>They had to use a compass to find a treasure box and get back to Beam House as fast as possible.</sentence>
<sentence>The girls were very excited.</sentence>
<sentence>“OK then, let’s go,” George answered and turned round.</sentence>
<sentence>The others followed him.</sentence>
<exercise>15 walk towards the woods while Anna, Brady say a word.</exercise>
<sentence>They walked through the woods for twenty minutes.</sentence>
<sentence>Everything seemed OK until George looked at the map again.</sentence>
<exercise>20 After ten minutes of walking he asked Claire, nervous.</exercise>
<sentence>“Are you sure you know where we’re going?” “Why?” she asked.</sentence>
<sentence>“Do you need help?” Brady asked.</sentence>
<sentence>“No, no, it’s OK,” said George.</sentence>
<sentence>He didn’t want to ask Brady for help in front of the girls.</sentence>
<exercise>25 the opposite direction.” followed.</exercise>
<sentence>“If you think you can do a better job, here you go!” Claire gave George the compass and looked at him angrily.</sentence>
<sentence>“George, stop!” Anna finally shouted.</sentence>
<sentence>“I can see a hill over there.</sentence>
<exercise>14 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='6'>
<chapter>1/B</chapter>
<exercise>B8 What do you think happens next? Use a grid to organize your ideas.  WB B5, p. 8</exercise>
<gap>What? Who? Where? When? …</gap>
<exercise>B9 It is easier to read a story that has a clear structure. Read the story in B7 again and make a list of phrases or words you can use ∙ to connect sentences (e. g. and, but ) P6-P8  WB B6, p. 8</exercise>
<exercise>B10 Target task v Portfolio Finish the story from B7. You can make it funny, scary or exciting.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Plan your story and use your ideas from B8. Writing, p. 128</exercise>
<exercise>2 Structure your story and make it interesting. LiF 2R: Simple past, p. 135; LiF 4: Connectives, p. 138</exercise>
<exercise>3 Swap your story with a partner’s. Use the checklist and give your partner feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<sentence>Look at pp.</sentence>
<exercise>3 connectives (e.g. so, but, …) 3 structure words (e.g. first, then, …) 3 direct speech (e.g. “Why?” answered Claire.) 3 adjectives, comparatives and superlatives (e.g. exciting, the scariest thing that …)</exercise>
<sentence>Your story is great but you need to add more direct speech to make it more interesting.</sentence>
<exercise>4 Gallery walk: Hang up your stories in the classroom. Choose three of your classmates’ stories and read them. Which one is your favourite and why? Gallery walk, p. 130  WB B7, p. 9</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</footnote>
<exercise>∙ to structure a story (e. g. on his first day, the next day )</exercise>
</page>
<page id='7'>
<chapter>1/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 a) It is the first day after the holidays at William Ellis School.</exercise>
<sentence>Look at the picture and say why Mrs Brogden is angry.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Think – pair – share:</exercise>
<gap>Some boys are sitting …</gap>
<sentence>What can make your teachers angry?</sentence>
<exercise>C2 L 1/4 a) On the first day of school Rajiv takes his new mobile phone with him. Listen to what he records with it. Find out what happens to him.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Speculate on what happens next to George and Rajiv.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Read how Mr Jackson, their teacher, and Mrs Edwards, the head teacher, talk to George and Rajiv. Were you right in b)? P15</exercise>
<gap>I think they must …</gap>
<gap>I guess they …</gap>
<sentence>Mrs Edwards: Rajiv, George, please sit down.</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Jackson told me what you did in his history lesson.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: I’m really sorry, Mr Jackson.</sentence>
<sentence>It was a stupid mistake.</sentence>
<sentence>Mrs Edwards: The school rules are very clear.</sentence>
<sentence>Leave your mobiles at home or leave them in your bags.</sentence>
<sentence>But you recorded parts of the lesson.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m really disappointed in you.</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Jackson: You should learn about British history in my lessons, not about mobile phones.</sentence>
<sentence>That was unacceptable.</sentence>
<sentence>Why didn’t you leave your mobile at home?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: No, really.</sentence>
<sentence>We were a bit bored and it’s the first day back at school.</sentence>
<sentence>So we had that stupid idea.</sentence>
<sentence>But it wasn’t just George, it was my fault, too.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: We’re very sorry.</sentence>
<sentence>It won’t happen again.</sentence>
<sentence>All the others talked about their exciting summer holidays, but I stayed at home all the time.</sentence>
<sentence>Mrs Edwards: It’s good that you both see that you did something wrong.</sentence>
<sentence>But I’m going to keep the mobile for the moment and I’m going to phone your parents.</sentence>
<sentence>George: It was my mistake, really.</sentence>
<sentence>I asked Rajiv to give me his mobile and I recorded the lesson.</sentence>
<sentence>It was just a bit of fun.</sentence>
<sentence>George: The Romans and the Celts?</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Jackson: I don’t think so.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe you wanted to put them online.</sentence>
<sentence>Mrs Edwards: No, you can’t.</sentence>
<sentence>Work hard on your presentation.</sentence>
<sentence>You may go now.</sentence>
<exercise>16 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='8'>
<chapter>1/C</chapter>
<exercise>C3 a) Look at C2 again and say how the people feel.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Look at C2 again.</exercise>
<gap>sad disappointed angry happy very angry sorry …</gap>
<gap>that … because …</gap>
<exercise>∙ … someone feels sorry for what he/she did</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write down how you can feel when your … … teacher gives you a lot of/no extra homework … teacher asks you to write something on the board … teacher talks to your parents … teacher is late … classmates are noisy</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Look at C2 again and complete the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 The school rules say that pupils must … 2 Mr Jackson wants to know why … 3 George thinks it was just …</exercise>
<exercise>4 Mrs Edwards is going to … 5 George and Rajiv must … 6 George wants to know if they can …</exercise>
<exercise>C4 George calls his mother to tell her what happened. Work with a partner. Complete the dialogue – one of you is Mrs Lambraki and the other one is George. Add phrases from C3b) where possible. LiF 1R: Simple present, p. 133/134; 2R: Simple past, p. 135/136  WB C6, p. 13</exercise>
<sentence>George: Hi, Mum.</sentence>
<gap>happened at school today. Mrs Lambraki: Oh no, what did you …? George: I didn’t do anything. It was Rajiv. He …</gap>
<gap>And then I … Mrs Lambraki: Why …? George: Because we were bored. Mrs Lambraki: Oh George. Now what … next?</gap>
<exercise>C5 v Extra a) Present your dialogues from C4 to another pair. Decide which of the two dialogues is better. Say why.</exercise>
<gap>George: Well, we had to go to Mrs Edwards. Mr Jackson was there, too. What … when</gap>
<gap>they called you? Mrs Lambraki: … And what …? George: Rajiv and I have to prepare a presentation about the Romans and Celts in</gap>
<gap>Britain. … Mrs Lambraki: George, I’m really …! …</gap>
<exercise>b) Present some good dialogues in class and discuss what makes them good dialogues. Think of what they are about and the language they use.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventeen 17</footnote>
<gap>that …</gap>
<exercise>∙ … someone does not like something</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … someone knows that he/she did</exercise>
<exercise>c) v Choose</exercise>
</page>
<page id='9'>
<chapter>1/C</chapter>
<exercise>C6 A few days later George and Rajiv write notes to each other in their English lesson. a) Put them in the right order. What are the notes about? Reading, p. 125  WB C7, C8, p. 14</exercise>
<sentence>Hi, Rajiv.</sentence>
<sentence>What do you think about what Mr Jackson said?</sentence>
<sentence>OK. Maybe we can make the presentation a little bit more interesting than a normal lesson.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe Charlie can help us.</sentence>
<sentence>You’re right.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s ask Charlie for help.</sentence>
<sentence>He’s good at history.</sentence>
<sentence>We can talk about it at lunch.</sentence>
<sentence>No way, George.</sentence>
<sentence>We should show him that we are not as stupid as he thinks we are.</sentence>
<sentence>Romans and Celts?</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t know anything about them.</sentence>
<sentence>They both sound boring to me.</sentence>
<sentence>Good idea, but we could ask Mr Jackson for some ideas, too.</sentence>
<gap>It was better than I thought. I think it was good that we said sorry again. He wasn’t as angry as last lesson. But a presentation about Romans and Celts … not so sure.</gap>
<sentence>That’s true.</sentence>
<sentence>They sound really boring.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s go to the library after lunch.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe we can find something that is more interesting than ‘Roman cities in England’.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Look at the notes again and complete the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Rajiv thinks that Mr Jackson wasn’t … 2 The boys think that the Romans and Celts … 3 They want to go to the library to …</exercise>
<exercise>c) Look at the notes again. Make a grid to collect phrases (how to agree/how to disagree). Then add more words/phrases to the grid. P10</exercise>
<exercise>C7 L 1/5</exercise>
<exercise>4 Rajiv doesn’t want to ask Mr Jackson</exercise>
<gap>because … 5 The boys think that Charlie … because …</gap>
<exercise>d) Look at your grid. Mark phrases you can only use with friends but not with teachers.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Listen to Charlie’s tips and note down the tip you like best. Say why. P13</exercise>
<gap>Charlie’s tip for/about… is my favourite because …</gap>
<exercise>b) Listen again and complete the sentences with as … as … or … than … . LiF 3: Steigerung von Adjektiven, p. 137/138  WB C9, p. 15</exercise>
<exercise>1 A presentation about Romans is … one about Celts. 2 It is … to find material on the Romans … on the Celts. 3 The BBC websites often have … information … other websites and some books. 4 In the Horrible Histories books you can find pictures that are … pictures from</exercise>
<gap>normal history books. 5 A presentation with those pictures is … without the pictures. 6 But maybe Mr Jackson doesn’t find it … the pupils.</gap>
<exercise>18 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='10'>
<chapter>1/C</chapter>
<exercise>C8 L 1/6 George and Rajiv are in the library to prepare their history presentation when there is an announcement over the PA system.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Listen to the announcement. b) What do you think about what the pupils did?</exercise>
<sentence>What does the head teacher say?</sentence>
<exercise>C9 Target task v " Project Portfolio P9</exercise>
<exercise>P17  WB C10, p. 15</exercise>
<gap>I think/don’t think it’s OK if you …</gap>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<gap>What they did was stupid/silly/clever/cool/… because …</gap>
<sentence>Look at pp.</sentence>
<exercise>1 Work in groups of three. Choose one role and read your role card.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What kind of person is he/she? ∙ What does he/she say?</exercise>
<exercise>2 Plan your dialogue. Use words and phrases from C3b) and C6).</exercise>
<exercise>∙ is not very clever or polite ∙ doesn’t understand why the ∙ thinks the sweets at school are too expensive so that pupils want to buy sweets from him.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Present your dialogue to another group.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Did the group use the language from C3b) and C6? Speaking 2, p. 127</exercise>
<gap>Support Giving feedback: Patrick was very good as Salman/Matt because he … I don’t think Vanessa acted like the role card says because …</gap>
<exercise>∙ is very angry that the boys started their own</exercise>
<exercise>∙ wants to find out about the details</exercise>
<exercise>∙ understands that he did something wrong but doesn’t see why selling</exercise>
<exercise>∙ saved the money for a new computer.</exercise>
<gap>Jessica did not ask many questions as Mrs Edwards, but the role card says … Lisa’s questions as Mrs Edwards were very good because she asked about … I liked Jens as Salman/Matt because he said that it was …’s fault, too.</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words nineteen 19</footnote>
<exercise>∙ How does he/she feel?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ is always in trouble</exercise>
<exercise>∙ wants to punish them for what</exercise>
<exercise>∙ is a good, polite pupil</exercise>
<sentence>Give feedback.</sentence>
<exercise>∙ Were the characters convincing?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='11'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P1 Words: holidays a) Find out the holiday words. Write them in your exercise book.</exercise>
<exercise>1 caebh 4 nnsuy 2 rdstpoca 5 ingghtsisee</exercise>
<exercise>P2 Words: positive/neutral/negative adjectives Complete the grid.</exercise>
<listing>great · OK · fantastic · boring · alright · wonderful · exciting · really nice · terrible · good · so-so · brilliant</listing>
<exercise>3 caitsuse 6 nivesour great so-so …</exercise>
<exercise>b) Choose five more holiday words and make a quiz for your partner like in a).</exercise>
<exercise>P3 Revision: simple past LiF 2R: Simple past, p. 135 Gillian did a lot of jobs in the holidays because her mum Gillian,</exercise>
<exercise>c) Find phrases to talk about holidays. at a hotel camping</exercise>
<exercise>a) Look at Gillian’s list. Write down what she did. Example: Gillian … shopping. She …</exercise>
<exercise>b) What did you do in your holidays? What didn’t you do? Write down six sentences. Example: I went shopping but I didn’t …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ go shopping (see shopping list) ∙ take out the rubbish ∙ bake a cake for the weekend</exercise>
<sentence>Thanks!</sentence>
<exercise>P4 Revision: simple past (questions with question words) LiF 2R: Simple past, p. 136</exercise>
<sentence>You are just back from your dream holiday.</sentence>
<sentence>Work with a partner.</sentence>
<sentence>He/She wants to know everything about it.</sentence>
<sentence>What did you do?</sentence>
<gap>I went swimming/ had ice cream every day/ played beach volleyball/ met a film star/…</gap>
<sentence>Where did you stay?</sentence>
<gap>I went to New York/the North Pole/… I stayed with my cousin/... ...</gap>
<sentence>What was the weather like?</sentence>
<sentence>How long did you stay?</sentence>
<gap>One day/week/… Ten weeks/…</gap>
<gap>I stayed in a five star hotel/ a holiday apartment/ with Mickey Mouse/…</gap>
<gap>It was sunny/ really cold/…</gap>
<exercise>20 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ tidy up your room</exercise>
<exercise>∙ phone Grandma</exercise>
<exercise>∙ clean the bathroom</exercise>
</page>
<page id='12'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P5 Revision: simple past (questions and short answers) LiF 2R: Simple past, p. 136 a) Work with a partner. Ask and answer questions about the friends from Camden.</exercise>
<sentence>Did the friends make a cake for Charlie?</sentence>
<sentence>Yes, they did.</sentence>
<gap>…</gap>
<exercise>b) Find five more questions for your partner.</exercise>
<exercise>P6 Words: connectives LiF 4: Verbindung von Sätzen, p. 138 Use the connectives (e.g. because, so, ... ) to link the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>P7 Words: writing a story S 1, L 1/7 Direct speech 1 makes stories more interesting.</exercise>
<sentence>George took the compass.</sentence>
<sentence>Brady wanted to help him.</sentence>
<sentence>But be careful – it’s boring if you always use the word say .</sentence>
<exercise>a) What are these words? You can use them instead of 2 say .</exercise>
<listing>/ ɑː s ĸ / · / ˈʃ a ʊ t / · / ˈɑː ns ə / · / ĸɔː l / · / l ɑː f / · / əˈɡ ri ː / · / tel /</listing>
<exercise>b) Listen to the CD and check your words.</exercise>
<exercise>1 direct speech – direkte Rede 2 instead of – statt</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words twenty-one 21</footnote>
</page>
<page id='13'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P8 Words: adjectives Nice is a nice word – but not if nice is the only adjective you use in your story!</exercise>
<exercise>a) Find other words for nice . You can use your dictionary.</exercise>
<gap>Example: pretty, amazing, lovely, …</gap>
<exercise>b) Caroline’s classmate Hamida wrote a report about her holidays. Copy her text, but use other adjectives for nice .</exercise>
<sentence>Madagascar is a nice island in the Indian Ocean.</sentence>
<sentence>My sister and I went swimming in the sea every day while many nice fi sh.</sentence>
<sentence>There were pink ones, blue ones, green The food there was nice.</sentence>
<sentence>We ate coconuts and papayas.</sentence>
<sentence>There were so many the town.</sentence>
<sentence>It was nice!</sentence>
<sentence>We also tried some Madagascan vanilla.</sentence>
<sentence>It was very nice.</sentence>
<sentence>We had a nice holiday!</sentence>
<exercise>P9 Words: giving feedback Copy the grid and write down the statements in the right groups:</exercise>
<gap>words grammar structure …</gap>
<exercise>1 It was good that you looked up some words</exercise>
<sentence>Don’t forget the -s after he, she, it .</sentence>
<exercise>5 You should check the word order of</exercise>
<exercise>22 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<sentence>It was very hot.</sentence>
<gap>ones … all the colours of the rainbow!</gap>
<sentence>The people of Madagascar are also very nice.</sentence>
<sentence>On the last day we were very sad to leave.</sentence>
</page>
<page id='14'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P10 Words: agreeing/disagreeing a) Match the sentences that mean more or less the same 1 .</exercise>
<exercise>1 I absolutely agree. 2 That’s nonsense. 3 I can understand that point, but there are other things you should think about.</exercise>
<sentence>A That’s really silly.</sentence>
<sentence>B I think the same.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Read some rules from different British schools. Then say what you think of them. Say why you think so, too. You can use phrases from a), for example.</exercise>
<exercise>1 more or less the same – mehr oder weniger das gleiche 2 quietly in line – ruhig in einer Reihe</exercise>
<exercise>1. Pupils should wear school uniform. 2. Pupils should wait quietly in line 2 in front of the</exercise>
<sentence>All people at school should respect each other.</sentence>
<sentence>Pupils mustn’t be late.</sentence>
<exercise>P11 Comparison of adjectives LiF 3: Steigerung von Adjektiven, p. 137/138 Here are some activities you can do at Beam House. Compare 1 the activities. What are your favourite I think … activities? is … than …</exercise>
<exercise>1 compare – vergleichen</exercise>
<listing>dangerous · boring · exciting · interesting · silly · difficult · fascinating</listing>
<gap>… is my favourite activity because …</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words twenty-three 23</footnote>
</page>
<page id='15'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P12 Revision: simple past (questions) LiF 2R: Simple past, p. 136</exercise>
<exercise>1. Form the questions that go with these answers.</exercise>
<sentence>I only saw Mr Jackson when it was too late to put the mobile phone away.</sentence>
<sentence>’ When ???</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Jackson?</sentence>
<exercise>2. You can check your answers on</exercise>
<sentence>You need help?</sentence>
<sentence>’ Do a), then b).</sentence>
<sentence>You can do it?</sentence>
<sentence>’ Do b).</sentence>
<gap>George and I had a meeting with the head teacher because Mr Jackson told her about the mobile phone. ’ Why ??? a meeting …?</gap>
<exercise>a) Rajiv’s classmates want to find out more about his mobile. What are their questions?</exercise>
<exercise>1 Where … you get it? – I bought it in Oxford Street. 2 How much … it …? – It cost £50. 3 Why … you … that one? – I chose this one because it’s cool! 4 Why … take it to school? – I took it to school because I thought you would like to see it.</exercise>
<exercise>b) George and Rajiv are not the only ones who got into trouble on the first day after the holidays. What did Mrs Edwards ask Dylan?</exercise>
<exercise>1 What … you …? – I drew a picture on my desk. 2 What …? – I drew a picture of Mrs Brogden. 3 You should take part in the lesson. Why …? – Because it was so boring. 4 What …? – I said sorry to Mrs Brogden and that I will clean the desk in the lunch break.</exercise>
<exercise>P13 Comparison of adjectives LiF 3: Steigerung von Adjektiven, p. 137/138 Compare the two pictures of a village 1 in Roman Britain.</exercise>
<sentence>What is different?</sentence>
<listing>big · colourful · dark · tall · happy · long</listing>
<exercise>1 village – Dorf</exercise>
<exercise>24 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='16'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P14 Words: weather S 2, L 1/8 Wordbank Weather, p. 149 Draw a picture of Great Britain like this: Then listen to the weather report. Use symbols to note down the information about the weather. Add information on temperatures, too.</exercise>
<exercise>1 weather report –</exercise>
<sentence>Are the statements true or false?</sentence>
<sentence>Correct the false sentences.</sentence>
<exercise>1 Pupils mustn’t bring mobiles to William Ellis School. 2 Rajiv brought the mobile to be more interesting to the other pupils. 3 George says he didn’t do anything wrong. 4 Mr Jackson is afraid that the boys could put the video clips on the Internet. 5 Both Rajiv and George had the idea about the mobile phone. 6 Mrs Edwards gives Rajiv the mobile phone back.</exercise>
<exercise>P16 Words: trouble at school a) Look at the pictures. Write down what the pupils in Rajiv and George’s class do wrong.</exercise>
<exercise>1 2 3</exercise>
<exercise>4 not wear · forget · take … to school · listen to … · not clean</exercise>
<exercise>b) What could the boys say to explain their mistakes? Use the words and phrases from C3b (page 17). Your ideas can be funny, too.</exercise>
<sentence>I’m really sorry.</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t wear my school tie because my dog ate it.</sentence>
<exercise>P17 Sounds S 3, L 1/9 a) Listen to the words and repeat them. Then make a</exercise>
<gap>[   t ] [d    ɪ d ] liked …</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words twenty-fi ve 25</footnote>
</page>
<page id='17'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>5 Or maybe you are more interested in wildlife? There are many ideal places for</exercise>
<sentence>Islands are also a fabulous place to see seals and even go whale spotting.</sentence>
<sentence>For those who love history, Great Britain has many special places of interest.</sentence>
<sentence>Are you keen on futuristic places?</sentence>
<sentence>Who wants to go to school in the holidays?</sentence>
<exercise>20 university college of Christchurch.</exercise>
<exercise>1 a) Look at the pictures and read the texts. Which of the holiday ideas is most attractive to you? Say why.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Have a class survey. What are the top three in class?</exercise>
<exercise>2 Note down the places in a list and work with the map at the front of your book to find the places. Test your partner.</exercise>
<exercise>1 coastline – Küstenlinie 2 scenery – Landschaft 3 wave – Welle 4 deer – Rotwild 5 badger – Dachs 6 druid – Druide, Zauberer 7 thermal spa – Thermalbad 8 ancient Romans – (die) alten Römer 9 medieval – mittelalterlich 10 artificial biosphere – künstliche Biosphäre 11 jungle – Dschungel</exercise>
<sentence>Where is Cornwall?</sentence>
<sentence>It’s in the north/ east/south/west.</sentence>
<gap>… is on/near the (south/west/...) coast.</gap>
<exercise>12 playwright – Schriftsteller 5</exercise>
<exercise>26 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='18'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words twenty-seven 27</footnote>
</page>
<page id='19'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>O1 Reading, p. 125</exercise>
<sentence>Rajiv and George are working on their history presentation for Mr Jackson’s class.</sentence>
<sentence>Look at the comic about Romans and Celts on this page.</sentence>
<sentence>Choose the best title for the comic and explain your choice.</sentence>
<sentence>A How the Celts and the Romans changed Britain B What the Romans built in Britain.</sentence>
<exercise>1 2 3</exercise>
<exercise>1. The Celts came to Britain in around 500 BC and took control of the country. They lived in tribes and often fought against others for land.</exercise>
<exercise>2. The Celts were not only good fighters, but also good farmers. They usually lived in round houses, often on the top of hills.</exercise>
<exercise>3. In 55 and 54 BC, Julius Caesar and his army landed in Britain. However, the Romans felt that the Celts and the British weather were too much for them and left.</exercise>
<exercise>4 5 6</exercise>
<exercise>4. In AD 43, the Romans invaded Britain again and this time they stayed in Britain and took control of the south of England. They hoped for better trade with the Celts.</exercise>
<exercise>5. The Romans brought a lot of new things with them: they built roads, temples, baths and stone houses and they brought new entertainment, such as gladiator fighting and wine.</exercise>
<exercise>6. Not all the Celts were happy with the Romans. The Celtic queen Boudicca and her men fought against the Romans in AD 60 and burned down some cities like London. In the end, however, the Romans won.</exercise>
<exercise>28 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='20'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>7 8 9</exercise>
<exercise>O2 a) Read the captions again and find the right words in the text: A a group of people who have the same language and religion and usually live in one area B to go to a country and fight C when people buy and sell goods</exercise>
<exercise>b) Start a timeline for Britain’s early history.</exercise>
<exercise>500 BC 55/54 BC</exercise>
<gap>The Celts came to Britain and …</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<exercise>O3 S 4, L 1/10 Listening, p. 124 a) Follow the steps to write captions for pictures 7–9 in O1.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Look at the pictures 7–9 in the comic again. 2 Listen to a podcast about the Romans in Britain. Take notes for each picture. 3 Use your notes to write captions.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Add more information to your timeline from O2b.</exercise>
<gap>Du kannst schon viel auf Englisch verstehen und ausdrücken. Du kannst … 3 über deine Ferien sprechen 3 deinen Mitschülerinnen und Mitschülern Rückmeldung geben</gap>
<exercise>3 ein Ereignis nacherzählen 3 Dinge vergleichen 3 das Ende einer Geschichte verfassen 3 Gefühle beschreiben 3 Abneigungen und Missfallen äußern</exercise>
<exercise>3 etwas vorschlagen, zustimmen und ablehnen  WB Portfolio-Fragebogen Theme 1</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words twenty-nine 29</footnote>
</page>
<page id='21'>
<chapter>2/A</chapter>
<sentence>Gung Hei Fat Choi!</sentence>
<sentence>That is ’Happy New Year!’ in Chinese.</sentence>
<sentence>Then we clean our houses, decorate them with fruit and flowers and put up red and gold banners with short poems in the house because they bring good luck.</sentence>
<sentence>Parents give their children red envelopes with money in them and we eat special food like dumplings or rice pudding.</sentence>
<sentence>Many people watch the famous dragon dance because we Chinese believe that dragons are friendly.</sentence>
<sentence>We also have fireworks that make a lot of noise to keep the monsters and bad luck away.</sentence>
<gap>Diwali A1 a) Think of three special days that In October or November Hindu people celebrate Diwali – you celebrate in your family (e.g. the Festival of Lights. My family and I often go to Diwali in Christmas). Make notes on how Trafalgar Square . Many groups dance there and perform you celebrate these days. stories about Diwali. Diwali is also a celebration for Think about decorations, food, Lakshmi, the goddess of good luck and wealth. We put guests, clothes, … diyas – small lamps – and candles around our houses to Wordbank Festivals, p. 150 help the goddess Lakshmi find her way into people’s houses. We also give each other presents for Diwali, send We always invite … I don’t wear my normal clothes, cards and eat a lot of delicious sweets and cakes. But the best thing about Diwali is the fireworks! but …</gap>
<exercise>b) Talk about these special days with a partner. P1</exercise>
<exercise>c) Make a list of the special days and celebrations in class. When do they take place over the year?  WB A1, p. 23</exercise>
<exercise>d) v Extra: Do you know any special celebrations in Britain or other English-speaking countries? Say what you know about them and add them to the list from c).</exercise>
<exercise>30 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='22'>
<chapter>2/A</chapter>
<sentence>Remember, remember, the fifth of November!</sentence>
<sentence>But their plan did not work.</sentence>
<sentence>When people found out that the king was safe, they lit bonfires to celebrate.</sentence>
<sentence>It is now a tradition to celebrate this event with fireworks and a bonfire.</sentence>
<sentence>In the past, children made dummies of Guy Fawkes to ask people for ‘a penny for the Guy’.</sentence>
<sentence>As it is usually cold in November, we have food that keeps us warm, like baked potatoes.</sentence>
<sentence>But marshmallows and toffee apples are everyone’s favourite food on Bonfire Night!</sentence>
<exercise>A2 The pupils at William Ellis present some celebrations for a school project. a) Mini jigsaw: Work in groups of three. Each group member reads about one of the festivals. Copy the grid and fill it in for ‘your’ festival. Mini jigsaw, p. 130 Reading, p. 125</exercise>
<gap>Chinese New Year Diwali Bonfi re Night When do people celebrate? What/Why do people celebrate? What do people do/wear/…?</gap>
<exercise>b) Present what you know about the celebrations to your group. Complete your grid with information about the other celebrations.</exercise>
<gap>Support … is a holiday that … celebrate every year at … The reason why they celebrate … is that … It is a holiday that is famous for …</gap>
<exercise>c) Imagine you have the chance to take part in one of these celebrations. Which one would you choose? Why? P2, P3, P13  WB A2–A4, p. 23-25</exercise>
<gap>celebrations, you should try … What is typical of that holiday is that …</gap>
<exercise>A3 Target task v " Project Portfolio</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<sentence>Work with a partner.</sentence>
<sentence>Design a page for a ‘special days’ calendar.</sentence>
<exercise>∙ a special day that you celebrate in your family or home town or</exercise>
<sentence>Hogmanay, St Patrick’s Day, Notting Hill Carnival.</sentence>
<sentence>Find out as much as you can about your festival.</sentence>
<exercise>∙ Plan your text so that your page answers ∙ If you use information from the Internet, make sure that your text is easy to read</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Include photos/pictures.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-one 31</footnote>
<exercise>∙ a special day that British or other English-speaking people</exercise>
</page>
<page id='23'>
<chapter>2/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 L 1/11 Caroline and Emma are watching a video. It is of a celebration they had last year. Listen to the sounds. Which celebration is it? How did you find out? Listening, p. 124  WB B1, p. 26</exercise>
<exercise>B2 L 1/12 a) Look at the card on Charlie’s desk. What is it about?</exercise>
<exercise>b) There is a message on Charlie’s mobile phone. Listen to it and find out what his problem is.</exercise>
<exercise>B3 L 1/13 a) What do you have to organize before you can have a party? Wordbank Festivals, p. 150</exercise>
<exercise>b) Close your books. Listen and find out what the girls are talking about.  WB B2, p. 26</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline, Emma and Gillian are in Caroline’s room.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Let me just check our list.</sentence>
<sentence>OK, I’m going to ask Mum and Dad to buy some fireworks for us.</sentence>
<sentence>Some rockets and some bangers, of course.</sentence>
<sentence>George is crazy about bangers – the noisier, the better.</sentence>
<sentence>And we should get some sparklers for everyone.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: I’m going to go shopping with Mum on Friday so I can bring whatever you like.</sentence>
<gap>the boys … so let them have their bangers. Gillian: Really, Emma. I didn’t know you were</gap>
<sentence>Caroline: Great idea!</sentence>
<sentence>But I already gave Charlie his invitation today.</sentence>
<exercise>15 you know. about it. Now who else are we going to invite?</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline: Just stop it, Gillian.</sentence>
<sentence>We all know who that particular person is!</sentence>
<gap>people I don’t like … Emma: And I don’t want to have the same people all the time.</gap>
<exercise>20 we’re going to have a party next weekend, Gillian: I think the same people and that</exercise>
<sentence>Gillian: OK, Miss Bossyboots.</sentence>
<sentence>So, what food are we going to have?</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: Stop it, Gillian!</sentence>
<sentence>Mrs Lambraki: Caroline!</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie’s on the phone.</sentence>
<exercise>25 apples. And I can ask Mum to make some of Caroline: Charlie? Are you sure he doesn’t want</exercise>
<sentence>What about you?</sentence>
<exercise>32 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='24'>
<chapter>2/B</chapter>
<exercise>B4 Read the dialogue in B3 again. Say how the girls feel and what they do. P9  WB B3, p. 27</exercise>
<gap>she thinks of … she tells … she remembers … the other girls … Gillian … Caroline … …</gap>
<exercise>B5 L 1/14 a) Close your books. Listen to Caroline and Charlie. How does Caroline react to Charlie’s news?</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline: Hi, Caroline speaking.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Hi, Caroline, it’s Charlie.</sentence>
<sentence>Thanks again for the invitation.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s really great, but there’s a bit of a problem.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Oh no!</sentence>
<sentence>That’s awful.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Yeah, I think he’ll invite George, you, of course, and Emma and Gillian.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe Rick and a few others.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: That’s a great idea.</sentence>
<sentence>What a mess!</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Yeah, well.</sentence>
<sentence>I hope you’ll sort that problem out.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Of course not.</sentence>
<sentence>But maybe we can think of something.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma and Gillian are here, so I’ll talk to them first.</sentence>
<sentence>Will you be at home later?</sentence>
<exercise>b) Complete the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Charlie hopes that Caroline will … 2 Charlie knows that he won’t …</exercise>
<sentence>Charlie: Yeah, you can call me here.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: OK then.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s talk later.</sentence>
<sentence>Bye.</sentence>
<exercise>3 Caroline hopes that she and the other girls will … 4 Caroline says that she will …  WB B4, B5, p. 27, 28</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-three 33</footnote>
</page>
<page id='25'>
<chapter>2/B</chapter>
<exercise>B6 Grammar card: will future You already know the going to future, but Caroline and Charlie use another tense to talk about the future – the will future . Start a grammar card for the will future .</exercise>
<exercise>1 Look at B5 on page 33 again. Note down examples of positive and negative sentences and questions.</exercise>
<exercise>2 How do you form the will future ? Check LiF 6 on page 139.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Look at B5 again and find phrases that introduce sentences with the will future . Example: I’m sure he’ll invite the same people as us. Now check LiF 6 on page 139 again. When do you use the will future ? P10  WB B6, p. 29</exercise>
<exercise>B7 a) What will happen next? Look at the pictures and write down if Caroline and Rajiv will do those things or not. Example: I guess Caroline will be angry and disappointed.</exercise>
<gap>I think she’ll ask Rajiv if … LiF 6: will future, p. 139</gap>
<gap>I guess she/he/they won’t … because …</gap>
<gap>I don’t think she/he/they will … because …</gap>
<gap>Maybe she/he/they … because …</gap>
<exercise>b) Round Robin: Work in groups. What will happen next? Write a short statement. Round Robin, p. 130  WB B7, B8, p. 30</exercise>
<exercise>34 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='26'>
<chapter>2/B</chapter>
<exercise>B8 a) Read Caroline’s email to Rajiv. Were you right in B7b)? Reading, p. 125</exercise>
<sentence>Hi Rajiv, How are you?</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t know if you already know, but we’ve got a problem.</sentence>
<sentence>Bonfire Night.</sentence>
<sentence>But now Charlie tells me that you would like to have a Diwali party on the same night.</sentence>
<sentence>I guess you’ll probably invite the same people as us.</sentence>
<sentence>I talked to Emma and Gillian about it and we’ve got an idea, but I’m not sure that you’ll like it.</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t you think it would be a good idea to have just one party on that night?</sentence>
<sentence>Why don’t we mix Bonfire Night and Diwali?</sentence>
<sentence>There are fireworks for both festivals.</sentence>
<sentence>What about one big party at our house?</sentence>
<sentence>We’ve got enough room and Mum and Dad say it’s no problem.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s just celebrate in one place.</sentence>
<sentence>I hope you won’t be upset about it.</sentence>
<sentence>Please call or email back soon.</sentence>
<exercise>b) What are Caroline’s arguments for a Diwali and Bonfire Night party? Note them down.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Look at the structure of Caroline’s email. Where can you find the following parts?</exercise>
<exercise>1 Saying hello 2 Introducing the email with a friendly question/sentence 3 Explaining why you are writing the email 4 Making suggestions 5 Finishing the email with a friendly statement 6 Saying goodbye P4, P5  WB B9, p. 31</exercise>
<exercise>d) Find words and phrases for each part of the email. Example: Hi; How … Then collect more words and phrases in class.</exercise>
<exercise>B9 Target task v Portfolio Imagine you are Rajiv. Answer Caroline’s email.</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<exercise>1 Before you start writing, decide how Rajiv feels about Caroline’s idea. What would he like to do? Note down your ideas.</exercise>
<exercise>2 When you write the email, follow the structure from B8c).</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the will future when necessary. Wordbank Festivals, p. 150 Writing, p. 128 LiF 6: will future, p. 139</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-fi ve 35</footnote>
<exercise>∙ Use phrases from B8d) to write your email.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='27'>
<chapter>2/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1</exercise>
<gap>What makes a good party? There is good food. …</gap>
<exercise>C2 L 1/15 a) Read the dialogue between Caroline and George. Find out what they and their friends expect of the party.</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline: Well, Emma’s coming, of course, and Gillian.</sentence>
<sentence>And then some girls from my class, Sophie and Hamida.</sentence>
<sentence>They’re really looking forward to it because there’ll be boys there!</sentence>
<sentence>They haven’t got any brothers, you see!</sentence>
<sentence>If you like, I’ll invite Denah, too.</sentence>
<sentence>George: If you invite her, I’ll never speak to you again!</sentence>
<sentence>If she comes, she’ll follow me around all the time and she always wants to talk George: So what do you want me to do?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv thinks it’s really funny, If I tell him about Emma, he’ll probably be but it’s just embarrassing.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: OK, OK, don’t worry.</sentence>
<sentence>So which boys are coming?</sentence>
<sentence>George: Well, Rajiv, of course.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s his party, too.</sentence>
<sentence>And Charlie will be there.They can’t wait for the fireworks!</sentence>
<sentence>I must tell Dad to buy more bangers.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Very funny!</sentence>
<sentence>But are only two boys coming, George?</sentence>
<sentence>That’s not many.</sentence>
<sentence>Did Rajiv ask Rick?</sentence>
<sentence>George: Well, he asked him and Holden, but they’re not sure.</sentence>
<sentence>Alexandra Palace to see the fireworks.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: But Rick must come!</sentence>
<sentence>If he doesn’t come, Emma will be so unhappy.</sentence>
<sentence>She’s got a big crush on him and she’s so excited about the party.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: That’s true.</sentence>
<sentence>But why don’t you talk to Rick and Holden and tell them that they can come after the fireworks.</sentence>
<sentence>If the party’s good, there’ll still be some people here.</sentence>
<sentence>George: What do you mean – if the party’s good?</sentence>
<sentence>Of course it’ll be good.</sentence>
<gap>dogs and … Caroline: But that’s only part of the fun, George. It’s not so important how much food and drink we have. I’m really worried that not many boys will come. My friends can’t wait to meet your friends. They’ll be really disappointed if there aren’t many boys! Please talk to Holden and Rick on Monday.</gap>
<exercise>∙ … George will feel if Denah comes to the party. Why? ∙ … Rajiv and Charlie will feel if there are not enough bangers. ∙ … the girls will feel if the boys don’t come. P11  WB C1, p. 32</exercise>
<exercise>36 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>b) Say how …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … Emma will feel if Rick doesn’t come. Why?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … Rick will feel if George tells him about Emma.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='28'>
<chapter>2/C</chapter>
<exercise>C3 L 1/16 a) Listen to George’s conversation with Rick and Holden. Will they come to the party? Listening p. 124</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and make a list of reasons for</exercise>
<exercise>∙ going to Rajiv and Caroline’s party</exercise>
<exercise>c) v Extra: What would you do? Say why.</exercise>
<exercise>C4 Grammar detective: conditional clauses, type 1</exercise>
<sentence>Will future or simple present ?</sentence>
<sentence>Can you solve the problem?</sentence>
<exercise>1 Look at this sentence: If you invite her, I’ll never speak to you again.</exercise>
<exercise>C5</exercise>
<exercise>2 Find more examples from the dialogue</exercise>
<sentence>Start a grammar card.</sentence>
<sentence>Mrs Lambraki is worried about the party preparations.</sentence>
<sentence>So she talks to Caroline.</sentence>
<sentence>Work with a partner.</sentence>
<sentence>Ask and answer Mrs Lambraki’s questions.</sentence>
<listing>help you · put up a tent · make some sandwiches · show them a film · run to the shop and buy more · ask our friends to be quiet · put him in George’s room</listing>
<sentence>What will we do if the party is too noisy?</sentence>
<sentence>What will we do if we don’t have enough drinks?</sentence>
<sentence>What will happen if the weather is bad?</sentence>
<gap>…</gap>
<sentence>What will happen if I don’t have enough time?</sentence>
<sentence>What will we do if the dog gets scared of the fireworks?</sentence>
<exercise>C6 v Extra</exercise>
<sentence>What will happen if your friends don’t like the food?</sentence>
<sentence>Work in groups.</sentence>
<gap>LiF 7: Bedingungssätze, Typ 1, p. 140 If I travel around the world, …</gap>
<sentence>If I win a lot of money, I’ll travel around the world.</sentence>
<gap>I’ll go to …</gap>
<gap>If I go to …</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-seven 37</footnote>
<exercise>∙ going to the fireworks at Alexandra Palace</exercise>
</page>
<page id='29'>
<chapter>2/C</chapter>
<exercise>C7 a) Look at the pictures and say what happens at the party.</exercise>
<exercise>1 2 Mum gave me some food to bring.</exercise>
<sentence>And I’ve got bangers!</sentence>
<exercise>3 4 When can we start the fireworks, Mr Lambraki?</exercise>
<sentence>Well, is everyone here?</sentence>
<sentence>Emma and I have made a guy.</sentence>
<sentence>Where’s Rick?</sentence>
<sentence>Isn’t he coming?</sentence>
<sentence>George said he might come.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m sure he’ll be here soon.</sentence>
<exercise>5 6</exercise>
<sentence>Let’s just wait a little bit longer, Dad.</sentence>
<sentence>I think some of George’s friends are still coming, aren’t they, George?</sentence>
<gap>sure …</gap>
<sentence>Mmm!</sentence>
<sentence>These samosas are great, Rajiv.</sentence>
<sentence>Did you make them?</sentence>
<sentence>No, his mum did!</sentence>
<sentence>Come on, Rajiv, let’s light some sparklers.</sentence>
<exercise>7 8 Well, she’ll feel happier</exercise>
<sentence>If Rick doesn’t come soon, I’ll die.</sentence>
<sentence>What’s wrong with you, Emma?</sentence>
<sentence>Here you are, Emma!</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t want your stupid sparkler, Rajiv!</sentence>
<exercise>9 10 I don‘t believe Is that</exercise>
<sentence>What have I done?</sentence>
<sentence>Come inside, everyone!</sentence>
<sentence>This is dangerous!</sentence>
<sentence>What a noise!</sentence>
<sentence>You‘ve spoilt the party for everyone, Emma!</sentence>
<exercise>38 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<sentence>Hi, everyone!</sentence>
<sentence>Wow!</sentence>
<sentence>Oh no!</sentence>
</page>
<page id='30'>
<chapter>2/C</chapter>
<exercise>b) Match the captions to the pictures.</exercise>
<sentence>George is really angry with Emma and so she starts to cry.</sentence>
<sentence>This party is really horrible for Emma.</sentence>
<sentence>The boys don’t understand why Emma isn’t having fun.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline isn’t very pleased that Hamida seems to be too friendly towards Rajiv.</sentence>
<sentence>The sparkler lands in the box of fireworks and they all start going off at once.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline feels very nervous because Emma is so unhappy.</sentence>
<sentence>She hopes Rick will come soon.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma is unhappy.</sentence>
<sentence>She still hopes that Rick will come although it’s getting quite late.</sentence>
<sentence>The friends eat hot dogs and samosas around the bonfire.</sentence>
<sentence>The boys can’t wait to start the fireworks.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie and Rajiv try to cheer Emma up.</sentence>
<sentence>The friends all bring things with them.</sentence>
<sentence>The girls carry a guy.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma, Gillian, Charlie and Rajiv come to the party together.</sentence>
<exercise>C8 a) Now read the picture story. Compare the atmosphere at the beginning (picture 1) and the end (pictures 8–10). Wordbank People p. 153</exercise>
<exercise>b) Dramatic reading: Read the story in groups of 8.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Try to learn your role by heart.</exercise>
<exercise>C9 Look at the story again. Say what happens in the story. Example: First, the doorbell rings. Emma, Gillian, … Then … After that … Later … P14</exercise>
<exercise>C10 Target task v " Project Portfolio Write the end of the story. Writing, p. 128</exercise>
<exercise>1 Work in groups.</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<sentence>Speculate on what happens next.</sentence>
<gap>I think the friends will … If it’s Rick, Emma will …</gap>
<exercise>∙ Use connectives (but, so, because, …)</exercise>
<gap>When? Where? What? Who? …</gap>
<exercise>∙ Add speech bubbles.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Agree on what happens.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write a picture story. Draw pictures and write captions. or</exercise>
<exercise>4 Find another group, present/read your stories and give feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127  WB C3, p. 33</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Add structure words (first, then, after that, …).</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-nine 39</footnote>
<exercise>∙ Think about how your character feels.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Now read the story together.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Choose:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write a story.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use connectives (but, so, because, …).</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use adjectives, comparatives and superlatives</exercise>
</page>
<page id='31'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P1 Words: festivals around the year Match the dates to the calendar pages.</exercise>
<exercise>1 New Year’s Day 2 Christmas Day 1 3 Christmas Eve 2 4 Halloween 5 Easter 3 6 Valentine’s Day 4 7 Bonfire Night</exercise>
<exercise>1 Christmas Day – 1. Weihnachtstag; 2 Christmas Eve – Heiligabend; 3 Easter – Ostern; 4 Valentine’s Day – Valentinstag</exercise>
<exercise>P2 Words: celebrations Start word lists that help you talk about celebrations. You can find a lot of words and phrases in the texts on pages 30/31.</exercise>
<exercise>P3 Listening S 5, L 1/17 Listening, p. 124</exercise>
<gap>New Year’s Day is on …</gap>
<exercise>What you must do before a celebration ∙ …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ give each other presents</exercise>
<exercise>a) Listen to Rajiv’s classmate talk about Christmas. Copy the grid. Note down what is similar 1 to / different from Christmas in Germany.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Compare your notes with a partner’s. Choose one thing about</exercise>
<gap>Christmas in England and Germany similar different …</gap>
<exercise>1 similar – ähnlich</exercise>
<sentence>Christmas in England that you would like to have in Germany, too.</sentence>
<sentence>Say why.</sentence>
<exercise>P4 Say it in English Maybe it’s a bit boring because … What do you say when … … you like an idea? … you’re not sure? That’s a great idea! … you don’t like an idea?</exercise>
<gap>It’s a fantastic idea because …</gap>
<gap>I think it’s cool because …</gap>
<sentence>It’s not perfect, but it’s OK.</sentence>
<sentence>Make a list.</sentence>
<gap>I think it’s silly because …</gap>
<gap>I’m not sure about it because …</gap>
<gap>I’m afraid I don’t like it because …</gap>
<gap>I don’t know what to think about it because …</gap>
<exercise>40 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ clean the house</exercise>
<exercise>∙ …</exercise>
</page>
<page id='32'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P5 Reading: Emma’s email Emma sent an email to her classmate Hamida. But there is something wrong. Puzzle out the missing words.</exercise>
<sentence>+@!^ are you today?</sentence>
<sentence>I’m very busy at the moment.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline, Gillian and I are preparing a party right now.</sentence>
<sentence>But there’s a problem.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv wants to !$%“=) a party on the same day as our party.</sentence>
<sentence>But we have got an %$“§!</sentence>
<sentence>: We can all have one big /(„$“ in one place.</sentence>
<sentence>I hope that Rajiv ?=“$§ say yes.</sentence>
<sentence>Well, you MUST come to our party.</sentence>
<exercise>P6 Words: connectives Use connectives to make this text more interesting. LiF 4: Connectives, p. 138</exercise>
<listing>after · then · so · suddenly · after that · finally · at first · when · later · because · and</listing>
<sentence>Rick and Holden decide to go to Alexandra Palace.</sentence>
<sentence>They want to see the fireworks.</sentence>
<sentence>They watch the fireworks.</sentence>
<sentence>They drink a coke.</sentence>
<sentence>Rick suggests they go to George’s party.</sentence>
<sentence>They leave Alexandra Palace.</sentence>
<sentence>They take the train to Camden Town.</sentence>
<sentence>They ring the doorbell.</sentence>
<sentence>George comes to the door.</sentence>
<exercise>1 text – SMS; 2 accident – Unfall</exercise>
<exercise>P7 Conditional clauses, type 1 (1) LiF 7: Bedingungssätze, Typ 1, p. 140 Gillian’s mum has to work at the weekend. Her mum wants Gillian to do some things. Write down sentences. Example: If you clean the bathroom, I’ll give you some extra pocket money 1 .</exercise>
<exercise>1 pocket money – Taschengeld</exercise>
<exercise>1 clean bathroom/give you some extra pocket money 2 make beds/buy you a comic book 3 take you to the cinema/go shopping 4 do all your homework/clean the kitchen after dinner 5 bring you some sweets/don’t play computer games</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words forty-one 41</footnote>
</page>
<page id='33'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P8 Sounds S 6, L 1/18 a) Look at the following words with three syllables 1 . Copy the grid and fill in the words.</exercise>
<exercise>1 syllable – Silbe</exercise>
<listing>envelope · fireworks · festival ·</listing>
<listing>delicious · remember · potato · decorate</listing>
<gap>envelope …</gap>
<gap>delicious …</gap>
<exercise>b) Listen to the CD and check your answers. Repeat the words after the speaker.</exercise>
<exercise>P9 Revision: going to future LiF 5R: going to future , p. 138 The Khans are preparing for Diwali. Look at the pictures and write down what the Khans are going to do.</exercise>
<gap>Example: 1. Mr Khan is going to …</gap>
<listing>wear · decorate · prepare food send · put · buy · give · make</listing>
<exercise>1 2 3 4</exercise>
<exercise>5 6 7 8</exercise>
<exercise>P10 Will future LiF 6: will future, p. 139 Oliver is George’s classmate. Look at the pictures of a Halloween party at his house. What do you think the people will do? Write it down.</exercise>
<gap>Example: I guess the girl will eat …</gap>
<gap>I think … I’m sure … Maybe … I guess …</gap>
<exercise>42 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='34'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>1 2 3 4</exercise>
<exercise>5 6 7 8</exercise>
<exercise>P11 Revision: much, many, some, any, a lot of The Lambraki family are preparing for the party. Read the dialogue and complete it. Use much , many , some , any or a lot of .</exercise>
<sentence>We’ll eat it!</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: What about chairs?</sentence>
<sentence>We can stand.</sentence>
<sentence>But what about the fireworks?</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t you think that’s enough?</sentence>
<sentence>George: You can’t have enough bangers!</sentence>
<exercise>1 borrow – ausleihen</exercise>
<exercise>P12 Conditional clauses, type 1 (2) LiF 7: Bedingungssätze, Typ 1, p. 140</exercise>
<exercise>1. Complete the sentences. If Rick and Holden (not come) to the party, Emma (be) really upset.</exercise>
<exercise>2. You can check your answers on page 221. 3. You need help? ’ Do a), then b). You can do it? ’ Do b).</exercise>
<sentence>Rajiv (bring) some more food to the party if Caroline (ask) him.</sentence>
<exercise>a) Match the sentence halves and write down the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 If Mrs Lambraki (not make) enough snacks, 2 If George (not help) his mother with the</exercise>
<sentence>A Mrs Lambraki (be) angry.</sentence>
<sentence>B Caroline and George (be) disappointed.</sentence>
<sentence>C Caroline (put) her in her room.</sentence>
<sentence>E the guests (be) hungry.</sentence>
<exercise>1 burn – (ver)brennen</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words forty-three 43</footnote>
</page>
<page id='35'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>b) Look at the pictures and say what the friends will do on the Sunday after the party.</exercise>
<sentence>Example: If the weather is sunny, Caroline and Gillian will go to the park and have ice cream.</sentence>
<exercise>4 5 6</exercise>
<exercise>P13 Viewing: Festivals Leanne, Rebecca and Daniel talk about celebrations in their families.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Watch the beginning of the video (0:00–0:25). Which special days does Rebecca’s family celebrate? Which special days does Daniel’s family celebrate? Rebecca’s family celebrates …</exercise>
<exercise>1 weddings – Hochzeiten; 2 Lent – Fastenzeit; 3 anniversaries – Geburts-/Jahrestage</exercise>
<exercise>44 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='36'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>b) Watch the rest of the video. What are the teenagers’ favourite celebrations? Note them down. Add information about why they like them and how they prepare for them.</exercise>
<gap>favourite celebration why? how do they prepare? Leanne Christmas no school, … …</gap>
<exercise>P14 Mediation You spend Bonfire Night in England with your family. Your younger brother sees this poster and asks you what it means. Give him the main information in German.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words forty-fi ve 45</footnote>
</page>
<page id='37'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>O1 Do you like surprises? Tell your partner about a surprise you have had. Say what you liked/didn’t like about it.</exercise>
<exercise>O2 Reading, p. 125</exercise>
<sentence>Read the first part of the story and say why Danny does not want to go with Chloe.</sentence>
<gap>“What do you mean?” she said. Danny gave her a triumphant laugh. “You … in your Halloween get up, all ready to give me a good scare on my birthday. Is Marmalade</gap>
<gap>door and her lantern flickered 5 with an orange glow 6 […]. She couldn’t wait to see Danny’s face once she got him to the Rock Department.</gap>
<sentence>I need you to come with me.</sentence>
<sentence>“You’ll have to do better than that,” laughed Danny, turning to go back indoors.</sentence>
<sentence>“I’m going to have my tea.</sentence>
<sentence>She hurried over, so he wouldn’t be on his own a moment longer.</sentence>
<sentence>“Danny?” Chloe felt desperate.</sentence>
<sentence>“Hi!” He smiled when he saw her, and then his smile deepened.</sentence>
<sentence>“How do I look?</sentence>
<sentence>What could she do?</sentence>
<sentence>He turned back to her and she held out her hand.</sentence>
<gap>Halloween?” “Very cool … for a witch,” Danny laughed.</gap>
<sentence>“Please, Danny.</sentence>
<sentence>We don’t have time.</sentence>
<sentence>“Hey, I’m sorry about Marmalade not turning up,” she said.</sentence>
<sentence>Chloe took his hand and held it.</sentence>
<sentence>She looked into his eyes.</sentence>
<gap>“Don’t worry,” said Danny. “I’ve had a brilliant time. I want to tell you all about it … but how</gap>
<sentence>“But it’s a treat.</sentence>
<gap>did you know he hadn’t met me?” “I just saw him,” she explained. “In fact … a few of us, including Marmalade are over at the Rock Department waiting for you.”</gap>
<sentence>“Oh.</sentence>
<sentence>Why’s that?” Chloe was already leading the way out of the dining room, and Danny hurried to keep up with her.</sentence>
<sentence>“It’s difficult to explain,” she told him, awkwardly.</sentence>
<sentence>“You’re not getting me like that.</sentence>
<exercise>1 witch – Hexe 2 talon – Fingernagel, Kralle 3 bob – schweben, dümpeln 4 gently – sanft 5 flicker – flackern 6 glow – Lichtschein 7 catch sight of sb – jmd erblicken 8 deepen – vertiefen 9 suitable – angemessen 10 awkward – unbehaglich 11 freeze – erstarren</exercise>
<exercise>12 lurk – lauern 13 bucket – Eimer 14 chuck over – ausschütten</exercise>
<exercise>46 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='38'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>O3 Which lines in the text show how Chloe feels about Danny? Describe/Speculate on her feelings for him.</exercise>
<exercise>O4 Read on and find out how the friends surprise Danny.</exercise>
<gap>Chloe kept hold of Danny’s hand 1 as they walked along the path to the Rock Department together. He was coming, though he still seemed a bit doubtful. 2 […]</gap>
<exercise>5 First of all he caught sight of their pumpkin 3 Everyone yelled as loudly as they could before</exercise>
<sentence>“It looks fantastic,” he said.</sentence>
<sentence>“But why did you bring it over here?</sentence>
<sentence>Danny’s friends surrounded him and several clapped him on his back.</sentence>
<exercise>10 Now, instead of her leading him Danny hurried but now he turned to her with a broad smile on</exercise>
<sentence>“Is this what you were bringing me to see?” “Yes,” said Chloe.</sentence>
<gap>his face. “I never expected …” he gestured to the happy birthday banner, ”all this … Why …? And how …?”</gap>
<exercise>15 ghost to make it bob about. “But you’re not “Well, you were so unhappy,” she explained.</exercise>
<sentence>These all look more like Halloween tricks than treats!” Chloe smiled.</sentence>
<gap>“And we wanted to do something to cheer you up.” […] “I’m gobsmacked 7 …,” he said. “Wow. I can’t believe you’d do all this … for me. It’s amazing.”</gap>
<exercise>1 keep hold of sth – etw festhalten 2 doubtful – skeptisch 3 pumpkin – Kürbis 4 reassure – beruhigen 5 dissolve – auflösen 6 amazement – Verwunderung 7 to be gobsmacked – platt sein</exercise>
<exercise>O5 What happens at the party? Write either Danny or Chloe’s diary entry that day.</exercise>
<gap>Du kannst schon viel auf Englisch verstehen und ausdrücken. Du kannst … 3 über Feste und Feiertage sprechen 3 ein Fest planen</gap>
<exercise>3 Hoffnungen und Erwartungen ausdrücken 3 Bedingungen äußern 3 auf eine E-Mail antworten</exercise>
<exercise>3 eine Geschichte nacherzählen  WB Portfolio-Fragebogen Theme 2</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words forty-seven 47</footnote>
</page>
<page id='39'>
<chapter>3/A</chapter>
<exercise>A1 Round Robin: Collect ideas in class: ‘When I think of London I think of …’ Round Robin, p. 130</exercise>
<exercise>A2 L 1/19</exercise>
<exercise>a) Listen to the CD. Note down the sights in the correct order.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and note down what is special about the sights.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Look at the photos. Can you name the sights? Tell a partner what you know about them.</exercise>
<listing>London Eye · Big Ben · Madame Tussauds · Trafalgar Square · Tower Bridge · Buckingham Palace · Covent Garden · Science Museum · Imperial War Museum · Sherlock Holmes Museum · Tate Modern · Emirates Stadium</listing>
<gap>I think this is …</gap>
<exercise>P1, P12  WB A1, A2, p. 41 This must be the …</exercise>
<exercise>1 2</exercise>
<sentence>London Film Museum attraction is waiting for you.</sentence>
<exercise>48 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<sentence>Garden.</sentence>
</page>
<page id='40'>
<chapter>3/A</chapter>
<exercise>A3 a) Which sights would you like to visit? Imagine what you can see or do there. P2</exercise>
<exercise>b) Look at some tips on what to do in London at the bottom of these pages.</exercise>
<sentence>Covent Garden because there are ...</sentence>
<gap>Read the texts and collect adjectives and phrases from the texts that make a place sound interesting. Example: It’s worth a visit; a special attraction; …  WB A3, p. 42</gap>
<exercise>A4 Target task v " Project Write about a London tourist attraction and present it.</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<exercise>1 Choose a place in London you would like to visit and find out more about it. Try to find information that is interesting for young people.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Use your phrases from A3b) and the information you have collected to write a text about your tourist attraction. Include information about prices and things to see or do. Use adjectives (e.g. the most exciting / ideal / perfect / best place to … ).</exercise>
<exercise>3 Work in groups of six. Present your tourist attraction to the group. Each group chooses their top three attractions. Compare your results: What are the top three attractions in class? Wordbank City, p. 151 Speaking, p. 126/127 LiF 3: Steigerung von Adjektiven, p. 137</exercise>
<sentence>But you can also do and the media centre.</sentence>
<sentence>OK, so you’re not interested in art, Modern.</sentence>
<sentence>The building was a power It’s worth a visit just to see the Go to the seventh floor to London for free.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words forty-nine 49</footnote>
</page>
<page id='41'>
<chapter>3/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 a) Read the chat messages to find out who wants to visit London. What are the friends planning to do?</exercise>
<sentence>Caro: Hi Sophie + Rob.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s cool that you can come for the weekend.</sentence>
<sentence>George and I have already made plans to show you around London!</sentence>
<sentence>SOPHEE: Can’t wait to see you again.</sentence>
<sentence>A weekend in London is just so cool.</sentence>
<sentence>You know I’ve never been to London before, so I’m really looking forward to it.</sentence>
<sentence>Hope it’s not only sightseeing though.</sentence>
<sentence>Caro: Don’t worry.</sentence>
<sentence>We haven’t planned too much sightseeing although the Science Museum and the Natural History Museum are worth a visit.</sentence>
<sentence>There are also some interesting places you haven’t heard about, yet – like the Film Museum next to the London Eye.</sentence>
<sentence>Is there anything you especially want to see?</sentence>
<sentence>SOPHEE: I’d love to go to Buckingham Palace.</sentence>
<sentence>And what about Notting Hill, where all the film stars live?</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: No way!</sentence>
<sentence>Sophie has read about all the film stars in London and she hasn’t talked about anything else since.</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t want any more of that!!</sentence>
<gap>Caro: Hmm, we could do Buckingham Palace. But you can’t go in. I’ve checked the Internet. It’s only open to visitors in the summer … And if you’re into film stars, then what about Madame Tussauds?</gap>
<sentence>SOPHEE: Sounds great!</sentence>
<sentence>I’ve always wanted to go there.</sentence>
<sentence>My friend Cherry has just been there.</sentence>
<sentence>She said there is a Chamber of Horrors.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: Great idea!</sentence>
<sentence>Anyway, I guess the London Eye is a must.</sentence>
<sentence>And I think the Emirates Stadium sounds great.</sentence>
<sentence>Georgie: The Emirates Stadium?</sentence>
<sentence>You must be joking!</sentence>
<sentence>Have you turned into an Arsenal fan, Rob?</sentence>
<sentence>;-)) To be honest, it doesn’t sound that exciting.</sentence>
<sentence>If you want to do a stadium tour, I think the Wembley Stadium would be more interesting.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: Don’t worry – I haven’t changed my mind about Manchester United!!!</sentence>
<sentence>Wembley is OK with me, but it’s not that high on my list.</sentence>
<sentence>What I’d really like to do is to go to a big music store.</sentence>
<gap>Caro: Buckingham Palace, Madame Tussauds, the London Eye … Cool! Sounds like a busy weekend. Why don’t we go on a sightseeing tour? We’ll find out more about it … Mum and Dad have offered to pay for tickets! :-) Looking forward to seeing you!!!</gap>
<exercise>b) Read the chat again and complete the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 ??? have made plans for Sophie and Rob. 4 ??? has always wanted to go to Madame Tussauds. 2 ??? has never been to London before. 5 ??? hasn’t changed his mind about 3 ??? has checked the Internet about Manchester United. Buckingham Palace. 6 ??? have offered to pay for the tickets.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Read the chat again and collect phrases the friends use …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … to say what they would like to do (e.g. I’d love to go to … ) ∙ … to disagree (e.g. You must be joking! )  WB B1–B3, p. 43, 44</exercise>
<exercise>50 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … to make suggestions (e.g. And what about …? )</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … to agree (e.g. Sounds great! )</exercise>
</page>
<page id='42'>
<chapter>3/B</chapter>
<exercise>B2 Grammar card: present perfect (statements) 1 Look at these sentences from the chat: George and I have already made plans …</exercise>
<gap>Sophie hasn’t talked about anything else … This is a new tense: the present perfect. Find more examples from B1.</gap>
<exercise>2 How do you form the present perfect? When do you use it? Check LiF 8 on page 140 and start a grammar card. P3, P8  WB B4, B5, p. 45</exercise>
<exercise>B3 Sophie and Rob have a lot to do before the weekend. Look at their checklist and say what they have already done and what they haven’t done yet. P9, P10 Example: Sophie has already bought … Rob and Sophie haven’t … yet.</exercise>
<exercise>B4</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Now describe the brochure. He/She has to draw it.</exercise>
<exercise>at the top ∙ in the middle ∙ in big letters ∙ at the bottom ∙ below the heading</exercise>
<exercise>b) Do you want to go on the tour? Say why/why not.</exercise>
<exercise>B5 a) Read the brochure and try to puzzle out the meanings of these words and phrases.</exercise>
<exercise>live guide ∙ commentary ∙ fantastic offers wide choice ∙ great value ∙ river cruise</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Does it sound/look like a German/French/… word?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Now check a dictionary to see if you were right. How to work with a dictionary, p. 129</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words fi fty-one 51</footnote>
<exercise>a) Look at the brochure about a London bus tour.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Work with a partner. He/She closes his/her book.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Compare the picture with the brochure.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Can you puzzle it out from the context?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Do you know a similar adjective or a similar word?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='43'>
<chapter>3/B</chapter>
<exercise>B6 …</exercise>
<exercise>a) Go through pages 48-51 and collect words to make CITY</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Make a word search with city words for your partner.</exercise>
<exercise>B7 L 1/20 a) Close your books and listen to George and Rob. Find out what the friends decide in the end. What are their reasons?</exercise>
<sentence>George: Hi Rob, how are you?</sentence>
<gap>Rob: I don’t know, they text each other all the time … Have you booked anything yet? George: Not yet. Why?</gap>
<sentence>Caroline and I have looked at different tours.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: Well, it would be really cool to see the Emirates Stadium even if I’m not an Arsenal fan.</sentence>
<sentence>Hop-on Hop-off tour.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: You mean the open double- decker buses?</sentence>
<gap>I’d like to see the real thing …</gap>
<sentence>Hey, have you seen the new Sherlock Holmes film?</sentence>
<sentence>George: Yes, I have – it’s fantastic!</sentence>
<gap>Could be fun on a sunny day … George: OK, then. Rob: Hey, have you been to this famous battleship yet?</gap>
<gap>Rob: I haven’t seen it yet. But isn’t there a Sherlock Holmes Museum in London? I know tickets can be quite expensive, but maybe we could …</gap>
<sentence>George: You mean the HMS Belfast?</sentence>
<sentence>No, I haven’t.</sentence>
<sentence>George: Hasn’t Mum phoned your mum?</sentence>
<sentence>But Caroline would hate it.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: I think the girls want to do their own little tour anyway.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: I think she’s talked to Dad.</sentence>
<gap>sure what the phone call was about. George: She wants to give us some money for our sightseeing …</gap>
<gap>Globe … Rob: Cool! Sounds great! 50</gap>
<sentence>George: Has Sophie already talked to Caroline about this?</sentence>
<exercise>b) Read the dialogue.</exercise>
<sentence>George: Right, see you at the weekend, then!</sentence>
<sentence>Find the questions to the following answers in the dialogue.</sentence>
<sentence>Who asks them and why?</sentence>
<exercise>1 No, I haven’t. But Caroline would hate it. 2 I think she’s talked to Dad. 3 You mean the open double-decker buses?</exercise>
<exercise>4 I don’t know, they text each other all the time … 5 Not yet. Why? 6 Yes, I have – it’s fantastic.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Read the dialogue between George and Rob again and add phrases to your list from B1c). P5  WB B6, B7, p. 46</exercise>
<exercise>52 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>b) v Choose:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write an acrostic about your favourite city. or</exercise>
</page>
<page id='44'>
<chapter>3/B</chapter>
<exercise>B8 Grammar card: present perfect (2) (questions) 1 Write down questions in the present perfect from the dialogue and use different colours like this: Have you booked anything yet? Has Caroline already talked to Sophie?</exercise>
<exercise>2 How do you form the questions? Check LiF 8 on page 142 and add the rule to your grammar card. P4  WB B8, p. 47</exercise>
<exercise>B9</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Look at the list and choose five activities.</exercise>
<listing>· have tea with the Queen · go on a boat trip on the Thames · take photos of London from the London Eye · buy souvenirs in Covent Garden · climb the 199 steps up inside Tower Bridge · feed squirrels in Green Park</listing>
<exercise>∙ Your partner asks questions to find out which activities you have chosen.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ If your answer is ‘yes’, your partner can go on. If your answer is ‘no’, it’s your turn.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ The person who has found out all five activities first is the winner.</exercise>
<listing>· be on a double-decker bus · go shopping in Bond Street · visit Madame Tussauds</listing>
<sentence>Yes, I have.</sentence>
<sentence>No, I haven’t.</sentence>
<exercise>B10 Target task v Portfolio Write a dialogue between Caroline and George and act it out.</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<sentence>Look at pp.</sentence>
<sentence>The friends want to see many different sights, but there isn’t enough time.</sentence>
<sentence>George and Caroline have to decide what to do.</sentence>
<exercise>1 Work with a partner. Go through pages 50-52 and note down what sights/places Sophie, Rob, Caroline and George want to see. Wordbank City, p. 151</exercise>
<exercise>2 Sophie and Rob will arrive on Friday afternoon. They have to get back to Manchester on Sunday afternoon. Think about how many sights/places they could visit in that time.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Now plan a dialogue between Caroline and George. You have to agree on some sights and places. One of you is Caroline, one of you is George.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Write your dialogue. Use statements and questions in the present perfect when necessary. The phrases from B1c) and B7c) can help you. LiF 8: Present perfect, pp. 141/142</exercise>
<exercise>5 Practise your dialogue and present it to another pair. Then give feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127</exercise>
<gap>Support Have you seen/been to …? I’ve never seen/been to … I’ve already visited …, but I haven’t …</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words fi fty-three 53</footnote>
</page>
<page id='45'>
<chapter>3/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 Have you ever been lost? Talk to a partner and tell him/her about your experiences.</exercise>
<listing>Support When I was small … · On a trip to … · Last year I got lost · I lost my way when … · I lost sight of … · I could not see/find … · I did not know where … · I was scared/worried/frightened/…</listing>
<exercise>C2 L 1/21 a) Read the text and find out why George says: “We’re not very well-organized today …”.</exercise>
<sentence>A week later.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob and Sophie are in London.</sentence>
<sentence>Sophie: It’s past four o’clock.</sentence>
<sentence>Where are the boys?</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: It’s only five past, Sophie.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m sure they will be here soon.</sentence>
<gap>Caroline: We’ll explain that later. Where are you? Rob: I don’t really know. I came out of the Underground and started walking down the road …</gap>
<exercise>5 Sophie: Well, Rob is always late. Caroline: Have you seen any sights or road</exercise>
<gap>Caroline: I’ll phone George. … No answer. Let’s just wait a few more minutes.</gap>
<sentence>Five minutes later.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: Well, I walked past a building on the left.</sentence>
<sentence>There was a huge queue.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: That was Madame Tussauds.</sentence>
<exercise>10 Caroline: Look, there’s George. But where’s Rob? walked along Marylebone Road.</exercise>
<sentence>George: Hi girls, have you seen Rob?</sentence>
<sentence>I’ve lost him.</sentence>
<sentence>Sophie: What do you mean, you’ve lost him?</sentence>
<sentence>George: Well, of course we did.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: Yes, well, then I turned right because I thought I saw George, but it wasn’t him.</sentence>
<sentence>So I walked straight on to the next street and turned left.</sentence>
<exercise>15 the Tube to Baker Street. It was really full and Caroline: Can you see a street name? I’ve got a</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline: I don’t believe it!</sentence>
<sentence>It’s only a short way from the station to here.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: Well, I’ve just crossed a main street.</sentence>
<sentence>Sophie: You don’t know Rob!</sentence>
<sentence>George: Sounds like Caroline!</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Very funny, George!</sentence>
<sentence>George: No, I haven’t, my mobile’s dead.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Oh great!</sentence>
<gap>you. What’s Rob’s number, Sophie? Sophie: Erm … 0775 6488318. … And I’ve left</gap>
<gap>we? … Rob: Hello! Caroline: Hi Rob, it’s Caroline! Rob: Caroline, where are you all? I’ve rung George and Sophie again and again but they aren’t answering.</gap>
<gap>right in front of me is Nottingham Street …</gap>
<exercise>54 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ How did you feel?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What happened?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='46'>
<chapter>3/C</chapter>
<exercise>b) Read the text again and collect information about Rob.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Where is he now? Find the place on the map below. P13  WB C1, C2, p. 48</exercise>
<exercise>c) Find words and phrases in the text for giving/talking about directions and write them down in a list.</exercise>
<exercise>C3 L 1/22 a) Listen to Caroline’s directions and follow them on the map. Listening, p. 124</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and add any new words or expressions to your list from C2c).</exercise>
<exercise>c) Match the expressions to the symbols. There are more symbols than you need. P6  WB C3, p. 49</exercise>
<exercise>1 walk straight on 2 turn left</exercise>
<exercise>3 turn right 4 walk past … 5 walk on till you get to … 6 on your right 7 on your left</exercise>
<exercise>8 cross the street</exercise>
<exercise>C4 v Extra</exercise>
<sentence>Play a game: Use the map and say where you are.</sentence>
<sentence>Your partner gives you directions, but he/she doesn’t say where you are going.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</footnote>
<exercise>∙ Where and how did he lose George?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='47'>
<chapter>3/C</chapter>
<exercise>C5 L 1/23 a) Look at the picture and describe the man in it. What do you know about him? Note down your ideas. Wordbank People, p. 153</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read about the friends’ visit to the Sherlock Holmes Museum and add any new information about Holmes to your notes from a).</exercise>
<sentence>George: Look, there he is.</sentence>
<sentence>Hi Rob!</sentence>
<sentence>Sophie: So you’ve found us!</sentence>
<sentence>Well done!</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: Well, you two didn’t answer your mobiles!</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: Come upstairs!</sentence>
<sentence>You must look at the man who has got a snake around his head.</sentence>
<sentence>And there’s a woman who is shooting someone.</sentence>
<sentence>Wow!</sentence>
<sentence>And all these weapons.</sentence>
<sentence>Sophie: Ugh!</sentence>
<sentence>That’s horrible.</sentence>
<sentence>Sherlock Holmes!</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Don’t be stupid!</sentence>
<sentence>Sherlock Holmes isn’t a real person.</sentence>
<sentence>Holmes met in the stories.</sentence>
<sentence>Look!</sentence>
<sentence>It says so in the brochure.</sentence>
<sentence>George: But in the film, Sherlock Holmes and Dr Watson live in Baker Street.</sentence>
<sentence>I’ve seen it!</sentence>
<sentence>It’s the film that Jude Law stars in.</sentence>
<sentence>George: I don’t remember them from the film.</sentence>
<sentence>Sophie: Let’s go and have a look in the shop.</sentence>
<gap>Dr Watson and … Sophie: I think you’re both right. Why don’t we</gap>
<sentence>Rob: Wow, these stairs are really dark and narrow.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: Come on George!</sentence>
<sentence>Perhaps I can get a DVD which we can watch when we get home.</sentence>
<sentence>Sophie: The lights aren’t very strong.</sentence>
<sentence>Rob: This looks like Sherlock Holmes’ study.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: And here’s the bedroom.</sentence>
<sentence>Look at all these photographs of the criminals who lived at that time!</sentence>
<exercise>c) Match the sentence halves about Sherlock Holmes and the museum.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Sherlock Holmes is the detective A which shows criminals from that time. 2 The house in Baker Street is now a museum B who played Dr Watson in the film. 3 There is a photo gallery C that they had in the 19th century. 4 Jude Law is an actor D which shows how Sherlock Holmes lived. 5 The lights are like the ones E who is falling through a trapdoor. 6 On one of the photos there is a man F that lived at 221b Baker Street.</exercise>
<exercise>56 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='48'>
<chapter>3/C</chapter>
<exercise>C6 v Extra: Grammar detective: relative clauses</exercise>
<sentence>Who , which or that ?</sentence>
<sentence>Can you solve this puzzle?</sentence>
<exercise>1 Find examples of relative clauses with who , which and that from C5 (e.g. So this is the house which belonged to Sherlock Holmes. ).</exercise>
<exercise>2 When do you use who ? When do you use which ? When can you use that ? Look at LiF 9 on page 142 for help. Write a grammar card for relative clauses. P7  WB C4, p. 50</exercise>
<exercise>C7 v Extra a) Puzzle out the answers. You can find the answers in the dialogue from C5.</exercise>
<exercise>1 This is a person who writes stories. 2 This is the man who was Holmes’ assistant and best friend. 3 This is something which a doctor often carries. 4 These are people that do bad things. 5 This is something that you can keep animals in. 6 This is something which you can buy for your friends.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Make five new puzzles for your partner. Use who, which and that . Example: This is the boy in our class who … This is the room in our school that … LiF 9: Relativsätze, p. 142  WB C5, p. 50</exercise>
<exercise>C8 Target task v " Project Portfolio Need help?</exercise>
<sentence>Write an English guidebook of your home town/area in class.</sentence>
<exercise>1 Collect places/sights/people that could be interesting for visitors.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Find out about the places/sights/people:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What is special about them?</exercise>
<exercise>3 Choose one place/sight/person and write a paragraph for the guidebook. Describe the place/sight/person and note down directions, too. Wordbank City, p. 151</exercise>
<sentence>Extra: Gallery walk: Hang up your paragraphs and read them.</sentence>
<sentence>Choose the top three sights/places/people in your home town/area.</sentence>
<sentence>Support You can add pictures, too.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words fi fty-seven 57</footnote>
<exercise>∙ Where are they? / Where did they live?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='49'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P1 Words: buildings and places Wordbank City, p. 151</exercise>
<exercise>a) What are the words? You can find the buildings/places in a city.</exercise>
<listing>tkemar · werto · rkpa · mseumu · lacepa · thetrea · idbrge · diustam</listing>
<exercise>b) Now note down an example of each building/place in London. Example: tkemar = market: Camden Market, Covent Garden, …</exercise>
<exercise>P2 Words: places</exercise>
<exercise>a) Match the parts to make correct phrases. Sometimes there is more than one correct answer.</exercise>
<exercise>1 an amazing A to see … 2 the perfect way B to eat 3 a fantastic place C to visit if you’re … 4 an absolute D to spend some time 5 a wonderful place E view 6 the ideal place F a visit 7 worth G to go for a good time 8 one of the best places H must</exercise>
<exercise>P3 Present perfect (1) LiF 8: Present perfect, p. 140</exercise>
<sentence>George ???</sentence>
<sentence>(want) to visit the London Dungeon for a long time.</sentence>
<sentence>Most of his friends ???</sentence>
<sentence>(be) there before.</sentence>
<exercise>a) Copy the grid. Find the present perfect forms.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Use each phrase to write a sentence about the places in P1 or other sights in London. Example: Covent Garden is the ideal place in London to spend some time and watch acrobats and musicians.</exercise>
<exercise>2. You can check your answers</exercise>
<sentence>You need help?</sentence>
<sentence>’ Do a), then b).</sentence>
<sentence>You can do it?</sentence>
<sentence>’ Do b).</sentence>
<gap>have/has planned see … check … make … buy … eat …</gap>
<gap>infi nitive present perfect visit … meet … take … be … fi nd … walk …</gap>
<exercise>58 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='50'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>b) Choose the correct form and write down the sentences about a school trip to London.</exercise>
<exercise>1 We (see already) a lot of London. 2 But we (not see) any film stars yet. 3 I (take already) photos of all the sights. 4 My friend (buy already) an “I love London” T-shirt.</exercise>
<exercise>5 I (not buy) a souvenir yet. 6 My friends and I (eat already) pizza at</exercise>
<sentence>Piccadilly Circus.</sentence>
<exercise>P4 Present perfect (2): questions LiF 8: Present perfect, p. 142 Look at the words and write down eight questions. Ask a partner and note down his/her answers.</exercise>
<listing>be · meet · eat · buy · read · climb · cook · do · drink · feed · find · fly · go · have · see · make · …</listing>
<sentence>Have you ever bought a present for your teacher?</sentence>
<gap>No, I haven’t. Have you ever …?</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<exercise>P5 Words: suggesting, agreeing, disagreeing Look at the pictures and write down what the other person could say in this situation. Try to use as many different phrases as possible.</exercise>
<listing>I think … sounds so much cooler. · That’s fantastic! · It would be cool to see the … · Could be fun. · I’m not sure. · I’m sure you would enjoy it, too. · I think it’s a great idea! · I’d love to go to … · You must be joking. · What about …? · I must admit I’d like to see … · Well, why not? · Well, to be honest, I’d much rather … · I’ve always wanted to go … · Why don’t we …?</listing>
<sentence>Let’s watch the Harry Potter film!</sentence>
<sentence>Well, any special plans?</sentence>
<sentence>All the stars live in Notting Hill.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s just stand here and wait until we see someone cool.</sentence>
<gap>… …</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>There are so many things to do. We could go to the zoo or to Stables Market or …</gap>
<sentence>Natural History Museum!</sentence>
<sentence>I’ve always wanted to see the dinosaurs.</sentence>
<sentence>Or is that too boring for you?</sentence>
<sentence>Well, what have you found out?</sentence>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>… …</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words fi fty-nine 59</footnote>
</page>
<page id='51'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P6 Words: directions S 7, L 1/24 a) Listen to the directions and follow them on the map. Where do you go?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Work with a partner and give him/ her directions.</exercise>
<exercise>P7 Relative clauses LiF 9: relative clauses, p. 142</exercise>
<gap>v Can you do it? 1. Write a short definition. Use relative pronouns (who, which or that). Film star: actor/very famous ’ A film star is an actor who … Covent Garden: place/was once a fruit market ’ …</gap>
<exercise>2. You can check your answers on</exercise>
<sentence>You need help?</sentence>
<sentence>’ Do a), then b).</sentence>
<sentence>You can do it?</sentence>
<sentence>’ Do b).</sentence>
<exercise>a) What are the correct relative pronouns ( who , which or that )?</exercise>
<exercise>1 A doctor is a person ??? looks after people</exercise>
<exercise>b) Write a short definition. Use relative pronouns ( who, which or that ).</exercise>
<exercise>1 Pickpocket: person/steals other people’s</exercise>
<exercise>5 Thames: river/is more than 300 kilometres long</exercise>
<exercise>1 dish – Gericht 2 wax – Wachs</exercise>
<exercise>60 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='52'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P8 Present perfect (3) LiF 8: Present perfect, p. 141 Look at the pictures. Write down what the pupils have already done or haven’t done yet on their school trip to London. Example: We have already had tea.</exercise>
<exercise>P9 Present perfect (4): word order LiF 8: Present perfect, p. 141 Write down the correct sentences. Then read the dialogue with a partner.</exercise>
<sentence>John: been / to Berlin, but / I / have / been / I / haven’t / to London yet / .</sentence>
<sentence>Linda: packed / you / have / already / your things / ?</sentence>
<sentence>John: my bag / I / no, / haven’t / packed / yet / .</sentence>
<sentence>John: yet / haven’t / I / no, / bought / a guidebook / .</sentence>
<sentence>Linda: I’m so excited!</sentence>
<exercise>1 I’m looking forward to – Ich freue mich auf 2 guidebook – Reiseführer</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words sixty-one 61</footnote>
</page>
<page id='53'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P10 Present perfect (5) Look at the tourists and the list of places. Say where they have or haven’t been and what they have done. LiF 8: Present perfect, p. 141</exercise>
<listing>be · London · visit · Paris · Rome · see · Texas · map · Hawaii · New York · Munich · Australia · kangaroo · buy</listing>
<exercise>P11 Sounds S 8, L 1/25 a) Listen to the sentences and note down the words that are stressed 1 most. Example: 1. But Caroline would hate it.</exercise>
<exercise>1 But Caroline would hate it. 2 It seems OK with me, but it’s not that high on my list. 3 Well, it would be cool to see the Emirates Stadium after all. 4 I must admit I’d like to see the real thing. 5 I know tickets can be quite expensive, but maybe we could … 6 Sounds great!</exercise>
<exercise>b) Now say the sentences again and stress the right words.</exercise>
<exercise>1 stress – betonen</exercise>
<exercise>P12 Listening S 9, L 1/26</exercise>
<sentence>Listen to the dialogues and match them to the sights.</sentence>
<listing>London Eye · Tower · Tower Bridge · Big Ben · Shakespeare’s Globe</listing>
<exercise>P13 Reading Reading, p. 125 Read C2 on page 54 and answer the questions.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Why didn’t George phone Rob? 2 Does Sophie phone her brother? Why/Why not? 3 What did Rob do after he lost George? 4 How can Caroline help?</exercise>
<exercise>62 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='54'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P14 Mediation Imagine you are in London with your parents. You want to visit the Sherlock Holmes Museum. Read its website and answer your parents’ questions in German.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Wann soll Sherlock Holmes in dem Haus</exercise>
<exercise>P15 Reading Reading, p. 125</exercise>
<sentence>Visitors can hear Florence’s story in her own words through audio The cost hot spots around the museum.</sentence>
<sentence>The audio tour is included children.</sentence>
<exercise>3 Wie sind die Öffnungszeiten? 4 Was müssen wir als Familie mit 3 Personen zahlen?</exercise>
<sentence>Answer the following questions about the text.</sentence>
<exercise>1 What time does the museum open on</exercise>
<sentence>Sundays?</sentence>
<exercise>1 closed – geschlossen</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words sixty-three 63</footnote>
</page>
<page id='55'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<sentence>Well worth a visit and entry is free.</sentence>
<sentence>The museums in Kensington Three of the most popular museums in London are close together in Kensington: the Science Museum, the Natural History Museum and the Victoria and Albert Museum.</sentence>
<sentence>At the Victoria and Albert Museum you can see a fantastic fashion collection.</sentence>
<gap>This is only a small selection of London museums. You might like to visit one of the more unusual museums, such as the Horniman Museum, where you will discover a brilliant aquarium and a rare collection of Asian and African masks. Or why not go to the London Transport Museum? Or to the Florence Nightingale Museum or …?</gap>
<exercise>1 Look at the exhibits and put them in the right museum.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Choose the museum you find most interesting. Visit its website and write a short report about it:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What can you see/do there?</exercise>
<exercise>3 Think of the museums you have already visited. Which is your favourite museum? Say why.</exercise>
<exercise>1 collection – Sammlung 2 mummy – Mumie 3 mummified – mumifiziert 4 development – Entwicklung 5 roar – brüllen</exercise>
<exercise>64 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Where is it?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What do you like best?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='56'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>6 7</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</footnote>
</page>
<page id='57'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>O1 Imagine you were inside a London Eye capsule 1 high above the city.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ How do you feel?</exercise>
<exercise>O2 Reading, p. 125 Read this excerpt from The London Eye Mystery and say what happens.</exercise>
<sentence>Before they move to New York, Aunt Gloria and her son, Salim, come to visit Ted and Kat and their parents.</sentence>
<sentence>One day Ted and Kat take Salim on a trip to London.</sentence>
<sentence>My favourite thing to do in London is to fly the Eye.</sentence>
<sentence>You would like to go round one more time, but it is not allowed.</sentence>
<sentence>So you get out feeling like an astronaut coming down from space, a little lighter than you were.</sentence>
<exercise>5 observation 2 wheel ever built. You are sealed into We took Salim to the Eye because he’d never</exercise>
<sentence>You begin to rise.</sentence>
<sentence>A stranger came up to us in the queue, offering us a free ticket.</sentence>
<sentence>We took it and gave it to Salim.</sentence>
<sentence>We shouldn’t have done this, but we did.</sentence>
<exercise>10 glass and steel and are hung from the rim 4 of the May, and was due to come down at 12.02 the</exercise>
<sentence>It takes thirty minutes to go a full circle.</sentence>
<exercise>15 like toy-town and the cars on the roads below Kat and I tracked Salim’s capsule as it made its</exercise>
<sentence>I think London looks like London and the cars like cars, only smaller.</sentence>
<gap>orbit. When it reached its highest point, we both said “NOW!” at the same time. Kat laughed and I joined in. […] Then the capsule landed. The doors opened and</gap>
<exercise>20 Thames. You can see how it loops 7 and curves the passengers came out in twos and threes.</exercise>
<gap>but when you are on the ground you think it is straight. […] It is also interesting to watch the capsules on either side of yours. You see strangers looking</gap>
<sentence>They walked off in different directions.</sentence>
<sentence>Their faces were smiling.</sentence>
<sentence>Their paths probably never crossed again.</sentence>
<exercise>25 out, just like you are doing. The capsule that is and the one after that. He still didn’t appear.</exercise>
<gap>higher than yours becomes lower than yours and the capsule that is lower becomes higher. […] And then your capsule goes lower and you are sad because you do not want the ride to end.</gap>
<exercise>1 capsule – Kapsel 2 observation – Beobachtung 3 rise – aufsteigen 4 rim – Rand</exercise>
<exercise>5 force of gravity – Schwerkraft 6 abacus beads – Kugeln auf einem Abakus</exercise>
<exercise>7 loop – (sich) winden 8 board – an Bord gehen 9 shadow – Schatten 10 seal in – einschließen in</exercise>
<exercise>11 vanish – verschwinden 12 face of the earth - Erdboden</exercise>
<exercise>66 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What can you see?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='58'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>O3 a) Look up the London Eye on the Internet and find more information about</exercise>
<exercise>∙ how to get there (visitor information)</exercise>
<exercise>b) Design a tourist brochure for the London Eye.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Find pictures to make your brochure more ∙ Make the London Eye sound interesting.</exercise>
<listing>brilliant · amazing · fantastic · stunning · you must go to … · don’t miss … · it’s the best sight/place … · it’s worth a visit · you should …</listing>
<exercise>O4 v Choose ∙ Kat rings up her mother when Salim doesn’t turn up. ∙ Ted and Kat want to find out how Salim disappeared. Write a conversation between them in which they speculate about what might have happened.</exercise>
<exercise>O5 S 10, L 1/27 a) What do you think happened?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Now listen to the CD and find out what actually happened. Compare your ideas.</exercise>
<gap>Du kannst schon viel auf Englisch verstehen und ausdrücken. Du kannst … 3 über Sehenswürdigkeiten in London sprechen 3 Vorschläge machen</gap>
<exercise>3 sagen, dass dir etwas gefällt/nicht gefällt 3 ausdrücken, was du gerne tun möchtest 3 über etwas berichten, das du schon einmal getan/erlebt hast 3 jemandem den Weg beschreiben 3 eine Person beschreiben</exercise>
<exercise>3 einen Artikel für einen Reiseführer verfassen  WB Portfolio-Fragebogen Theme 3</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words sixty-seven 67</footnote>
<exercise>∙ ticket prices (standard tickets for adults and children)</exercise>
<exercise>∙ opening times (visitor information)</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use your information from a).</exercise>
<sentence>Write their telephone conversation.</sentence>
</page>
<page id='59'>
<chapter>4/A</chapter>
<exercise>A1 Look at the posters 1-3 at Camden School for Girls. Which event would you like to go to? Which one would you like to take part in? Which one would you hate to go to? Say why.  WB A1, p. 59</exercise>
<exercise>A2 a) Make a list of events and activities that take place at your school. Then compare the events and activities to the ones at Camden School for Girls. Include places, prices, dates, classes/age groups.</exercise>
<gap>At our school we also have/perform …</gap>
<gap>We organize … every year.</gap>
<gap>We don’t have … There is no …</gap>
<exercise>b) What is your favourite event/activity at your school? Say why. Wordbank Entertainment, p. 152 P15, P16</exercise>
<exercise>68 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='60'>
<chapter>4/A</chapter>
<exercise>A3 a) Read the article from the Camden School Friday News below. Who gets a lot of praise?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Collect words and phrases you can use to praise someone. P1</exercise>
<exercise>A4  S 11, L 1/28 a) Listen to the friends and look at the posters to find out which event they are talking about. Listening, p. 124</exercise>
<exercise>b) Use the correct poster to note down information in a grid ( who, when, what, where? ). Then listen again and add more information to your grid. P2  WB A2, p. 59</exercise>
<exercise>A5 Target task v  Portfolio Write an article about the event from A4 for the Camden School Friday News. 1 Plan your article and think about</exercise>
<exercise>∙ an introduction: say what your article is ∙ the main part: describe the details and ∙ the ending: say something positive about the event.</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<exercise>2 Collect words and phrases for your article. Your list from A3b) can help you.</exercise>
<sentence>Check your articles and give each other feedback.</sentence>
<exercise>3 Camden S C hool Friday n ew S</exercise>
<sentence>CSG at Step Live!</sentence>
<sentence>– a real success!</sentence>
<sentence>Step Live!</sentence>
<sentence>The CSG The girls looked brilliant in their excellent!</sentence>
<sentence>It was the perfect end ending applause.</sentence>
<sentence>Well done to everyone who took stage with their ‘Mamma Mia’ piece.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words sixty-nine 69</footnote>
<exercise>∙ a title</exercise>
<sentence>).</sentence>
</page>
<page id='61'>
<chapter>4/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1  L 1/29 a) Read these sentences from the dialogue below. Speculate on what the girls are talking about.</exercise>
<exercise>1 “Don’t you think we should do something totally different this year?” 2 “Don’t worry, we can practise together.” 3 “I just love auditions!”</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the dialogue. What is it about? What are the girls’ suggestions? Say which one you like best and why.</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline: Let me see.</sentence>
<sentence>There are only six proper roles.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: That’s true.</sentence>
<sentence>What do you suggest then?</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Hmm, I don’t know.</sentence>
<sentence>We haven’t had a musical since ‘The Lion King’.</sentence>
<sentence>And that was two years ago!</sentence>
<sentence>I loved ‘The Lion King’.</sentence>
<gap>we could do ‘Cats’ or ‘Starlight Express’? e mma: Great idea! But the auditions … I would be super-nervous. I haven’t sung on</gap>
<sentence>Caroline: Don’t worry, we can practise together.</sentence>
<sentence>I love auditions!</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: A musical?</sentence>
<sentence>Oh no, not such boring, girly stuff again, please!</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Oh, yes.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s do Shakespeare!</sentence>
<gap>silly … Gillian: Oh no, not another classic. We did ‘A Christmas Carol’ by Charles Dickens last year, remember? Don’t you think we should do something totally different this year? Look, I’ve done some research on the Internet and I’ve found a comedy that sounds fantastic. It’s called ‘Invasion from Planet</gap>
<sentence>Zorgon’.</sentence>
<sentence>Walsh would like that.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: But just think about it – it’s really cool!</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: No, something like ‘Twilight’!</sentence>
<sentence>DVD ‘New Moon’ with Dad.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: I know.</sentence>
<sentence>But it’s just a first idea.</sentence>
<sentence>Well, we could change it into a play.</sentence>
<sentence>Great idea!</sentence>
<sentence>Just think about the amazing costumes and the decoration for the stage.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: Fantastic idea!</sentence>
<sentence>Come on, girls, let’s find Ms Walsh and ask her now!</sentence>
<exercise>c) Read the dialogue again and note down phrases to persuade someone about something (e.g. Let’s … ). P3  WB B1, p. 61</exercise>
<exercise>70 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='62'>
<chapter>4/B</chapter>
<exercise>B2</exercise>
<sentence>Write down five sentences.</sentence>
<sentence>Some can be wrong.</sentence>
<sentence>Then show them to a partner.</sentence>
<sentence>He/She must say if they are right or wrong and correct the wrong sentences.</sentence>
<exercise>B3 Grammar card: present perfect with for/since 1 Look at these sentences from B1: I haven’t had a big role for ages. I haven’t sung on stage since our last Christmas play.</exercise>
<exercise>2 In English you can use two words for the German word ‘seit’: for and since . When do you use since ? When do you use for ? Check LiF 10 on page 143 and add the information to your grammar card for the present perfect.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Think of four more sentences with for and since and add them, too. P8  WB B2, B3, p. 62</exercise>
<exercise>B4 Work with a partner and talk about your hobby.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … have known the teacher/the other children in the group ∙ … have been interested in your hobby</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … have had/taken lessons ∙ … have practised …</exercise>
<exercise>B5 Target task v  Portfolio</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<sentence>Write a dialogue between Emma, Gillian, Caroline and Ms Walsh.</sentence>
<sentence>The girls tell Ms Walsh about the vampire play, but she is not sure about it.</sentence>
<sentence>So they try to persuade her.</sentence>
<sentence>In the end, Ms Walsh says yes.</sentence>
<exercise>∙ Collect ideas about why Ms Walsh doesn’t like the idea of a vampire play.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Write your dialogue. You can use the phrases from B1c).</exercise>
<exercise>3 Practise your dialogue and perform it in front of another group. Give feedback. Wordbank Entertainment, p. 152 Speaking 2, p. 127</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventy-one 71</footnote>
<gap>Say since when or for how long you …</gap>
<exercise>∙ … have dreamed of a horse/boat/prize/…</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … have wanted to …</exercise>
<exercise>1 Work in groups of four.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Find arguments to persuade Ms Walsh.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='63'>
<chapter>4/B</chapter>
<exercise>B6 v Extra Design a poster for the vampire play. You can look at the posters on pages 68/69 for help.</exercise>
<exercise>B7 Grammar card: present perfect or simple past? 1 Look at these sentences from the dialogue in B1: We haven’t had a musical since ‘The Lion King’. And that was two years ago!</exercise>
<exercise>2 You can use the present perfect or the simple past for things that happened in the past. But when do you use the present perfect? When do you use the simple past? Check LiF 11 on page 143 and write a grammar card. Add four examples. P10  WB B6, p. 64</exercise>
<exercise>B8 The girls have persuaded Ms Walsh, and she has written a play about vampires. The next day there is an audition for pupils who want to take part in the play. There are lots of things to do. LiF 11: Present perfect or simple past, p. 143</exercise>
<gap>Caroline has got the to-do list and is checking with Ms Walsh to see if everything is ready. Look at the checklist and write their dialogue. You can start like this: Ms Walsh: “Caroline, has Emma ...?” Caroline: “Yes, she has. She copied the script two weeks ago.” …</gap>
<exercise>∙ copy the script (Emma) (two weeks ago)</exercise>
<exercise>∙ make a list of the pupils who are interested (Emma) (yesterday)</exercise>
<exercise>∙ find music for the play (Caroline) (–)</exercise>
<exercise>B9  L 1/30 Read Caroline’s text message to Rajiv. Then listen to the telephone conversation and find out what the text message is about. Listening, p. 124</exercise>
<exercise>72 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ buy vampire teeth (Gillian) (Friday)</exercise>
<exercise>∙ make posters for the auditions (Gillian) (last week)</exercise>
<exercise>∙ book assembly hall for the audition (secretary) (two days ago)</exercise>
<exercise>∙ send the script to the pupils who are interested</exercise>
</page>
<page id='64'>
<chapter>4/B</chapter>
<exercise>B10 Look at these words and organize them in a word web. In class find more words to describe music. How to work with a dictionary, p. 129 melody text/lyrics</exercise>
<listing>melody · text/lyrics · happy · sad · quiet · rhythm · fast · slow · scary · cheerful · atmosphere · dark</listing>
<gap>…</gap>
<exercise>B11  S 12, L 1/31</exercise>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<sentence>Three days later Caroline is at Rajiv’s house.</sentence>
<sentence>He has written a vampire song.</sentence>
<exercise>a) Close your books and listen to the song. What is it about?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and describe the music. How does it make you feel?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Imagine you are the vampire. Write about a night in your life.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write a different last verse for the song.</exercise>
<sentence>The house was dark and eerie.</sentence>
<sentence>And I had the strangest feeling something bad was near me.</sentence>
<sentence>I crept down to the basement and guess what I found there?</sentence>
<sentence>A vampire lurking in the shadows!</sentence>
<sentence>It gave me such a scare.</sentence>
<sentence>Since then I haven’t slept at all.</sentence>
<sentence>I can’t wait for the day to end.</sentence>
<exercise>B12 Target task v  Portfolio P4, P5 to see my vampire friend.</exercise>
<sentence>Present your favourite song.</sentence>
<exercise>1 Collect information about the singer/band.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … how long he or she has been a singer/they have been a band ∙ … since when they have been interested in music</exercise>
<sentence>Write a profile about the singer/band.</sentence>
<exercise>∙ … the kind of music (rock, pop, hip hop, …)</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … what you think of when you hear it</exercise>
<exercise>3 Present your favourite song to your class. Speaking 1, p. 126  WB B7, p. 65</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventy-three 73</footnote>
<exercise>c) v Choose:</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<gap>Find out …</gap>
<exercise>∙ … since when the singer/band is/are famous</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … if they have won any prizes</exercise>
<exercise>2 Makes notes about …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … why you like the song</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … how it makes you feel</exercise>
</page>
<page id='65'>
<chapter>4/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1  L 1/32 a) Read the story. What happens at the audition?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Write down two true sentences and one false sentence about the story. Your partner must say which sentence is wrong and must correct it.  WB C1, p. 65</exercise>
<sentence>It was the day of the audition and all the girls were very excited.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline was happy, but she was nervous, too.</sentence>
<sentence>The girls went ouside.</sentence>
<sentence>“Tell me what’s wrong,” Gillian said quietly.</sentence>
<sentence>“I’ve mucked it up,” Anastasia said sadly.</sentence>
<sentence>“My mum had to go to hospital yesterday.</sentence>
<sentence>“It would be OK for me if Anastasia got the role,” Caroline said to Emma.</sentence>
<gap>worried …” “Don’t worry – if we tell Ms Walsh, you’ll get another chance!” Gillian said cheerfully and smiled at her.</gap>
<gap>convincingly – when she laughs, she laughs happily or nervously, just as the stage directions say.” “She’s just a very good actress,” Emma agreed admiringly. “But Moira …?” Caroline rolled her eyes and Emma pulled a face.</gap>
<gap>At the audition, Anastasia was first. When she went on the stage, her face was sad. “OK, let’s hear your part, then!” Ms Walsh said kindly. All the girls were quiet. Anastasia started, but she spoke very slowly: “Will I have to … stay in … the shadows forever? ...” “Come on, Anastasia! You know your words, don’t you?” “I do, Miss, but …” Anastasia whispered and then she began to cry. Gillian ran to the stage and put her arms around her. “What’s wrong?” Ms Walsh asked worriedly, but Anastasia couldn’t answer.</gap>
<gap>Inside, Moira was next. There was loud applause from her friends when she went on stage. She turned around like a star. “Can I begin, Miss?”, she asked arrogantly, but didn’t wait for an answer. She knew the words and spoke clearly: “Will I have to stay in the shadows forever? …” “Word, words, words,” Emma said quietly, “but no emotion!” But Moira’s friends clapped excitedly. Caroline watched them. “You’re right,” she answered nervously.</gap>
<gap>On stage Caroline wanted to be the best actress. She really liked the role and she knew she could be better than Moira. “Will I …,” Caroline started loudly, but then she looked at Moira and her friends. They gave her the thumbs down behind Ms Walsh’s back. Caroline started to stammer. She tried to remember the words, but suddenly she couldn’t remember anything.</gap>
<exercise>74 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='66'>
<chapter>4/C</chapter>
<exercise>C2 a) Copy the grid. Note down all the</exercise>
<exercise>b) Dramatic reading:</exercise>
<gap>Emma Ms Walsh …</gap>
<gap>“She’s just a very good actress.” “OK, …” …</gap>
<gap>admiringly … …</gap>
<exercise>∙ Remember how the characters feel. Use your notes from a) and show the feelings of the different characters.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Work in groups of four and have a reading competition. Find the best reader. You can use your grid from a) and a checklist to find out who read best. Dramatic reading, p. 130</exercise>
<exercise>C3 Grammar detective: adverbs of manner</exercise>
<sentence>Clear or clearly ?</sentence>
<sentence>Can you solve this puzzle?</sentence>
<exercise>1 Look at these sentences from C1:</exercise>
<sentence>When she laughs, she laughs happily.</sentence>
<exercise>2 Copy the grid and add more examples with nervous/nervously , worried/worriedly , quiet/quietly , excited/excitedly and loud/loudly from the story.</exercise>
<exercise>3 What do you describe with an adjective? What do you describe with an adverb? Look at LiF 12 on page 144 for help.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Start a grammar card. Look at LiF 12 on page 144 and find out about the spelling. When do you have to be careful? Add the information to your grammar card. P11-P13  WB C2, p. 66</exercise>
<exercise>C4</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write down these verbs on ten cards:</exercise>
<exercise>eat ∙ walk ∙ dance ∙ sing ∙ jump ∙ talk ∙ smile ∙ move ∙ laugh ∙ play ∙ Now note down ten adverbs on ten different cards. Example: angrily, happily,</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Now one player takes a card from each pile and acts out what the cards say.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventy-five 75</footnote>
<exercise>1 Practise reading the story:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Read the story quietly twice.</exercise>
<gap>scarily …</gap>
<exercise>∙ Make two piles (verbs and adverbs). Turn the cards upside down.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ The others must guess what the player is doing and how he/she is doing it.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='67'>
<chapter>4/C</chapter>
<exercise>C5  L 1/33 a) Think – pair – share: Speculate on how the story about the audition goes on. Think – pair – share, p. 130</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the story to find out if you were right. Reading, p. 125  WB C5, p. 68</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline was really upset.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma tried to calm her down but Caroline didn’t want to listen.</sentence>
<sentence>“You know why I mucked it up?” she shouted angrily.</sentence>
<sentence>“It was just because of Moira’s friends – they pulled faces at me and now they’ve won.” “We should talk to Ms Walsh,” Emma suggested.</sentence>
<sentence>“And tell her I was tricked out?”, Caroline said.</sentence>
<sentence>“No way!</sentence>
<sentence>Then she’ll think I’m just telling a sob story because I want to get the leading role.</sentence>
<sentence>Anyway, Ms Walsh has offered me another job – she said I could be the prompter.</sentence>
<sentence>That’s OK.” Caroline tried to sound cool, but Emma knew that her friend was hurt.</sentence>
<sentence>On Friday it was drama group again.</sentence>
<sentence>Dear Diary, I feel awful.</sentence>
<sentence>At least I don’t have to be on stage with Moira.</sentence>
<sentence>The way she acts just makes me sick.</sentence>
<sentence>She ruins everything!!</sentence>
<sentence>All week Caroline was very gloomy.</sentence>
<sentence>When George asked her what was wrong, she didn’t answer.</sentence>
<sentence>So George asked Emma.</sentence>
<sentence>“That audition was just so unfair,” Emma said angrily.</sentence>
<sentence>“The first night with Moira will be a nightmare for Caroline.” George felt sorry for his sister.</sentence>
<sentence>He wasn’t that interested in drama, but he still thought it was unfair.</sentence>
<sentence>“We must do something to cheer her up,” he suggested.</sentence>
<sentence>“Hey, there’s a Popsicles concert on the day of the first performance.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe I can get some tickets for Caroline and me.” “What a great idea!” Emma answered.</sentence>
<sentence>“But I don’t think she can go.</sentence>
<sentence>You know she’s the prompter.</sentence>
<sentence>She has to be there like everyone else.” “But her job is backstage, so anyone can do it.</sentence>
<gap>A few days later, Caroline found an envelope in her room. Inside there were tickets for the Popsicles concert. Caroline couldn’t believe it …</gap>
<sentence>It was the last week before the play started.</sentence>
<sentence>The girls tried on their costumes.</sentence>
<sentence>The boys in the band were ready.</sentence>
<sentence>Everything was prepared.</sentence>
<sentence>But Ms Walsh was a bit worried.</sentence>
<sentence>Moira wasn’t very good.</sentence>
<sentence>She spoke clearly and knew her words, but she didn’t say them with feeling.</sentence>
<sentence>But it wasn’t only that.</sentence>
<sentence>Moira was often difficult and the other girls on the stage were often tense when Moira was around.</sentence>
<sentence>But it was too late now.</sentence>
<sentence>Finally, everyone was ready.</sentence>
<sentence>But where was Moira?</sentence>
<sentence>Ms Walsh was annoyed.</sentence>
<sentence>She was really fed up with Moira, who always pretended to be a star.</sentence>
<sentence>Finally, Moira arrived.</sentence>
<sentence>“Oh, Ms Walsh,” she whispered sweetly, “I need a microphone.” “What are you talking about?” Ms Walsh asked.</sentence>
<sentence>“Well, you can hear – I’ve lost my voice.</sentence>
<sentence>But maybe I can act my part with a microphone.” “The drama group always works without microphones – and if you have one, everyone will need one.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m afraid we can’t do it.” Moira looked at Ms Walsh coldly.</sentence>
<sentence>“Then we’ll have to postpone the play.” “Postpone the play?” Ms Walsh was shocked.</sentence>
<exercise>76 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='68'>
<chapter>4/C</chapter>
<exercise>C6 Choose a title for each part of the story and explain your choice. You can find different titles, too. P14  WB C6, p. 68</exercise>
<listing>The idea · Keeping cool · Dear Diary · Hard times · Lost voice · Real friends · Moira wins · The surprise · A new chance? · Winners and losers · A difficult choice</listing>
<gap>For part no. … I chose the title … because …</gap>
<exercise>C7</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … after the next meeting of the drama group ∙ … when Moira can’t act in the play</exercise>
<exercise>b) Caroline has got tickets for her favourite pop group – and she has the chance to take over Moira’s role. What would you do if you were Caroline and why? P6  WB C7, p. 69</exercise>
<exercise>C8 Look at the story again. Collect different words for say and adjectives/adverbs that show how a character feels.</exercise>
<exercise>C9 Target task v " Project  Portfolio P7 Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>1 2 3 4</exercise>
<sentence>Boo!</sentence>
<exercise>1 Look at the pictures and choose the ending you like best. Then write your ending to the story.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What happens exactly? How will the characters in the story react? ∙ Collect words and phrases for your story. Wordbank Entertainment, p 152; People, p. 153</exercise>
<exercise>3 Write the ending. Remember to …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … include adjectives/adverbs to describe the characters’ feelings and their actions. ∙ … use different words for say . You can use your results from C8.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Work in groups and read your stories to your group. Then correct them and choose the one you like best. Present the story to the class. Writing, p. 128  WB C8, p. 69</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventy-seven 77</footnote>
<exercise>a) Say how Caroline feels …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … when she talks to Emma after the audition</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … when she finds the tickets</exercise>
<exercise>2 Plan your ending:</exercise>
<sentence>How will they feel?</sentence>
<sentence>What will they say?</sentence>
<exercise>∙ … use the simple past.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … use direct speech (e. g. “OK, I can do it,” Caroline said.).</exercise>
</page>
<page id='69'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P1 Words: adjectives</exercise>
<sentence>Look at the adjectives.</sentence>
<sentence>Copy the grid and organize the words.</sentence>
<gap>amazing …</gap>
<gap>disappointed …</gap>
<listing>amazing · bad · beautiful · awful · wonderful · boring · perfect · silly · lovely · terrible · exciting · fantastic · fascinating · stupid</listing>
<exercise>P2 Listening  S 11, L 1/28 Listen to the friends again and finish the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 The music is … 2 The singers in the choir really … 3 They must put in …</exercise>
<exercise>4 Mr Gibson is … 5 He really has … 6 The audience …</exercise>
<exercise>P3 Words: suggest, disagree, agree, persuade a) Sort the phrases (suggest, disagree, agree, persuade).</exercise>
<gap>Let’s … Why not? I’m not sure. That sounds interesting, but … You must be joking. Maybe we could … What about …? To be honest, it doesn’t sound that good. It’s important that …</gap>
<gap>Sounds great! Can’t we …? Why don’t we …? Don't you think we should …? But just think about it … We could even … No way!</gap>
<gap>You’re right. I don’t think that this is a great idea. That’s a great idea. Don’t you think …? OK, let’s do it. I completely agree.</gap>
<exercise>b) Work with a partner. You are friends and want to spend Friday afternoon together. Make plans and try to persuade your friend to do what you have planned. Remember to be polite!</exercise>
<exercise>78 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='70'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P4 Writing a) Read the article about Rihanna and note down facts about her.</exercise>
<sentence>It featured the international hit singles “Umbrella”, “Don’t Stop the Music” and “Disturbia”.</sentence>
<sentence>The album won a Grammy.</sentence>
<sentence>She is also the official face of tourism for Barbados.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Use your notes from the article to create a profile.</exercise>
<gap>Name: Rihanna Date of birth: … Career: … Famous songs: … Hobbies/Interested in: … …</gap>
<exercise>1 record producer – Schallplattenproduzent; 2 release – veröffentlichen; 3 feature – enthalten; 4 foundation – Stiftung ; 5 appear – auftreten; 6 fragrance – Parfum</exercise>
<exercise>P5 Present perfect with for/since (1) LiF 10: Present perfect (for/since), p. 143 Play this game with a partner.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Write something you have/haven’t done on a piece of paper like this:</exercise>
<sentence>I haven’t done my homework.</sentence>
<exercise>2 Fold the paper so that your partner can’t see what you have written.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Give the paper to your partner. Don’t read what’s on the paper! Now write down a time with since or for .</exercise>
<exercise>4 Open the paper and read the sentence. I haven’t done my homework for three years.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventy-nine 79</footnote>
</page>
<page id='71'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P6 Reading Reading, p. 125 a) Look at C5 on page 76 again. Match the parts of the sentences.</exercise>
<sentence>Moira wasn’t there.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline was hurt.</sentence>
<sentence>Moira suggested they postpone the play.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Put the sentences in the correct order.</exercise>
<exercise>P7 Words: verbs and adverbs To make a story interesting you should include direct speech. Match the verbs to the adverbs, then make sentences.</exercise>
<sentence>Example: “Look, Roberta is talking to James,” Myra whispered excitedly.</sentence>
<sentence>“Oh no, Mr Grey is watching us,” Rajiv whispered nervously.</sentence>
<exercise>1 seriously – ernsthaft</exercise>
<exercise>P8 Present perfect with for/since (2) LiF 10: Present perfect (for/since), p. 143 Look at the pictures and say what these people have/haven’t done. Use the verbs and for/since . Example: He hasn't played football for three weeks.</exercise>
<listing>play · live · be · write · do · eat · have</listing>
<exercise>80 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='72'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P9 Revision: conditional clauses type I LiF 7: Bedingungssätze, Typ 1, p. 140 Choose four of these sentences and write down what you will/won’t do.</exercise>
<gap>What if …</gap>
<exercise>1 … I lose 1 my mobile phone? 2 … my favourite TV star sits next to me on the bus? 3 … they close the school?</exercise>
<exercise>4 … I find my diary on the Internet? 5 … I find €10,000? 6 … I see a pickpocket?</exercise>
<gap>Example: I will … if I lose my …</gap>
<exercise>1 lose – verlieren</exercise>
<exercise>P10 Present perfect or simple past? LiF 11: Present perfect or simple past, p. 143 Read the sentences and choose the correct form.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Mrs Carson lived/has lived in London since 2008. 2 She bought/has bought a small house in Camden in 2009. 3 She has got a sister, but she didn’t see/hasn’t seen her for a long time. 4 Her sister lived/has lived in India since 2010. 5 They were/have been very good friends when they were children. 6 Mrs Carson met/has met her husband five years ago. 7 At first she didn’t talk/hasn’t talked to him because she was/has been very shy 1 . 8 But then they went/have gone to a party together. They were/have been together since then.</exercise>
<exercise>1 shy – schüchtern</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words eighty-one 81</footnote>
</page>
<page id='73'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P11 Adjectives and adverbs of manner (1) LiF 12: Adverbien der Art und Weise, p. 144</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline can read very ???</sentence>
<sentence>(quick).</sentence>
<sentence>She is a ???</sentence>
<sentence>(quick) reader.</sentence>
<exercise>2. You can check your answers on page 221. 3. You need help? ’ Do a), then b). You can do it? ’ Do b).</exercise>
<exercise>a) Read the sentences and choose the correct form. 1 Caroline always learns her role (quick/quickly)</exercise>
<exercise>4 But when she is on stage her performance</exercise>
<exercise>b) Complete the sentences. Choose the correct form (adjective or adverb).</exercise>
<exercise>1 The boys in the band can sing very (good). 2 That’s why their fans think the band is (amazing). 3 Ben has a (fantastic) voice. 4 Chris plays the guitar 1 (perfect).</exercise>
<exercise>1 guitar – Gitarre</exercise>
<exercise>5 Their friend Stephen has (great)</exercise>
<exercise>P12 Adjectives and adverbs of manner: exceptions 1 LiF 12: Adverbien der Art und Weise, p. 144 a) What are the missing adjectives/adverbs? Copy the grid and fill in the correct forms.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Write down six sentences and use the adjectives/adverbs from a). Add two more sentences with look and feel .</exercise>
<exercise>1 exception – Ausnahme</exercise>
<exercise>P13 Adjectives and adverbs of manner (2) LiF 12: Adverbien der Art und Weise, p. 144 a) Choose adjectives or adverbs for the text about the audition.</exercise>
<listing>worriedly · cool · clearly · quiet · dark · good · nervous · excitedly · excited · small · brilliant · sunny · worried · rainy · big · quietly · nervously · arrogantly · coolly · loudly · bored</listing>
<sentence>First there were the auditions for the leading role.</sentence>
<exercise>82 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='74'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>b) Find a partner who has chosen other adjectives/adverbs and read your texts to each other. Decide which fit better.</exercise>
<exercise>P14 Sounds  S 13, L 1/34 Find the first letters of these words and say the words. Do you say /v/ or /w/? Then listen and check.</exercise>
<exercise>P15 Reading Reading, p. 125</exercise>
<sentence>Work with a partner.</sentence>
<sentence>The other chooses the correct phrase and reads the poster to answer the questions.</sentence>
<exercise>1 So quiz night is on Friday – that’s what the poster says. 2 I’m babysitting from 9pm to 10pm.</exercise>
<sentence>Is that OK for quiz night?</sentence>
<listing>Pupils only have to pay … · That’s OK. · Don’t worry. · There’s a new … · The quiz takes place … · I’m afraid not. · Quiz night is from … to … · The price includes … · That’s right, but … · Well, …</listing>
<exercise>P16 Say it in English Look at Theme 4 again and find the answers. Was sagst du auf Englisch, wenn du … 1 … etwas vorschlagen willst? 2 … wissen willst, was mit jemandem los ist? 3 … etwas toll findest? 4 … jemanden sagen willst, dass er sich keine Sorgen machen soll?</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words eighty-three 83</footnote>
</page>
<page id='75'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>O1 Reading, p. 125 Monstroso by Charlie Higson is a story about Oscar, a boy who plays on his dad’s computer although he is not allowed to do so.</exercise>
<sentence>Before you read the story, start a word web with computer words.</sentence>
<sentence>Which words do you also use in German?</sentence>
<sentence>Which are different?</sentence>
<exercise>O2 a) Look at this sentence from the story and speculate what the story is about: "There on the desktop was the image of a clenched fist 1 with the words P RO j ECT x written across it in red."</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the story and add more words to your word web from O1.</exercise>
<sentence>He knew he shouldn’t touch the computer.</sentence>
<sentence>He’d promised Dad.</sentence>
<sentence>He knew it was very special and important for Dad’s work.</sentence>
<sentence>He knew it was blah-di-blah-di-blah ...</sentence>
<sentence>There on the desktop was the image of a clenched fist with the words PROJECT X written across it in red.</sentence>
<sentence>It was a computer.</sentence>
<sentence>A COMPUTER!</sentence>
<sentence>And Oscar LOVED computers.</sentence>
<sentence>It was a shortcut to a program ... Why hadn’t Oscar noticed it before?</sentence>
<sentence>Before he even knew what he was doing, he found himself [...] pressing the power switch.</sentence>
<sentence>[...] He was sure the icon hadn’t been there before.</sentence>
<sentence>Had it somehow magically appeared?</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t be stupid.</sentence>
<sentence>Well, now that it had popped up, there was only one thing to do with it ...</sentence>
<sentence>Click on it.</sentence>
<sentence>That was what icons were for ...</sentence>
<sentence>He couldn’t find anything interesting.</sentence>
<sentence>[...] Even the games on it would probably all be rubbish.</sentence>
<sentence>It was worth a look, though ...</sentence>
<sentence>PROJECT X.</sentence>
<sentence>What could it be?</sentence>
<sentence>Oscar nervously moved the pointer over it, afraid to click.</sentence>
<sentence>He found the games folder and opened it.</sentence>
<sentence>He scrolled down the list.</sentence>
<sentence>He took a deep breath and clicked.</sentence>
<sentence>For a moment nothing happened.</sentence>
<sentence>Just as he’d thought.</sentence>
<sentence>All the same boring games you got on any computer.</sentence>
<sentence>What had he done?</sentence>
<sentence>A chess game!</sentence>
<sentence>[...] He closed the folder.</sentence>
<sentence>And then he spotted something.</sentence>
<sentence>Two words appeared on the screen.</sentence>
<exercise>1 clenched fist – geballte Faust 4 waggle – wackeln (an) 7 trigger – auslösen 2 climb – klettern 5 chess – Schach 8 glow – leuchten 3 peer – gucken 6 groan – stöhnen 9 throb – pochen</exercise>
<exercise>84 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='76'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<sentence>Oscar typed in Dad’s name.</sentence>
<sentence>Oscar began to work his way through them.</sentence>
<sentence>DO YOU WISH TO PROCEED, BRIAN?</sentence>
<sentence>Oscar clicked on YES.</sentence>
<sentence>ENTER PASSWORD Oscar knew the answer to that as well.</sentence>
<sentence>He clicked YES and it was done.</sentence>
<sentence>PROCEED, BRIAN.</sentence>
<sentence>Yes!</sentence>
<exercise>10 imaginative – einfallsreich 11 accidentally on purpose – aus Versehen mit Absicht</exercise>
<exercise>12 steel shutter – Stahlklappe 13 slam shut – zuknallen 14 reveal – zeigen</exercise>
<exercise>15 battle-scarred – vom Kampf gezeichnet 16 greedy – gierig 17 warrior – Krieger</exercise>
<exercise>O3 a) Were you right in O2? Say why/why not.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Draw a picture of the warrior and describe him.</exercise>
<exercise>O4 Writing, p. 128 What might happen next? How could the story end? Draw a comic or write the story down. You can also use your computer words from O1.</exercise>
<gap>Du kannst schon viel auf Englisch verstehen und ausdrücken. Du kannst …</gap>
<exercise>3 über Veranstaltungen an deiner Schule sprechen 3 einen Artikel über ein Ereignis schreiben</exercise>
<exercise>3 einen Dialog verfassen und vorspielen 3 deinen Lieblingssong vorstellen 3 eine Geschichte vortragen 3 erklären, wie jemand etwas macht 3 das Ende einer Geschichte verfassen  WB Portfolio-Fragebogen Theme 4</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words eighty-five 85</footnote>
</page>
<page id='77'>
<chapter>5/A</chapter>
<sentence>Green Week or the Mill?</sentence>
<exercise>A1 In class talk about special events, trips and activities that take place at your school and note them down. LiF 1R, p. 133, LiF 2R, p. 135, LiF 8, p. 140/141  WB A1, A2, p. 77</exercise>
<gap>Every year we have a project week. Then we …</gap>
<gap>Last year we went to …/ organized …/ took part in …</gap>
<gap>I have already acted in the school play/played for the school team/…</gap>
<gap>There are always concerts/ music shows/dance shows/ … at our school in …</gap>
<exercise>A2</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Group A reads the report about Green Week.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … who? ∙ … what? ∙ … where? ∙ … when? ∙ … why? Reading, p. 125</exercise>
<exercise>b) Work with a partner who read the other report. Use your notes from a) to explain what your report is about.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Which report do you find more interesting? Say why.</exercise>
<sentence>“What’s going on at CSG?</sentence>
<sentence>Why are there so many people in green?” That is what many people asked when they walked past CSG last week in the first Green Week at our school.</sentence>
<sentence>It was a very informative experience about the world that we live in and what we can do to save it.</sentence>
<sentence>Each day had a different motto.</sentence>
<sentence>Thank you to everyone who took part in the projects.</sentence>
<sentence>Please remember your green pledges.</sentence>
<exercise>15 talked about recycling waste. Some of our pupils and others donated to buy solar panels for our</exercise>
<sentence>On Friday, we used green handprints to form a tree.</sentence>
<sentence>There is always more that we can do – but we have taken the first big step and the first Green Week at our school was a great success.</sentence>
<exercise>86 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>a) Divide the class into two groups.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Group B reads the report about the Mill.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Make notes on …</exercise>
</page>
<page id='78'>
<chapter>5/A</chapter>
<exercise>A3  L 1/35 a) The Lambrakis talk about George’s trip to the Mill and Caroline’s Green Week. Listen to them and find out what George and Caroline are going to do at the Mill/Green Week. Take notes. Listening, p. 124</exercise>
<exercise>b) v Extra: Would you like to have a Green Week at your school or go to the Mill? Say why/why not. Your notes from a) can help you.</exercise>
<exercise>A4 Look at the elements of a report below. Read the reports again and find examples of them.</exercise>
<exercise>1 a headline 2 an entertaining beginning 3 a person’s statement 4 details of an activity/event 5 a sentence that refers back to the title</exercise>
<gap>On Monday, for example, we all watched …  WB A3, A4, p. 78, 79</gap>
<exercise>A5 Target task v P1, P7 Need help? Look at p. 96. ∙ Choose an event at your school and write a report about it for the English version</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Prepare a school radio report in English about an event at your school. Present it to the class.</exercise>
<exercise>Support ∙ Look at your list from A1 and choose one event ∙ Look at the reports in A2 again. Collect words and phrases that you can use with your report.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Your report should answer the questions who, what, where, when and why .</exercise>
<sentence>It is just one hour and a half on the motorway, but for many pupils it is like a fascinating trip into another world.</sentence>
<sentence>“First I thought, ‘Oh no, boring walks and lots of biology and geography exercises.’ But it turned out to be lots of fun,” Jeremy Fowler said when he came back.</sentence>
<sentence>During the week, the pupils made posters about the birds which you can find at the Mill.</sentence>
<sentence>With football and other games, there was a lot of exciting entertainment – even if some boys were not happy that there were no supermarkets or shops nearby.</sentence>
<sentence>But this is what makes the Mill so special.</sentence>
<sentence>“I haven’t really thought much about birds and other wild animals – we don’t see them much in Camden.</sentence>
<sentence>But it’s almost magic to be away from the traffic and the noise of London for a few days,” Manish Malik said about his experience.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words eighty-seven 87</footnote>
<exercise>∙ To structure your report, you can use A4.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='79'>
<chapter>5/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 Think – pair – share: What can you do to protect the environment? Think – pair – share, p. 130 Wordbank Environment, p. 152</exercise>
<exercise>a) Write down as many ideas as you can. You have got one minute.</exercise>
<listing>recycle paper · turn off … when … · use …, not … · go by bike when …</listing>
<exercise>b) Compare your list with a partner’s and add new words. … …</exercise>
<exercise>c) Work in groups and share your ideas.</exercise>
<exercise>d) In class group your ideas like this: go by bike</exercise>
<exercise>B2  L 1/36 a) Listen to Caroline and her mother and find out what the pupils do for Green Week that day. Listening, p. 124</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and complete the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 All pupils at Camden School for Girls have to …</exercise>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<exercise>2 Mrs Lambraki doesn’t understand why Caroline doesn’t … 3 When Caroline goes by bike, she can … 4 Mrs Lambraki doesn’t know if Caroline’s bike … 5 The bike doctor … 6 Caroline doesn’t want to take Mrs Lambraki’s bike because …</exercise>
<exercise>B3 a) In art class that morning, Caroline and her classmates design new signs that tell people how to protect the environment. Look at the posters and write down the tips/rules.</exercise>
<gap>Example: You should turn off the lights when you leave the room. You mustn’t/shouldn’t …</gap>
<listing>turn off · recycle leave on standby go by … · throw away</listing>
<exercise>b) Use your ideas from B1 to design your own poster. Show it to a partner. He/She must say what your poster is about. Wordbank Environment, p. 152 P8  WB B1, p. 80</exercise>
<exercise>88 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='80'>
<chapter>5/B</chapter>
<exercise>B4  L 1/37 a) Close your books and listen to Caroline and Emma and their teacher, Mrs Perry. Find out which two topics they are talking about. Listening, p. 124  WB B2, p. 80</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … Caroline feels angry ∙ … George is happy ∙ …the girls are excited</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline: I can’t stand George these days.</sentence>
<sentence>He can’t stop telling me how fantastic his trip to the Mill will be.</sentence>
<sentence>He thinks he’ll be able to do whatever he wants there.</sentence>
<gap>Emma: Will we all be allowed to talk to them? Mrs Perry: I’m sorry, no. Just two of you will be able to talk to the reporter. So who wants to take part in the interview? … OK … There are</gap>
<gap>Emma: Really? That’s just not fair! Yesterday we weren’t even allowed to take a break until we finished our projects … and they can relax</gap>
<sentence>So now we have to choose the two girls who’ll represent the class.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s have a vote.</sentence>
<sentence>He’s just so lazy!</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: Ssh, there’s Mrs Perry.</sentence>
<sentence>Mrs Perry: Good morning, girls.</sentence>
<sentence>Before we go on with our Green Week projects, there’s something I have to tell you.</sentence>
<sentence>You probably all know the TV station ‘CamdenTV’.</sentence>
<sentence>Green Week for tomorrow’s evening news.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Wow, cool!</sentence>
<sentence>Emma.</sentence>
<sentence>Congratulations!</sentence>
<exercise>B5 Grammar card: modal verbs and their substitutes 1 You already know the modal verb can . You can only use it in the present tense. For other tenses, you need a substitute verb. Look at line 3 in B4 and say what the substitute verb is.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Check LiF 13 on page 145 and find out about the substitute verbs of must/mustn’t, may and needn’t . Write a grammar card. P9  WB B3, p. 81</exercise>
<exercise>B6 The reporter gives Caroline and Emma some advice for the interview.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ they will be allowed to do/won’t be allowed to do</exercise>
<exercise>∙ speak slowly and clearly ∙ no “hello” to friends</exercise>
<exercise>∙ no white or striped shirt</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words eighty-nine 89</footnote>
<exercise>b) Listen again and explain why …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ they will have to do/won’t have to do</exercise>
<exercise>∙ use short sentences</exercise>
<exercise>∙ be polite</exercise>
<exercise>∙ no chewing gum</exercise>
<exercise>∙ normal clothes OK</exercise>
</page>
<page id='81'>
<chapter>5/B</chapter>
<exercise>B7  L 1/38 After the lesson, Caroline calls her mother to tell her about the TV interview. a) Read Caroline’s answers and find out what Mrs Lambraki’s questions are. LiF 6: will future, p. 139, LiF 2R: Simple past, p. 135</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline: Hi, Mum!</sentence>
<sentence>Guess what!</sentence>
<gap>I’ll be on TV tomorrow! Mrs Lambraki: Oh! What will you …?</gap>
<gap>Mrs Lambraki: …? Caroline: Emma will be with me. Isn’t that cool? Mrs Lambraki: Yes, but …?</gap>
<gap>answer some questions. Mrs Lambraki: …?</gap>
<gap>Caroline: We will have to answer some questions about Green Week – if we like it … erm, you know. We</gap>
<sentence>Caroline: The interview will be about Green Week.</sentence>
<gap>are super excited! We’ll be on TV!!! Mrs Lambraki: …?</gap>
<gap>Mrs Lambraki: …? Caroline: The TV people didn’t choose me. My class voted for me. But I won’t be the only one.</gap>
<sentence>Caroline: I’m not sure.</sentence>
<sentence>I think it will be on at six o’clock.</sentence>
<sentence>Oh, I have to go, Mum.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma wants to talk to me now.</sentence>
<sentence>Bye!</sentence>
<exercise>b) Now listen to the conversation and check if your questions are correct. P2</exercise>
<exercise>B8  L 1/39 a) Read the interview. Who is more nervous – Caroline or Emma? Say why you think so.</exercise>
<sentence>Emma: Oh no, I’ll make a fool of myself.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Emma, you needn’t worry.</sentence>
<sentence>The TV people can cut out the bits where we say something wrong.</sentence>
<sentence>It won’t be live.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Yes, yes, so we produce a mountain of rubbish every year.</sentence>
<exercise>5 TV reporter: Ready, girls? Then let’s start … paper and … paper … I mean, paper and …</exercise>
<sentence>We’re here at Camden School for Girls today, where we will find out more about their Green Week.</sentence>
<gap>Emma: … plastic and glass and other materials</gap>
<exercise>10 Butler – who can tell us what is going on at we can?</exercise>
<gap>called Green Week, Emma? Emma: It’s called Green Week … because we do a lot of projects about the environment.</gap>
<sentence>Emma: No, recycling isn’t enough.</sentence>
<exercise>15 Caroline: Yes, we cover topics like energy, waste, I’ve heard that some pupils have made</exercise>
<sentence>Every day has a different motto.</sentence>
<sentence>TV reporter: That sounds interesting.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: That’s right.</sentence>
<exercise>20 Caroline? wanted to throw away. They used them to</exercise>
<gap>Caroline: Today our topic is waste. We throw away so much … erm … plastic …erm … We throw away so much … erm … plastic and …</gap>
<sentence>TV reporter: It sounds as if you liked the smoothies, but how do you feel about Green Week as a whole?</sentence>
<exercise>90 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='82'>
<chapter>5/B</chapter>
<gap>than … erm … normal lessons.</gap>
<sentence>Emma: Caroline’s right.</sentence>
<exercise>60 65</exercise>
<sentence>Do you agree?</sentence>
<sentence>Emma: That’s true.</sentence>
<sentence>Everyone had to walk to school or go by bike yesterday.</sentence>
<sentence>A lot of pupils usually go by bus.</sentence>
<sentence>TV reporter: Thank you very much, Emma and Caroline.</sentence>
<sentence>That was it.</sentence>
<sentence>You did a very good job.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Guess how Caroline and Emma feel after the interview.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Say what happened at Green Week. What do you think of the activities? How would you like them?</exercise>
<exercise>d) Note down words and phrases that show that you want to understand/ are interested in/are listening to what the other person says. P3  WB B6, B7, p. 83 Example: That sounds interesting; Do you mean …</exercise>
<exercise>B9 Target task v Write an interview and act it out.</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<sentence>Work with a partner.</sentence>
<sentence>One of you is a TV reporter and the other is a pupil at CSG.</sentence>
<sentence>The reporter interviews the pupil about Green Week.</sentence>
<exercise>1 Together think about what you are going to talk about. Here are some ideas:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ go to a supermarket and find out where the fruit and vegetables come from</exercise>
<exercise>2 Read your role cards and prepare your roles.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the reason why pupils do them</exercise>
<exercise>∙ what you have done ∙ if you liked it and why</exercise>
<exercise>3 Take turns to write down your questions and answers. The phrases from B8d) can help you.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Practise your interview, then act it out for another pair. Give feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127 P13</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words ninety-one 91</footnote>
<exercise>∙ wear warm pullovers to show that you can keep warm without central heating</exercise>
<exercise>∙ plant vegetables in the school garden</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … Wordbank Environment, p. 152</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the activities</exercise>
<exercise>∙ if the pupils like them and why</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the reasons</exercise>
</page>
<page id='83'>
<chapter>5/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 Remember your last class trip: what were you allowed/not allowed to do? Write down the rules.  WB C1, p. 84</exercise>
<exercise>C2 Before George’s class go to the Mill, the parents get a letter from the school. Read the letter and find out more about the Mill. P14</exercise>
<listing>Highgate Road · London NW5 1RN</listing>
<sentence>I’m sure they’ll have a great week.</sentence>
<sentence>Please make sure that your child brings camping things (a sleeping bag, a small rucksack, a plastic cup and plate, a knife, fork and spoon), enough clothes for a week, toothbrush/soap, a hat and an exercise book or diary.</sentence>
<sentence>There are some games at the Mill, but pupils may also bring their own cards, games or books.</sentence>
<sentence>The children do not need to bring any extra food.</sentence>
<sentence>There will be three meals a day.</sentence>
<sentence>Pupils who are not able to eat certain foods or pupils who take medicine must bring a note with them and talk to Mr Glover before the trip.</sentence>
<sentence>If your child breaks the rules, we will ask you to come to the Mill and pick up your child immediately.</sentence>
<sentence>The pupils can walk to Forest Green, a small village near the Mill.</sentence>
<sentence>There are no shops in Forest Green.</sentence>
<sentence>They will be able to buy food, drinks, pens, pencils, etc.</sentence>
<sentence>Many thanks for your help.</sentence>
<exercise>C3 C4  S 14, L 1/40 a) Make a list of rules for the trip and compare a) The boys are not very happy about the rules. them to the rules for your class trips. Listen to them and note down their arguments.</exercise>
<sentence>Discuss which rules you find sensible, too strict or silly.</sentence>
<exercise>92 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='84'>
<chapter>5/C</chapter>
<exercise>C5  L 2/1 a) Close your books and listen to the boys. Find out where they are.</exercise>
<sentence>George: But this isn’t yours.</sentence>
<sentence>Holden: But it looks like mine!</sentence>
<gap>Holden: OK, but the music must be awful. George: It’s not that bad. … Hey, Rajiv, give us one of those bags of crisps. Whose are they anyway?</gap>
<sentence>George: Well, it’s Sam’s.</sentence>
<sentence>Holden: It can’t be his.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: They’re not mine.</sentence>
<sentence>John and Leo are sitting here.</sentence>
<sentence>The bags are theirs.</sentence>
<sentence>George: I know, but he brought his sister’s.</sentence>
<sentence>Holden: What?</sentence>
<sentence>He pinched his sister’s player?</sentence>
<gap>to the front to talk to Stephen. … Oh, there they are. Hey, Leo, those crisps – are they yours?</gap>
<sentence>It’s hers?</sentence>
<sentence>Oh, she’ll go mad.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Read the dialogue. Find out which words the boys use for the following expressions:</exercise>
<exercise>c) Look at LiF 14 on page 146 and</exercise>
<sentence>Leo: Yes, but we mustn’t eat them on the coach.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s have them later in the tents.</sentence>
<listing>your MP3 player · my MP3 player · Sam’s MP3 player · his sister’s MP3 player · my crisps · their bags · those crisps</listing>
<exercise>C6  L 2/2</exercise>
<exercise>a) Look at the pictures on this page and page 94. Speculate about what might happen at the Mill.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the story to find out if you were right. P4</exercise>
<sentence>It was a quiet night at the Mill.</sentence>
<sentence>The boys were all very tired after the long trip and a day full of activities.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv was in a tent with George.</sentence>
<sentence>There were two boys in every tent.</sentence>
<sentence>Only Jason, who slept next to George and Rajiv, was alone in his tent.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv and George didn’t know Jason very well because he was very quiet.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv and George were asleep in their tent.</sentence>
<sentence>Suddenly, they woke up.</sentence>
<sentence>“Get off, get off!</sentence>
<sentence>!” somebody screamed.</sentence>
<sentence>It was Jason.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv and George got up and looked out of their tent.</sentence>
<sentence>Then they laughed.</sentence>
<sentence>“Hey Jason, it’s only the tent!</sentence>
<sentence>Then they heard an angry voice outside.</sentence>
<sentence>The next morning, Jason got up early.</sentence>
<sentence>He wanted to do everything right that day.</sentence>
<sentence>“What are you doing?” It was their teacher, Mr Glover.</sentence>
<sentence>“Come on, Jason.</sentence>
<sentence>He didn’t want to be late.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words ninety-three 93</footnote>
</page>
<page id='85'>
<chapter>5/C</chapter>
<sentence>Rajiv and George got up later.</sentence>
<sentence>They didn’t have time to take a shower and got dressed quickly.</sentence>
<sentence>“Why don’t we help you go home?” Michael said with a strange laugh.</sentence>
<sentence>“Hurry up,” Rajiv said to George.</sentence>
<sentence>They saw Jason a few metres away.</sentence>
<sentence>“Come on, Jason.</sentence>
<sentence>We’ll be late for breakfast,” George said.</sentence>
<sentence>“Leave me alone,” he said and ran away.</sentence>
<exercise>30 “I don’t know,” said Jason. “I can’t find them.” Jason and Mr</exercise>
<sentence>“Oh, Jason.</sentence>
<sentence>Here, you can wear my brown shoes,” Rajiv said.</sentence>
<sentence>At breakfast, Mr Glover stood up.</sentence>
<sentence>“This morning I found these shoes by the river,” he said and held up a wet pair of shoes.</sentence>
<sentence>“You all know you’re not allowed to go down there without a teacher.</sentence>
<sentence>The owner should come and see me after breakfast.” Everyone knew whose shoes they were and Jason felt terrible again.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv and George felt sorry for him, but they saw a few boys laugh.</sentence>
<sentence>And the day only got worse for Jason.</sentence>
<sentence>When the boys did a quiz, Jason lost.</sentence>
<sentence>And he was late for lunch.</sentence>
<sentence>When one of the pupils found it and gave it to Mr Glover, it looked terrible.</sentence>
<sentence>It was very dirty and Mr Glover said, “This looks like it has come straight from the bin.” Jason went red in the face when all the other boys laughed.</sentence>
<gap>Later, Jason sat near the tents. George saw him and said, “Hi Jason, I guess you’ve had quite a bad day.” “Yeah,“ said Jason. “Mr Glover is really angry with me. But you know what? I didn’t really …”</gap>
<sentence>Just then two other boys walked up to them.</sentence>
<sentence>It was Michael and Matt.</sentence>
<sentence>They were the class clowns.</sentence>
<sentence>They often played tricks on other boys and were always in trouble.</sentence>
<sentence>Matt had something small and red in his hands.</sentence>
<sentence>“Hey, Jason, are you having a bad day?” he said.</sentence>
<sentence>Glover weren’t at dinner.</sentence>
<sentence>He was upset.</sentence>
<sentence>“Now, you may have noticed that Jason isn’t here,” he said to the boys.</sentence>
<sentence>“When we checked the tents, we found this red pocket knife under Jason’s sleeping bag.</sentence>
<sentence>We told you that you mustn’t bring knives to the Mill.</sentence>
<sentence>George looked at the red knife, then he looked at Matt and Michael.</sentence>
<sentence>They were smiling.</sentence>
<sentence>Suddenly George knew where he had seen the knife before – in Matt’s hand that afternoon!</sentence>
<sentence>George knew it wasn’t Jason’s knife and now he knew why Jason was so frightened and unhappy.</sentence>
<sentence>“Matt and Michael are bullying him!” he thought.</sentence>
<sentence>But George didn’t know what to do.</sentence>
<sentence>Should he tell Rajiv?</sentence>
<sentence>Should he tell Mr Glover?</sentence>
<sentence>But Jason’s parents were on the way already.</sentence>
<sentence>Should he talk to Matt and Michael?</sentence>
<sentence>What was the right thing to do?</sentence>
<exercise>c) What should George do? I think he should/ shouldn’t … What shouldn’t he do?</exercise>
<exercise>d) Hot seat: Write down questions you would like to ask the different characters in the story. Choose pupils to be the characters and interview them. You can make up the answers. Hot seat, p. 130 P5</exercise>
<gap>George, why Mr Glover, did you notice …? didn’t you …?</gap>
<gap>Matt and Jason, did you think you Michael, why…? could …?</gap>
<exercise>94 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='86'>
<chapter>5/C</chapter>
<exercise>C7 Mr Glover has phoned Jason’s parents. But before they arrive he talks to Jason. Read what he says to him. How does Jason react? Can you think of a reason?</exercise>
<gap>Mr Glover: Jason, I’m really disappointed in you. I always thought you were a nice, quiet boy. But you were late for meals. The shoes I found at the river were yours … And the geography project you gave me was a mess – but you had done some work, so I thought I would give you another chance. But when we found the knife you hid in your tent – that was the limit, boy. You read the letter that explained the rules before the trip, didn’t you?</gap>
<exercise>C8 v Extra: Grammar card: contact clauses</exercise>
<sentence>Jason: Yes, sir.</sentence>
<sentence>Jason: Yes.</sentence>
<sentence>Jason: I’m sorry, sir.</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Glover: Well, so am I. I’ve phoned your parents, who are very upset.</sentence>
<sentence>And I’m sure your classmates will be very disappointed, too.</sentence>
<exercise>1 You know relative clauses with the relative pronouns who, which and that . Here is an example from C7: You read the letter that explained the rules before the trip.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Now look at this sentence from C7: The shoes I found at the river were yours. This relative clause doesn’t have a relative pronoun. It is called a contact clause . Look at C7 again and find more examples of contact clauses.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Check LiF 15 on page 147 to find out when you can leave out the relative pronoun. Write a grammar card for contact clauses. Add your examples. P6  WB C4, p. 85</exercise>
<exercise>C9 v Extra a) How much do you remember about the story? Match the sentence halves.</exercise>
<exercise>1 The school sent a letter with rules 2 Matt and Michael are the boys 3 Mr Glover found the shoes 4 Mr Glover found the knife 5 Matt and Michael often play tricks 6 Mr Glover talked to Jason’s parents,</exercise>
<sentence>A that Michael and Matt threw in the river.</sentence>
<sentence>B which Michael and Matt put in Jason’s tent.</sentence>
<sentence>C that everybody knew about.</sentence>
<sentence>D which the others don’t like.</sentence>
<sentence>E that bullied Jason.</sentence>
<sentence>F who were very upset.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Look at the sentences again. Where can you leave out the relative pronoun? Note down these sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>C10 Target task v  Portfolio Write a letter.</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<sentence>Look at pp.</sentence>
<sentence>George has decided to write a letter to Mr Glover.</sentence>
<exercise>∙ what really happened at the Mill</exercise>
<exercise>∙ what should happen to Jason, Matt, Michael</exercise>
<exercise>2 This is a letter to a teacher. Be polite. Start with “Dear Mr Glover, …” and finish with “Yours sincerely, George Lambraki” . Writing, p. 128 Then give your letter to a partner and read his/ her letter. Give feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127  WB C5, C6, p. 86</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words ninety-five 95</footnote>
<exercise>1 Plan the letter. Think about</exercise>
<exercise>∙ whose fault it was</exercise>
<exercise>∙ why George didn’t say anything at the Mill</exercise>
</page>
<page id='87'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P1 Writing a) Match the parts of the report to their function.</exercise>
<exercise>1 A personal statement … 2 An entertaining beginning … 3 A sentence that refers back</exercise>
<gap>to the title … 4 Details … 5 A headline …</gap>
<gap>A … makes the readers more interested</gap>
<gap>so that they read on. B … is usually at the end of a report. C … helps the readers to find out about the feelings</gap>
<gap>of the people in the report. D … tells the readers what the report is about. E … can help the readers to imagine what happened.</gap>
<exercise>b) Look at a) again and say which parts of a report you can see here.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Year 7 at London Zoo</exercise>
<sentence>Who doesn’t like looking at gorillas?</sentence>
<sentence>The pupils spent a day at London Zoo.</sentence>
<sentence>They took part in a “Green Team Challenge” about the problems of gorillas today.</sentence>
<sentence>They watched the gorillas, found out about the danger to them in Africa and learned what we can do to save them.</sentence>
<sentence>“I usually just look at the animals for fun, but I never thought about their situation in Africa,” said Danny Mumbanga.</sentence>
<sentence>“Now I know more about what we can do to help.” His teacher, Mr Scott, agreed.</sentence>
<sentence>“It isn’t the same if we talk about animals in class and how you can save them.</sentence>
<exercise>1 danger – Gefahr 2 collect – einsammeln 3 survive – überleben</exercise>
<exercise>96 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='88'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P2 Revision: simple present (questions) Caroline and her classmates have prepared a quiz for Green Week, but now the questions are missing. Write down the questions. LiF 1Rc: Simple present, p. 134 Example: Where should your food come from?</exercise>
<sentence>Your food should come from your area so that you don’t need much energy to transport it.</sentence>
<sentence>You can save energy if you turn off the lights, the computer, the TV etc.</sentence>
<sentence>This sign means that you can recycle this product.</sentence>
<exercise>1 rubbish bin – Mülltonne 2 heating – Heizung 3 tap – Wasserhahn</exercise>
<exercise>P3 Words: an interview A reporter in Camden wants to interview Karen, a pupil at CSG. Copy the interview and add some of the phrases from B8d) (page 91) to make the interview more interesting. Example: Reporter: That sounds interesting. What did you do?</exercise>
<sentence>It seems to be a great event.</sentence>
<sentence>Karen: Yes.</sentence>
<sentence>We do lots of projects.</sentence>
<sentence>Reporter: What did you do?</sentence>
<sentence>Reporter: What do you think about it?</sentence>
<sentence>Karen: We must all start to change.</sentence>
<sentence>Reporter: What will you do in future?</sentence>
<sentence>Reporter: OK, thanks.</sentence>
<exercise>1 climate – Klima</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words ninety-seven 97</footnote>
</page>
<page id='89'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P4 Connectives Match the sentence halves and use connectives. LiF 4: Connectives, p. 138</exercise>
<sentence>Jason is a very quiet boy.</sentence>
<sentence>Matt and Michael are bullying him.</sentence>
<sentence>Jason has to go home.</sentence>
<exercise>P5 Words: feelings Use these adjectives to say how Jason felt in the story on pages 93/94 …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ when Mr Glover held up his wet shoes.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ when George talked to him.</exercise>
<listing>scared · worried surprised · happy embarrassed · …</listing>
<exercise>P6 Contact clauses LiF 15: Contact clauses, p. 147</exercise>
<sentence>Can you leave out the relative pronoun?</sentence>
<sentence>Matt and Michael are the boys who are bullying Jason.</sentence>
<exercise>2. You can check your answers</exercise>
<sentence>You need help?</sentence>
<sentence>’ Do a), then b).</sentence>
<sentence>You can do it?</sentence>
<sentence>’ Do b).</sentence>
<sentence>George has seen the knife which Matt and Michael put in Jason’s tent.</sentence>
<exercise>a) Read the sentences and decide if you can leave out the relative pronoun. Write down the sentences without the relative pronoun.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Mr Glover is the teacher who went to the Mill with his class. 2 Jason is a quiet boy who George and Rajiv don’t know well. 3 Rajiv brings a brown bag to the Mill with all the things that he needs. 4 At the Mill the boys do a lot of projects which are very interesting.</exercise>
<exercise>1 dinner lady – Kantinenmitarbeiterin</exercise>
<exercise>5 They collect a lot of information which they have to write down in an exercise book. 6 There are dinner ladies 1 who are preparing the meals for the boys.</exercise>
<exercise>98 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ when he couldn’t find his shoes.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ when he lost the quiz.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ after Matt and Michael</exercise>
</page>
<page id='90'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>b) Look at the pictures and write down a sentence for each picture with a relative or a contact clause.</exercise>
<sentence>Example: These are the wet shoes that Mr Glover found at the river.</sentence>
<sentence>These are the wet shoes Mr Glover found at the river.</sentence>
<exercise>1 2 3</exercise>
<exercise>4 5 6</exercise>
<exercise>P7 Revision: relative clauses LiF 9: Relative clauses, p. 142 Emma’s brother Jack went to the Mill a few years ago. He shows Rajiv and George his photos. Write down what Jack might say. Example: This is the bed that I slept in. These are …</exercise>
<exercise>P8 Revision: modal verbs The Camden School for Girls’ head teacher wants to write ‘green rules’ for the school. Look at his ideas and turn them into rules. Use must/mustn’t, can, should/shouldn’t, needn’t.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ collect old paper and glass ∙ close the windows and doors to save energy</exercise>
<exercise>1 leave the tap running – den Wasserhahn laufen lassen 2 waste – verschwenden</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words ninety-nine 99</footnote>
<exercise>∙ walk to school</exercise>
<exercise>∙ use recycled paper</exercise>
<exercise>∙ keep the school tidy</exercise>
<exercise>∙ leave the tap running 1</exercise>
<exercise>∙ look after the school garden</exercise>
<exercise>∙ waste 2 paper</exercise>
</page>
<page id='91'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P9 Modal verbs and their substitutes (1) LiF 13: Modal verbs, p. 145/146 Sometimes Charlie and his mother have problems. Look at the picture and say what Mrs Batson might say to her son. Use must, have to, mustn’t, can’t, not allowed to .</exercise>
<exercise>P10 Modal verbs and their substitutes (2) LiF 13: Modal verbs, p. 145/146 Think about when you were six years old. What were/weren’t you allowed to do? What did/didn’t you have to do?</exercise>
<sentence>Write down six sentences and read them to a partner.</sentence>
<exercise>P11 Possessive pronouns LiF 14: Possessivpronomen, p. 146 The boys are at the Mill. Who do the things belong to? Read the dialogue and write down the missing pronouns.</exercise>
<sentence>Mr Glover: Now, this bag is huge – whose is it?</sentence>
<sentence>George: No, sir, I think it belongs to Matt and Michael.</sentence>
<sentence>They always pack their things together.</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Glover: Right, Rajiv, here you are.</sentence>
<gap>I think I saw Holden use it. So it must be 4 . Sam: Oh, no, that’s my MP3 player. George: But you said it isn’t 5 – it’s your sister’s. Sam: Well, yes, it’s 6 . But she gave it to me for the trip, Mr Glover. Mr Glover: Well, isn’t your sister nice. George: But Sam, you said that you pinched … ouch, Rajiv! Why are you kicking me? Mr Glover: OK, Sam, so it’s 7 . Here you are.</gap>
<exercise>100 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='92'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P12 Viewing: school rules  a) Watch the video clip to find out about the rules at Haverstock School. Note down five rules.</exercise>
<gap>Example: You have to … You are/aren’t allowed to …</gap>
<exercise>b) Work with a partner. Compare your results, then find out which of Haverstock School’s rules are rules at your school, too. Which school rules are stricter – yours or Haverstock School’s?</exercise>
<exercise>P13 Mediation  At the end of Green Week, the girls get a pledge card. Tell your teacher in German what the pledge card is about.</exercise>
<sentence>I promise to recycle everything that is recyclable, including clothes and shoes.</sentence>
<sentence>I promise to turn off the TV and not leave it on standby when I am not using it.</sentence>
<exercise>1 meat – Fleisch; 2 flight – Flug</exercise>
<exercise>P14 Reading Reading, p. 125 Right or wrong? Read the letter from William Ellis on page 92 again. Correct the wrong sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 The pupils must bring things to eat with them. 2 They mustn’t bring knives. 3 They can buy extra food at the shops in Forest Green.</exercise>
<exercise>P15 Listening  S 14, L 1/40 Listening, p. 124 Listen to the boys again and finish the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 George thinks that some rules for the trip</exercise>
<gap>to the Mill … 2 He can understand that computer games … 3 But he can’t understand why the pupils mustn’t …</gap>
<exercise>4 Pupils mustn’t bring their mobile phones. 5 Pupils are not allowed to walk to the village. 6 The pupils should bring £ 20 for drinks, pens and pencils.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Holden thinks computer games are OK</exercise>
<gap>because … 5 George doesn’t want to take his MP3</gap>
<gap>player because … 6 George says that they could …</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and one 101</footnote>
</page>
<page id='93'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>O1 a) Marty and his brother have to spend their holidays in the library while their mother is at work. Say how you would feel in their situation.</exercise>
<exercise>b) The two boys hate reading and they are scared of the strict librarian, Mrs Murphy. She says they must stay on a carpet in the children’s corner and mustn’t leave it. Speculate about what might happen. Then read the text to see if you were right. Reading, p. 125</exercise>
<sentence>Marty smiled.</sentence>
<sentence>“The best way to mess with a librarian is to put things back in the wrong place.</sentence>
<sentence>They hate that.</sentence>
<sentence>It drives them nuts.” Marty was an expert on messing with librarians.</sentence>
<gap>Marty’s mouth flapped. “But … I didn’t.“ Spud put her hands on her hips. “I know you didn’t, and I’m sure your mother will believe that. Unless of course you’ve been in trouble</gap>
<sentence>There had been several notes home from the school library.</sentence>
<sentence>“So I’m just going to switch a few books for Mrs Spud Murphy.</sentence>
<gap>home watching cartoons.” […] 45 Two hours and fourteen papercuts later, Marty</gap>
<sentence>One book at a time, he switched almost every single book in the section.</sentence>
<sentence>He put mysteries with romance, adventure with birdwatching and gardening with model aeroplanes.</sentence>
<gap>was finished. “That wasn’t so bad,” he said on the way to the exit. “I’ve had teachers meaner than her. […] Do you think she’ll really say I set off the fire extinguishers?” […]</gap>
<gap>be furious 1 . […] 50 Marty had started to wander over towards Spud.</gap>
<gap>Suddenly a shadow fell across my brother. […] Spud stood, slippered feet apart, with her hand hovering over the book stamps 2 on her belt. It was too late to warn him. There was nothing</gap>
<gap>[…] “Just one question, Mrs Murphy. You wouldn’t really say I set off the fire extinguishers, would you?” Spud smiled back at Marty. […]</gap>
<sentence>I could do.</sentence>
<gap>Spud’s left hand moved with lightning speed, grabbing the book stamp and throwing it in one smooth precise motion 3 . […] It was too late to move out of the way. All Marty could do was</gap>
<sentence>“I don’t think so.</sentence>
<sentence>Throwing a stamp is one thing.</sentence>
<gap>close his eyes and squeal like a kitten. […] 60 Spud opened the box on her desk. “I have a</gap>
<gap>“I knew it,” said Spud slowly. “I can always tell a troublemaker.” […] Marty stood slowly, no sudden moves. “I’m sorry, Spu– Mrs Murphy. I’ll never leave the</gap>
<sentence>One came in last week you might like.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s in the shape of a pirate flag.</sentence>
<gap>Spud slid across the floor on her slippers. “Too late for that. Since you’re already off the carpet, you can fix the damage 4 you’ve done. […] You get these in order by the time your mother</gap>
<sentence>Marty was already rolling up his sleeve.</sentence>
<sentence>“No, I’d love that.</sentence>
<sentence>On my arm.</sentence>
<sentence>Wait until the lads in the swimming pool see this.” Spud selected a stamp, inking it on a blue pad.</sentence>
<sentence>“I’m sure.</sentence>
<sentence>Stamp away.” “Well, if you’re sure.” Spud’s smile widened.</sentence>
<exercise>102 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='94'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<sentence>“OK, then.</sentence>
<sentence>Keep still.” The librarian rolled the rubber stamp across Marty’s forearm.</sentence>
<sentence>Across and back, three times.</sentence>
<sentence>When she removed the stamp, we leaned in to examine the pirate ship.</sentence>
<gap>Marty couldn’t speak. If anyone saw those words on his forearm, he’d be teased for all eternity 8 . […] We walked to the door. Marty held his arm in front of him as though it belonged to</gap>
<sentence>It was a short sentence of three words.</sentence>
<sentence>The words were: I LOVE BARBIE.</sentence>
<sentence>“Oops,” said Spud.</sentence>
<sentence>“Wrong stamp.</sentence>
<sentence>Spud called to him as he opened the door.</sentence>
<exercise>80 that.”</exercise>
<exercise>1 furious – sehr wütend 2 stamp – Stempel 3 in one smooth precise motion – in einer flüssigen und präzisen Bewegung</exercise>
<exercise>4 fix the damage – den Schaden beheben 5 fire extinguishers – Feuerlöscher 6 he had met his match – er hatte seinen Meister gefunden 7 forearm – Unterarm</exercise>
<exercise>8 eternity – Ewigkeit</exercise>
<exercise>O2 How to work with a dictionary, p. 129</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … somebody is very angry about something ∙ … go on and put the stamp on my arm</exercise>
<exercise>O3 Which of the following statements sums up the story best? 1 Mrs Murphy knows how to deal with difficult kids, so she teaches Marty a lesson. 2 Marty always wants to see what he can get away with but he has met his match in Mrs Murphy. 3 Marty often gets into trouble and that is why he sets off the fire extinguisher in the library. 4 Mrs Murphy is a librarian who hates children and does everything to keep them out of her library.</exercise>
<exercise>O4 Read the text again and collect phrases that are used to describe Mrs Murphy. Decide which of the following words fit her character and explain why.</exercise>
<listing>cool · friendly · clever · strict · nasty · angry · helpful · scary</listing>
<exercise>O5 a) With a partner take notes on Marty and his brother.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Imagine you could talk to Marty or his brother after what happened. Write down questions you would like to ask them.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Hot seat: Put two people from the class in the hot seat as Marty and his brother and ask them about their experience in the library. Hot seat, p. 130</exercise>
<gap>Du kannst schon viel auf Englisch verstehen und ausdrücken. Du kannst … 3 über Umweltschutz sprechen 3 deine Meinung ausdrücken 3 Interesse an dem ausdrücken, was dein Gesprächspartner sagt 3 ein Interview durchführen 3 Personen zu ihren Handlungen befragen 3 einen Brief verfassen  WB Portfolio-Fragebogen Theme 5</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and three 103</footnote>
<gap>Find statements in the text that mean …</gap>
<exercise>∙ … very quickly</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … cry like a baby cat</exercise>
</page>
<page id='95'>
<chapter>6/A</chapter>
<sentence>Are you fit?</sentence>
<exercise>A1  L 2/3 Listen to the CD. What are the different sports? Write them down.  WB A1, p. 95</exercise>
<exercise>A2 Charles Cousins is a British rowing star. He is visiting William Ellis School to talk about fitness and health. To find out how fit the pupils are, they do a fitness test.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Are you fit? Do the fitness test with a partner. Note down your results on a piece of paper.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Check your results on page 105.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Jump up and down for 30 seconds. Are you out of breath? No, not at all.</exercise>
<sentence>A little bit.</sentence>
<exercise>2 Can you touch the floor like this? Yes, I can. I can, but it is difficult. No, I can’t. It’s too hard.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Walk up and down 20 stairs quickly. Are you out of breath?</exercise>
<sentence>No, I’m not.</sentence>
<sentence>That’s easy.</sentence>
<exercise>4 Can you balance like this for 15 seconds?</exercise>
<sentence>Yes, I can.</sentence>
<sentence>Sorry, I can’t do it.</sentence>
<exercise>5 Do press-ups. How many can you do?</exercise>
<exercise>104 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='96'>
<chapter>6/A</chapter>
<exercise>A3 Find words and phrases about sport and fitness in A2 and organize them in a word web. You can add more words and phrases you know.</exercise>
<gap>…</gap>
<gap>Wordbank Sport and health, p. 153 P1  WB A2, p. 95 … SPORT + FITNESS actions</gap>
<exercise>A4 v Extra: Viewing: Cha cha slide  Dancing is a great way to get fit! Watch the “Cha cha slide” and dance along. Have fun!</exercise>
<exercise>A5  L 2/4 a) Listen to Rajiv and George and find out what they are talking about. Listening, p. 124</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and make notes. What did Rajiv/ George like? What didn’t they like?  WB A3, p. 96</exercise>
<exercise>A6 Target task v " Project  Portfolio P2, P3 Write a dialogue between George and Caroline.</exercise>
<gap>…</gap>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<gap>…</gap>
<sentence>In the evening, George tells his sister about the day with Charles Cousins.</sentence>
<exercise>∙ What happened? What did George think about Charles Cousins? Collect words and ideas.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Write the dialogue, then show it to a partner. Writing, p. 128 Read his/her dialogue and give feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127</exercise>
<exercise>3 Choose one of your dialogues and act it out. P9</exercise>
<sentence>Congratulations!</sentence>
<sentence>You’re as fit as a fiddle!</sentence>
<sentence>Keep up the good work!</sentence>
<sentence>You can share your love for sport with your friends: you could organize a class football match, for example.</sentence>
<sentence>Not bad!</sentence>
<sentence>You did quite well on most exercises but you can do better.</sentence>
<sentence>If you get out of breath quickly, try to run or play tennis or football more often.</sentence>
<sentence>If you are not very flexible, try stretching exercises every day.</sentence>
<sentence>Oh dear!</sentence>
<sentence>You need to get off the couch!</sentence>
<sentence>If you are in front of a computer or TV for more than an hour, turn it off and get outside.</sentence>
<sentence>Cycling to school, playing football with friends or dancing are great fun!</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and five 105</footnote>
<exercise>1 Plan your dialogue:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What will Caroline say?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='97'>
<chapter>6/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 a) Read the two poems. Which poem do you like better? Say why.</exercise>
<sentence>I dreamt I played for England I dreamt I scored each goal I dreamt I left the players standing as I took the team on whole I dreamt the fans all cheered I dreamt they called my name before Mum pulled me out of bed to end my greatest ever game.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Find titles for the poems and compare them in class. P10</exercise>
<exercise>c) Extra: Add more sport words to your word web from A3. Wordbank Sport and health, p. 153  WB B1, p. 96</exercise>
<exercise>B2  L 2/5 Last weekend, there was a football match between William Ellis School and Acland Burghley. On Monday, George meets Lewis, a boy from Acland Burghley.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Close your books and listen to them. Why are the boys arguing about the match?</exercise>
<sentence>Just look at my nose!</sentence>
<sentence>Lewis: Well, I can see your nose is hurt.</sentence>
<sentence>But it wasn’t Oliver’s fault, was it?</sentence>
<sentence>It was your own fault, wasn’t it?</sentence>
<sentence>George: What???</sentence>
<sentence>The fact is that Oliver was pushing me!</sentence>
<sentence>And while he was chasing the ball he hit me on the nose with his elbow.</sentence>
<sentence>And it sure wasn’t an accident!</sentence>
<sentence>George: Well, Oliver fell down while he was running.</sentence>
<sentence>I didn’t push him, did I?</sentence>
<sentence>George: Let’s ask someone else, then.</sentence>
<sentence>There’s Gillian – hey Gill, can you tell Lewis here what happened to my nose during the match?</sentence>
<exercise>15 Lewis: Well, I only know what I saw … Gillian: Well, when the accident happened I was</exercise>
<sentence>George: Then you know that Oliver also shouted at me while I was running towards the ball.</sentence>
<sentence>And when I shouted back he pushed me.</sentence>
<sentence>Lewis: That’s a great story, Georgie-boy.</sentence>
<gap>now, sorry, George. George: But – Gillian … ?</gap>
<exercise>b) Read the dialogue and say what happened while …  WB B2, B3, p. 97</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … Oliver was chasing the ball</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … George was running towards the ball</exercise>
<gap>While Oliver was chasing the ball, he hit George …</gap>
<exercise>106 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … Oliver was running</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … Gillian was talking to Emma</exercise>
</page>
<page id='98'>
<chapter>6/B</chapter>
<exercise>B3 Grammar card: past progressive 1 Look at B2 again and find examples like this:</exercise>
<sentence>While Oliver was chasing the ball he hit George on the nose.</sentence>
<sentence>The past progressive is often used in sentences where one action takes place while something else is going on.</sentence>
<sentence>You form it with was/were + infinitive + -ing .</sentence>
<exercise>2 Check LiF 16 on page 147 and start a grammar card on the past progressive. P4  WB B4, p. 98</exercise>
<exercise>B4</exercise>
<listing>Work with a partner. Look at the pictures to find out what really happened at the match. Write the story. Use the past progressive when necessary. LiF 16: Past progressive, p. 147 Wordbank Sport and health, p. 153 audience · stick out her tongue · flag · hold a sign ·</listing>
<gap>Example: Oliver and George chased the ball. While George was running to … Oliver saw …</gap>
<listing>shout at · get angry · chase the ball · hit · bleed · fall to the ground · hurt</listing>
<exercise>1 2 3</exercise>
<exercise>4 5 6 7</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and seven 107</footnote>
</page>
<page id='99'>
<chapter>6/B</chapter>
<exercise>B5 George and Oliver went to the doctor’s after the football match. Look at the other patients in the waiting room.</exercise>
<sentence>The girl was playing hockey when she hurt her foot.</sentence>
<sentence>What happened to them?</sentence>
<exercise>B6  L 2/6 On Sunday Gillian and Oliver speak to each other on the phone. Listen to them, then read these sentences. Are they right or wrong? Correct the wrong sentences. Listening, p. 124 P14  WB B6, p. 100</exercise>
<exercise>1 Oliver is calling Gillian. 2 Gillian wants to say sorry. 3 Oliver knows many girls who are interested in football.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Alex Scott is a man. 5 Oliver is still angry with Gillian. 6 Charlie is at Oliver’s school.</exercise>
<exercise>B7 v Extra  L 2/6 a) Listen to the phone call again. Note down useful words and phrases for a telephone conversation. Example: Hello; Is that …?; …</exercise>
<exercise>b) Write a telephone conversation between George and Oliver about the match.</exercise>
<exercise>B8 Grammar card: question tags 1 When George and Lewis were arguing about the match, they used some questions like these: You don’t really think that Oliver played fairly, do you ? But it wasn’t Oliver’s fault, was it ?</exercise>
<sentence>The blue part of each sentence is called a question tag .</sentence>
<exercise>2 Then check LiF 17 on page 148 and write a grammar card on question tags. P5  WB B7, p. 100</exercise>
<exercise>108 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='100'>
<chapter>6/B</chapter>
<exercise>B9 How much do you remember about the match?</exercise>
<sentence>No, he didn’t.</sentence>
<sentence>Work with a partner and ask him/her about the match.</sentence>
<sentence>Use question tags.</sentence>
<sentence>George hit Oliver, didn’t he?</sentence>
<exercise>B10 Target task v " Project  Portfolio Write a mystery. Another group has to solve it later.</exercise>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<exercise>1 Work in groups of four. Choose a mystery or make up your own.</exercise>
<sentence>After a football match, one player lies unconscious in the changing rooms.</sentence>
<sentence>The only thing that is missing are his/her football boots.</sentence>
<sentence>At a swimming competition one of the swimmers is locked in the toilets and misses the race.</sentence>
<sentence>During a race a famous cyclist suddenly falls off his bike and breaks his right arm.</sentence>
<sentence>The bike mechanic notices that someone must have done something to the bike before the race.</sentence>
<exercise>∙ the victim · witness 1 · witness 2 · the person who did it</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the best football player in the team</exercise>
<exercise>∙ he hurt the football player because …</exercise>
<exercise>3 Read your role cards carefully. Discuss if there is anything that needs to be added/changed. Tip: Don’t make it too easy for the police!</exercise>
<exercise>4 Get together with another group. They are the police and will ask each member of your group about the mystery.</exercise>
<gap>What were you doing when …?</gap>
<gap>How long have you known …?</gap>
<sentence>You weren’t at home last night, were you?</sentence>
<sentence>Is there anything you saw?</sentence>
<gap>I was eating a sandwich when I heard a loud noise in …</gap>
<gap>I have known him for … years.</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<exercise>5 When “the police” have solved the mystery, it’s your group’s turn to ask questions about their mystery. Wordbank Sport and health, p. 153 Speaking 1, p. 126 P15</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and nine 109</footnote>
<exercise>2 Now prepare role cards for each member of your group together:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ man</exercise>
<exercise>∙ 20 years old</exercise>
<exercise>∙ man</exercise>
<exercise>∙ 22 years old</exercise>
<exercise>∙ …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ …</exercise>
</page>
<page id='101'>
<chapter>6/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 Think – pair – share: What do you like most about a sports competition? What do you dislike? Note down your ideas. Think – pair – share, p. 130</exercise>
<gap>I enjoy … most.</gap>
<gap>I like … best.</gap>
<gap>I can’t stand …</gap>
<gap>The thing I dislike most about sports competitions is …</gap>
<exercise>C2 Every year Camden School for Girls has a Sports Day. Each girl belongs to a house and the houses compete against each other. a) Read about the Sports Day that took place last year and answer the questions in a few words.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Which years take part in the Sports Day? 2 What are the names of the Houses? 3 Who was most successful in the long jump?</exercise>
<exercise>4 Who won the 200m sprint? 5 Who won the House Cup? 6 What took place in the afternoon?</exercise>
<sentence>Last week Camden School for Girl’s Sports Day took place at Finsbury Park.</sentence>
<sentence>The day started with the long jump.</sentence>
<sentence>She broke the school record and put Red House in the lead.</sentence>
<sentence>So the Yellows took the lead.</sentence>
<sentence>The atmosphere in the stadium was tense.</sentence>
<sentence>Great running, Ronke!</sentence>
<sentence>Both girls scored points for Yellow House.</sentence>
<sentence>The audience cheered for ages.</sentence>
<sentence>In the afternoon everyone enjoyed the fun and games.</sentence>
<sentence>A lot depended on the result of the relay races.</sentence>
<sentence>The teachers won narrowly.</sentence>
<sentence>Well done to all!</sentence>
<exercise>b) Compare the Sports Day with the sports day at your school. Example: There are more events at CSG than at our school.</exercise>
<gap>We only … The girls at CSG are more competitive than … LiF 3: Steigerung von Adjektiven, p. 137/138 P6  WB C1, p. 101</gap>
<listing>exciting · boring · many · successful · competitive · funny · serious · outstanding</listing>
<exercise>110 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='102'>
<chapter>6/C</chapter>
<exercise>C3  L 2/7 a) Caroline and Emma are both looking forward to this year’s Sports Day. They are in Red House. Listen to them and find out why they are excited about Sports Day. Listening, p. 124</exercise>
<exercise>b) How will Caroline and Emma feel if they don’t win the races? Say why.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Listen again and take notes. Find out what will happen if …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … the Reds win the House Cup this year? ∙ … the Reds come last in the House competition?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … Caroline promises not to be so bossy?</exercise>
<exercise>C4  L 2/8 It’s a week after Sports Day. Emma wrote a story about it for her English class.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Read the story and choose the best title for it. Give reasons.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Victory for the Reds ∙ Friends forever</exercise>
<sentence>Caroline and I were really excited about Sports Day.</sentence>
<sentence>The weeks before the big day we trained for at least half an hour after school every day.</sentence>
<sentence>I took the race more seriously now.</sentence>
<sentence>Thanks to Caroline I was running much more confidently and was getting so much better.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline wanted to come first in one of her races so she trained very hard and she ran faster from week to week.</sentence>
<sentence>Nothing can stop the Reds!</sentence>
<sentence>Nothing can stop the Reds!</sentence>
<sentence>We’ll never give up!</sentence>
<sentence>We’ll never give in!</sentence>
<sentence>We’ll fight to the end, we’ve come here to win!</sentence>
<sentence>On the field Navina from our class was just doing the high jump.</sentence>
<sentence>It was a fantastic jump and the Reds all cheered enthusiastically.</sentence>
<sentence>Finally the big day arrived.</sentence>
<sentence>We all met at Finsbury Park Stadium where the sports events were taking place.</sentence>
<sentence>The stadium was full of us, all wearing our house colours.</sentence>
<sentence>Of course, my classmates and I were all wearing red.</sentence>
<sentence>Suddenly I had an idea.</sentence>
<sentence>There was still time to send a message over the microphone.</sentence>
<sentence>I ran to Mrs Shimmin, who was doing the “shout-outs” and wrote mine down quickly.</sentence>
<sentence>Then I went back to my seat to watch the race.</sentence>
<sentence>I crossed my fingers for luck.</sentence>
<sentence>I knew how much Caroline wanted to win.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and eleven 111</footnote>
<exercise>∙ … the Reds don’t win the Cup?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ … Emma trains a bit harder?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Emma’s big day</exercise>
</page>
<page id='103'>
<chapter>6/C</chapter>
<exercise>4 6 loudspeaker came on: “This is a message for</exercise>
<sentence>Then it was time for my race.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline Lambraki from her friend, Emma: ‘You can do it, Caroline!</sentence>
<sentence>Go!</sentence>
<sentence>Go!</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline smiled at me.</sentence>
<sentence>Then the race started: “On your marks, get set, go!” We all cheered madly.</sentence>
<sentence>The girls just flew along the track.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline’s main rival, Kadhija, was on her left.</sentence>
<sentence>She ran faster than Caroline.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline was trying hard to keep up, but there was no way she could catch her.</sentence>
<sentence>At the finishing line, Caroline fell on the ground dramatically.</sentence>
<sentence>I hugged her.</sentence>
<sentence>“That’s all thanks to you, Caroline!” I said.</sentence>
<sentence>After the competitions there was an afternoon of fun.</sentence>
<sentence>We all felt relaxed now and even Caroline joined in.</sentence>
<sentence>At the end of the day we all waited impatiently to hear the results of the house competitions.</sentence>
<sentence>When Mrs Shimmin announced the results, the Reds clapped more wildly than ever.</sentence>
<sentence>For the first time in years we won the House Cup.</sentence>
<sentence>What a day!</sentence>
<sentence>“Great race, Caroline!” I said.</sentence>
<sentence>“Well done!” “But I only came second,” she answered.</sentence>
<sentence>Typical Caroline.</sentence>
<sentence>She hates to lose.</sentence>
<sentence>“But your time was fantastic!</sentence>
<sentence>Kadhija broke the school record, and you were just behind her!” But that didn’t help much.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline was very disappointed.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Find headings for the different paragraphs. Example: Paragraph 1 – Excited about Sports Day; paragraph 2 – … P7, P12</exercise>
<exercise>C5  L 2/9 a) Find examples of adverbs with -ly in Emma’s story and write them down. Example: excitedly, …</exercise>
<exercise>b) Do you know how to pronounce the words? Where is the stress? Check the CD to see if you were right. P8  WB C2, C3, p. 102, 103</exercise>
<exercise>112 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<sentence>Now it was time for the race.</sentence>
</page>
<page id='104'>
<chapter>6/C</chapter>
<exercise>C6 Grammar card: comparison of adverbs 1 Look at these sentences to find out about comparisons of adverbs: I was running much more confidently. She ran faster than Caroline.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Look at LiF 18 on page 148 and add the rules to your grammar card for adverbs.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Write down two sentences with -er/-est , two sentences with more/most and four sentences with a comparison of well, badly and much . P11  WB C4, p. 103</exercise>
<exercise>C7</exercise>
<sentence>Look at these verbs and adverbs and write down five sentences about your classmates.</sentence>
<sentence>Example: Leon swims faster than Ben.</sentence>
<listing>swim/fast · run/quickly · sing/well · write/clearly · draw/beautifully ·</listing>
<exercise>C8 v Choose Wordbank Sports and health, p. 153  WB C6, p. 104</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use rhyming words. Describe your hobby and use the words and phrases from A3.</exercise>
<sentence>We’re cool!</sentence>
<sentence>We’re crazy!</sentence>
<sentence>We’ll beat you!</sentence>
<sentence>Defeat you!</sentence>
<sentence>Gooooo (put the name of your class here) !</sentence>
<exercise>C9 Target task v  Portfolio Write Caroline’s story about Sports Day.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Look at Emma’s story in C4 again. What are her thoughts, feelings and opinions?</exercise>
<exercise>2 Compare Caroline to Emma. What do you think Caroline’s thoughts, feelings and opinions might be?</exercise>
<gap>Support I love basketball because … My favourite sport/team is … I’m really good at … / I could improve my … I play in a team/at a club/… I have been training since … / I started when I was … I (don’t) take it very seriously.</gap>
<sentence>Need help?</sentence>
<exercise>3 Now write Caroline’s story. Describe what happens from her point of view.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use adjectives and adverbs (and comparisons when necessary) to make the story more interesting.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and thirteen 113</footnote>
<exercise>∙ Write your own class chant.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write your sports profile.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Repeat words or sounds.</exercise>
<sentence>We’re never ever lazy!</sentence>
<sentence>We’ll even try to eat you!</sentence>
<exercise>∙ Include Caroline’s thoughts, feelings and opinions.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Add direct speech.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Add connectives (e.g. and, but ) and structure words (e.g. first, then ).</exercise>
</page>
<page id='105'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P1 Words: sport and health Find the odd one out and give a reason.</exercise>
<exercise>1 swim · football · do press-ups · run · jump 2 chips · coke · fruit · hamburger · pizza 3 hockey · basketball · tennis · volleyball · football</exercise>
<sentence>‘Football’ isn’t a verb.</sentence>
<exercise>4 watch TV · cycle · go by bus · play computer games · go by car ·</exercise>
<exercise>P2 Words: positive and negative adjectives What are the words? Note them down and sort them into positive and negative adjectives.</exercise>
<exercise>1 / ɡreɪt / 2 / ˈbɔːrɪŋ / 3 / ˈterəb(ə)l /</exercise>
<exercise>4 / ˈɪntrəstɪŋ / 5 / ˈfæsɪneɪtɪŋ / 6 / ˈɔːf(ə)l /</exercise>
<exercise>7 / bæd / 8 / fænˈtæstɪk / 9 / ˈwʌndəf(ə)l /</exercise>
<exercise>10 / ˈlʌvli / 11 / ɪkˈsaɪtɪŋ / 12 / ˈbɒsi /</exercise>
<exercise>13 / ɪmˈbærəsɪŋ / 14 / ˈhɒrəb(ə)l /</exercise>
<exercise>P3 Words: expressing opinion Read the dialogue between George and Rajiv about Charles Cousins. Note down all the words and phrases you can use to express your opinion. Example: Charles Cousins is a great guy, isn’t he?; …</exercise>
<sentence>Charles Cousins is a great guy, isn’t he?</sentence>
<gap>such a famous person come to our school! George: Pfff … Rajiv: What do you mean? George: He made us run for 20 minutes round the football field … boring.</gap>
<sentence>What’s the point really?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Err, what do you think?</sentence>
<sentence>Charles explained how important it is to be fit.</sentence>
<sentence>George: Why didn’t they get a footballer to come to our school?</sentence>
<sentence>That would have been cool!</sentence>
<sentence>I would love to try rowing too!</sentence>
<sentence>George: But a fitness test?</sentence>
<sentence>Please!</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: I think the fitness test was fun.</sentence>
<sentence>George: You’re right.</sentence>
<sentence>That’s something for girls.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: You didn’t listen to anything he said, did you?</sentence>
<sentence>George: But what does he know about football?</sentence>
<sentence>He is a rower.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, he’s a famous rower.</sentence>
<gap>know a thing or two about sports and health. George: OK … Rajiv: Come on grumpy, let’s get lunch. Maybe you’ll be in a better mood 4 after you’ve had some food.</gap>
<exercise>1 exhausted – erschöpft, aufgebraucht; 2 muscle – Muskel, Stärke; 3 wholemeal – Vollkornmehl, Vollkorn-; 4 mood – Laune, Stimmung</exercise>
<exercise>114 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='106'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P4 Past progressive LiF 16: Past progressive, p. 147 Lionel had a terrible day. Look at the pictures and describe his day. Example: Lionel was eating his breakfast when …</exercise>
<exercise>P5 Question tags LiF 17: Question tags, p. 148 Nathan is from New Zealand. He is at William Ellis School for one year. Read his conversation with Rajiv and note down the correct question tags.</exercise>
<sentence>Nathan: Yes, I’m from Auckland, I miss it a bit.</sentence>
<sentence>Nathan: Yes, I do.</sentence>
<sentence>Everyone has been very nice to me.</sentence>
<sentence>Nathan: No, not really.</sentence>
<sentence>Do you know Colin Baker?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Yes, I do.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Yes, he is.</sentence>
<sentence>I know his parents, too.</sentence>
<sentence>Nathan: Yes, they’re all very nice.</sentence>
<sentence>Listen, maybe we can do something together soon.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: No, I don’t, sorry.</sentence>
<sentence>But what about Friday?</sentence>
<sentence>Nathan: Oh yes, I know some of their songs.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Yes, we can walk there.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s meet at the corner of Parkway and Camden High Street at seven.</sentence>
<sentence>Nathan: OK, great.</sentence>
<sentence>See you then.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and fifteen 115</footnote>
</page>
<page id='107'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P6 Revision: comparison of adjectives Look at the Sports Day results and compare them. Example: Harriet’s jump was high, but Rachel’s was higher than Harriet’s and Alexandra’s jump was the highest. LiF 3: Steigerung von Adjektiven, p. 137/138</exercise>
<exercise>P7 Words: competition Look at the following sentences and complete them. Be careful: Some of the words are irregular verbs!</exercise>
<exercise>1 Caroline hoped to 1 the Year 7 sprint on Sports Day. 2 She trained every day and 2 to improve her time. 3 Before the race 3 , the girls went to the starting line.</exercise>
<listing>be in the lead · battle it out · win · beat · fight hard · start · overtake</listing>
<exercise>4 When the race started, Caroline and Kadhija 4 on the track. 5 Kadhija 5 and Caroline couldn’t 6 her. 6 It was Caroline’s best time, but Kadhija still 7 her.</exercise>
<exercise>P8 Revision: adverbs of manner LiF 12: Adverbien der Art und Weise, p. 144 Look at the pictures and describe what the people did at the football match and how they did it. Example: Before the match many people waited impatiently outside the stadium.</exercise>
<listing>impatient · enthusiastic · excited · nervous · loud</listing>
<exercise>116 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='108'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P9 Revision: adverbs of frequency Write down these sentences in the correct order. Be careful where you put the adverb (e.g. sometimes, often, … ).</exercise>
<exercise>1 with his father / plays basketball / Oliver / sometimes / . 2 Perfect Peter / never / eats / fast food / . 3 after the football training / is / Sarah / very tired / often / . 4 takes / Karen / usually / the bus / to school / . 5 to bed / often / on school days/ Hugo / goes / at nine o’clock / . 6 always / Sam / and sweets / after school / eats ice cream / .</exercise>
<exercise>P10 Revision: will future LiF 6: will future, p. 139 What will the friends do in 20 years? Think about them and write two sentences about each friend. Example: I think George will be a famous film star. He won’t have a boring job or children.</exercise>
<listing>film star · doctor · teacher · banker · lawyer 1 · housewife 2 · nurse 3 · stewardess · model · mechanic</listing>
<exercise>1 lawyer – Rechtsanwalt/Rechtsanwältin; 2 housewife – Hausfrau; 3 nurse – Krankenschwester/Pfleger</exercise>
<exercise>P11 Comparison of adverbs LiF 18: Steigerung von Adverbien, p. 148</exercise>
<exercise>1. Emma can run two kilometres quite easily. But Caroline can run two kilometres ??? (fast). Charlie is a terrible dancer, but George dances even ??? (terrible).</exercise>
<exercise>2. You can check your answers on page 221. 3. You need help? ’ Do a), then b). You can do it? ’ Do b).</exercise>
<exercise>a) Complete the sentences.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Gillian runs quite fast. But Caroline runs even … 2 Emma trained quite seriously for her race but Caroline trained even … 3 Mrs Lambraki plays golf well but her husband plays even … 4 Charlie plays football well. But Phil Jones from Manchester United plays football … 5 Emma sometimes reacts emotionally but when Caroline loses she reacts …</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and seventeen 117</footnote>
</page>
<page id='109'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>b) Mr Wilson is a sports teacher at CSG. He is talking to some girls before Sports Day. Fill in adverbs and decide when you have to use comparative or superlative forms.</exercise>
<exercise>P12 Say it in English Look at Theme 6 again and find the answers.</exercise>
<gap>Was sagst du auf Englisch, wenn …</gap>
<exercise>1 du sagen willst, dass jemand selber schuld hat? 2 wenn eine Mannschaft die Führung übernimmt? 3 wenn zwei Mannschaften nur haarscharf auseinander liegen? 4 du jemanden anfeuern willst? 5 du „auf die Plätze, fertig, los!“ sagen willst?</exercise>
<exercise>P13 Words: body parts a) Draw a person, but use the hand you don’t usually write with. Then label as many body parts as you can in two minutes.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Compare your results with a partner and add any new words.</exercise>
<exercise>P14 Viewing: Karate with Jessica  a) Watch the film clip and say where it was filmed.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Watch the clip again. Right or wrong?</exercise>
<exercise>1 Jessica usually trains four times a week. 2 The training sometimes starts with a warm-up. 3 Stretching different parts of your body is important. 4 Jessica’s team uses punchbags 1 in their training. 5 Jessica loves karate because her team are all her friends.</exercise>
<exercise>1 hurdles – Hürdenlauf</exercise>
<exercise>1 punchbag – Sandsack</exercise>
<exercise>118 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='110'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>P15 Writing Reading, p. 125 Look at the pictures and write a story about Robin Hood. You can start like this: One day the Sheriff … The farmer called for help. He was very …</exercise>
<sentence>Help!</sentence>
<sentence>He’s got all the money!</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t worry.</sentence>
<sentence>I’ll get that money back for you.</sentence>
<sentence>One day the Sheriff of Nottingham stole a lot of money from an old farmer.</sentence>
<sentence>Oh no, I can hear Robin Hood.</sentence>
<sentence>Give me your dress!</sentence>
<sentence>The Sheriff took my dress, Robin.</sentence>
<sentence>Hurry up, men.</sentence>
<sentence>He’s in the forest!</sentence>
<sentence>Oh, I hate Robin Hood!</sentence>
<sentence>You helped us to catch the Sheriff.</sentence>
<sentence>You stole this money from my friend!</sentence>
<sentence>I’m very angry.</sentence>
<sentence>Remember, Sheriff: This is my forest!</sentence>
<exercise>1 recognize – erkennen</exercise>
<sentence>The Sheriff won’t be back for a long time.</sentence>
<sentence>Ha ha!</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and nineteen 119</footnote>
</page>
<page id='111'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<sentence>This does not mean, however, that there is no more world-class sport, because London is the home of many top sports events: In late March or early April, there is the famous University Boat Race on the River Thames.</sentence>
<sentence>In April, thousands of runners come to London for the London Marathon, one of the biggest marathons in the world.</sentence>
<sentence>In the summer months, cricket is one of the most popular sports because you need good weather and a lot of sunshine as matches can last a few days.</sentence>
<sentence>All year round, you can go and see football and rugby matches.</sentence>
<sentence>There are a number of Premier League football teams in London – Arsenal and Chelsea are just two of them.</sentence>
<sentence>Many matches of England’s national team are played at Wembley Stadium as well as the English cup final.</sentence>
<sentence>Twickenham Stadium is sometimes called the home of English rugby.</sentence>
<exercise>1 4  S 16, L 2/11</exercise>
<sentence>Look at the photos and identify the kinds of sports you can see.</sentence>
<sentence>Example: cricket – rowing – ...</sentence>
<exercise>a) Listen to the official song of the 2012 Summer Olympics in London, “Survival“ 6 by Muse. Note down words from the song that tell you it</exercise>
<sentence>Find out which sports or sport event they are about.</sentence>
<sentence>I think of ... when I listen to that song.</sentence>
<sentence>Choose one topic and prepare a presentation or poster: a) One of the sports and its rules, e.g.</sentence>
<sentence>I wouldn’t normally listen to a song like that because ...</sentence>
<sentence>This is the kind of music that I like because ...</sentence>
<exercise>1 compete for – antreten gegen 2 sports facility – Sportstätte 3 move into – umziehen in 4 glory – Ehre 5 tournament – Turnier 6 survival – Überleben</exercise>
<exercise>c) Many sportmen and sportswomen listen to music before an important competition. Choose a song that makes you feel good and ready to take part in a competition. Explain why that song is so special to you.</exercise>
<exercise>120 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='112'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>1 2</exercise>
<exercise>3 4</exercise>
<exercise>5 6</exercise>
<exercise>7 8</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</footnote>
</page>
<page id='113'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<exercise>O1 a) Look at these clothes. Are there any that are for boys only or for girls only?</exercise>
<listing>shoes · trousers · tie · skirt · socks · suit · dress · shirt · T-shirt · gloves · boots · jacket · coat · football boots · scarf · hat · shorts</listing>
<exercise>b) Can you think of any situations when girls might wear boys’ clothes or boys girls’ clothes?</exercise>
<exercise>O2 Reading, p. 125 Read the first part of the story and say why the boys wear dresses.</exercise>
<sentence>Dennis lives with his dad and brother.</sentence>
<sentence>His mother left the family some time ago and Dennis misses her very much.</sentence>
<sentence>He misses her clothes, too, and he becomes interested in fashion.</sentence>
<sentence>His father is not very happy about this, but Dennis shares his love of beautiful dresses with his new friend, Lisa.</sentence>
<sentence>One day Lisa persuades him to wear a dress to school.</sentence>
<sentence>The headmaster, Mr Hawtrey, expels him.</sentence>
<sentence>Dennis is the best football player in the school and that means that the school team are much weaker without him.</sentence>
<sentence>The school’s team was nowhere to be seen.</sentence>
<gap>But you can’t expel us all, Sir!” he shouted back triumphantly. All the boys in the team lined up […] behind their captain, striking poses 10 like they were</gap>
<gap>dancers in a Madonna video. The crowd went wild. “THIS IS A DISGRACE 11 !” bellowed Mr Hawtrey. He stormed off. […] Gareth smiled at Dennis.</gap>
<gap>gown 5 … Then Darvesh followed in a yellow 30 “Come on boys. Let’s do it!” said Gareth. […]</gap>
<gap>polka dot frock 6 … Then the defenders were right behind in matching red cocktail dresses … The rest of the team followed in a variety of outfits from Lisa’s wardrobe … And finally</gap>
<sentence>Within seconds Dennis had scored a goal.</sentence>
<sentence>The Maudlin Street team were still in shock.</sentence>
<gap>pink bridesmaid’s 7 dress. There was a huge cheer from the crowd. […] As they ran onto the pitch, Mr Hawtrey bellowed 8 at Gareth.</gap>
<sentence>Laughing, Dennis scored again.</sentence>
<sentence>He was on his way to a hat- trick and he was a hundred times happier than he had ever been.</sentence>
<gap>wearing a dress. Then Darvesh scored […] 6-3. “My boy! My boy in the yellow polka-dot dress</gap>
<exercise>1 pitch – Spielfeld 2 eager to – erpicht sein auf 3 demolition job – Zerstörung 4 changing room – Umkleidekabine</exercise>
<exercise>5 gold lamé ball gown – Ballkleid aus schimmerndem, goldenen Stoff 6 polka dot frock – Kleid mit Punkten 7 bridesmaid – Brautjungfer 8 bellow – bellen</exercise>
<exercise>9 expel – von der Schule verweisen 10 strike a pose – sich in Positur werfen 11 disgrace – Schande 12 hitch up – hochziehen 13 weave – schlängeln</exercise>
<exercise>122 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='114'>
<chapter>DELETE</chapter>
<sentence>They were on fire.</sentence>
<sentence>Now there were only a few more minutes of the game to play.</sentence>
<sentence>One more to go.</sentence>
<exercise>45 50 […] The crowd laughed and cheered. Then another goal followed and another. 6-6.</exercise>
<gap>done it. […] But, at that moment Dennis fell to the ground in pain 15 . The crowd gasped 16 . […]</gap>
<exercise>14 tap – anticken 15 in pain – voller Schmerzen 16 gasp – Luft anhalten</exercise>
<exercise>O3 What do you think will happen? Read on and find out if you were right.</exercise>
<gap>“OI!” WHAT’S GOING ON HERE?” Dad. Dennis couldn’t believe it. Dad had never come to 20 see him play for the school before, and now here Dennis was, lying on the ground with tears in his eyes wearing a dress. He was going to be in so much trouble … But Dad looked at Dennis and</gap>
<sentence>“I called him at half-time,” said Darvesh.</sentence>
<sentence>“After what you said about your Dad never seeing you play a match, I thought he wouldn’t want to miss this.” “Thanks, mate” said Dennis.</sentence>
<sentence>“OI!</sentence>
<sentence>REF!” he shouted.</sentence>
<sentence>Street boys.</sentence>
<sentence>Darvesh ran up the outside, and Gareth passed it to him.</sentence>
<sentence>Dad.</sentence>
<sentence>“You OK?” asked Darvesh.</sentence>
<sentence>“Yeah,” said Dennis.</sentence>
<sentence>“COME ON, SON!” shouted Dennis’s Dad, really getting into it now.</sentence>
<sentence>The keeper didn’t stand a chance.</sentence>
<exercise>35 was all over.</exercise>
<exercise>1 glow – glühen 2 spread – sich verbreiten 3 steady – (sich) aufrichten</exercise>
<exercise>4 charge towards – auf jmd. zurennen 5 goalie – Torwart 6 final whistle – Schlusspfiff</exercise>
<exercise>O4 Describe Dennis’s feelings towards his father. Explain why you think it is so important to Dennis that he watches the match.</exercise>
<exercise>O5 At the end of the game Mr Hawtrey comes back and tells Dennis that he is still expelled from school. Write a dialogue between the headmaster and Dennis’s father.</exercise>
<gap>Du kannst schon viel auf Englisch verstehen und ausdrücken. Du kannst … 3 über verschiedene Sportarten sprechen 3 eine Geschichte anhand von Bildern verfassen 3 über Krankheiten und Verletzungen sprechen 3 ein Telefongespräch führen 3 beschreiben, wie jemand etwas tut  WB Portfolio-Fragebogen Theme 6</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and twenty-three 123</footnote>
</page>
</document>