<document><page id='14'>
<chapter>1/A</chapter>
<exercise>Agony aunt</exercise>
<exercise>A1 a) Milling around: Have you ever read any ‘agony aunt’ letters? Talk about the kind of problems you might read about on an agony aunt page. Milling around, p.149</exercise>
<exercise>b) Find categories for the problems, e.g. ‘problems with parents’.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Now read the letters to Ally on these pages and note down the problems.</exercise>
<exercise>d) Talk to a partner about the letters. Say which categories from A1b) you would put them into. Explain your choice. WB A1 - A3, pp.7/8</exercise>
<exercise>((Foto Ally))</exercise>
<gap>Ask Ally… Write to: Go! magazine, 23 Market St., London, W12 7JR.</gap>
<exercise>5 long time ago. Now she tells me that It’s not embarrassing to fall in</exercise>
<exercise>A2</exercise>
<sentence>Dear Ally, I am so unhappy!</sentence>
<sentence>You must help me, please.</sentence>
<sentence>My mum is going to get married again!</sentence>
<sentence>She and Dad split up a long time ago.</sentence>
<sentence>Now she tells me that she has got a new boyfriend – and they are both almost forty.</sentence>
<sentence>This “boyfriend” has asked her to marry him.</sentence>
<sentence>So now she wants me to meet this “new man in her life”!!!</sentence>
<sentence>But I don’t want to meet some stupid Welshman called Gwynn.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m too embarrassed to tell my friends.</sentence>
<sentence>I think I’ll run away from home!</sentence>
<sentence>Yours, Miserable in Camden</sentence>
    <sentence>Dear Miserable in Camden, I can understand that you’re unhappy but don’t you think you are being a bit selfish?</sentence>
<sentence>It’s not embarrassing to fall in love when you’re forty.</sentence>
<sentence>Why shouldn’t your mum be happy? And why don’t you agree to meet her boyfriend?</sentence>
<sentence>He’s probably really nice.</sentence>
<sentence>Running away is certainly not the answer.</sentence>
<sentence>It will only make everyone upset.</sentence>
<sentence>Try talking to a good friend. Yours, Ally</sentence>
    <sentence>Dear Ally, Please help, I’m desperate.</sentence>
    <sentence>You see, I might not get into the school football team this year.</sentence>
    <sentence>Last year our coach didn’t let me play in the last few games.</sentence>
    <sentence>But I was playing much better than the others when he stopped choosing me.</sentence>
    <sentence>I told the coach that I’m a Manchester United fan but he supports Arsenal.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’m sure that’s why he didn’t choose me.</sentence>
    <sentence>What should I do?</sentence>
    <sentence>Dear R., You and your coach support different teams but that can’t be the reason he didn’t choose you.</sentence>
    <sentence>The best thing to do is to do some training.</sentence>
    <sentence>If you play well, you will certainly get into the team.</sentence>
    <sentence>Yours, Ally</sentence>
<exercise>30 My mum is going to</exercise>
<exercise>a) Think – pair – share: Read the profiles of the characters (pp.4/5) and try to guess which letter comes from one of them. Give reasons for your answers. Think – pair – share, p.149</exercise>
<exercise>b) Explain your ideas to your partner. Agree on the letter you both think is from a textbook character. Don’t you think it’s …? · It can’t be … because … · It’s probably … · My guess is that it’s … – No, that doesn’t make any sense because …</exercise>
<exercise>c) Work in groups: Present your choice to the group, giving reasons for your speculations.</exercise>
<exercise>10 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='15'>
<chapter>1/A</chapter>
<exercise>A3 a) Read Ally’s answers to the letters again. Note down what the teenagers should do.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Work with a partner. What do you think of Ally’s advice? Give reasons for your opinions. Use the following adjectives to comment on it: (not) helpful, useful, serious, amusing, arrogant .</exercise>
<exercise>I really don’t think/I think her advice is very … ∙ Her advice here is … because …</exercise>
<sentence>DearAlly, I’ve fallen in love with someone but he has no idea how I feel.</sentence>
<sentence>What can I do?</sentence>
<sentence>I’m dying of a broken heart.</sentence>
<sentence>The problem is that he’s my older brother’s best friend and they hang out together a lot.</sentence>
<sentence>They are ten years older than me though.</sentence>
<sentence>I think my brother knows how I feel but there’s no way I’m talking to him about it.</sentence>
<sentence>What can I do to make his friend love me?</sentence>
<sentence>Heartbroken, Camden</sentence>
<sentence>Dear Heartbroken, Sounds like you really do need some advice.</sentence>
<sentence>I think you probably just have a crush on your brother’s friend.</sentence>
<sentence>You don’t seem to know that much about him and you can’t love someone you don’t know.</sentence>
<sentence>And ten years is a big difference when you are only a teenager.</sentence>
<sentence>Try to forget about him.</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t worry – nobody dies of a broken heart and you will move on soon enough.</sentence>
<sentence>Yours, Ally</sentence>
<sentence>Dear Ally, I’m writing this letter to you because I really don’t know what to do about my sister.</sentence>
<sentence>She’s a bit younger than I am and we argue all the time.</sentence>
<sentence>She always comes into my room and wants me to help her with her homework.</sentence>
<sentence>Mum says I should be nice to her and explain things to her but sometimes I don’t have the time.</sentence>
<sentence>I have my own stuff to do, too.</sentence>
<sentence>And then she always takes my clothes without asking.</sentence>
<sentence>Last week I couldn’t find my favourite top.</sentence>
<sentence>Where do you think it was?</sentence>
<sentence>In my sister’s room of course!</sentence>
<sentence>Mum and Dad think I’m the one being difficult.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s not fair!</sentence>
<sentence>Please help.</sentence>
<sentence>Dear C.in Camden, You are not the first person to have problems with their sister.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s perfectly normal.</sentence>
<sentence>Obviously there are some things that you need to discuss.</sentence>
<sentence>She should not take your things without asking.</sentence>
<sentence>On the other hand you should think about your behaviour.</sentence>
<sentence>You don’t seem to be very friendly towards her.</sentence>
<sentence>Perhaps it would be a good idea to have a family conference.</sentence>
<sentence>Your mum and dad could help you.</sentence>
<sentence>Yours, Ally</sentence>
<exercise>A5 Target task v " Project Portfolio P1-P3</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at p.22.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Write a letter to Ally and put it in a box in the classroom.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Start your letter with Dear …, and end your letter with ∙ Say why you are writing the letter in the first sentence.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Take a letter out of the box and write</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Start your letter with Dear …, and ∙ Use the phrases you collected in A4. Writing, pp.144/145 WB A4, A5, pp.8/9</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 11</footnote>
<exercise>I’m dying of a</exercise>
<exercise>Yours,</exercise>
<exercise>all the time.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Think of a problem that your classmates will</exercise>
<exercise>understand.</exercise>
<exercise>an answer to it.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Try to give some useful advice.</exercise>
<gap>Yours, … You don’t have to write your real name.</gap>
<exercise>∙ Use the phrases you collected in A4.</exercise>
<gap>end your letter with Yours, …</gap>
</page>
<page id='16'>
<chapter>1/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 L 1/1 a) Listen to the conversation between Emma and Gillian. Say what they are talking about.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Describe Emma’s reaction to Gillian’s news.</exercise>
<exercise>B2 a) Look at the picture and describe what</exercise>
<exercise>c) v Extra: Finish the conversation between Emma and Gillian. Use phrases from A4 to ask for and give advice. Then present your conversation to the class with a partner.</exercise>
<exercise>Gillian and her mother are doing.</exercise>
<exercise>How do they feel?</exercise>
<exercise>Why might they feel like that?</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank People, p.174 P4</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read Mrs Collins’ story on page 13 and choose the best title for it. Explain your choice.</exercise>
<exercise>Mother and Daughter ∙ The New Baby ∙ Dropping the Bombshell ∙ Moving House</exercise>
<sentence>I’ve made your favourite breakfast, Gill.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m not hungry.</sentence>
<exercise>c) Read the story again and note down Gillian’s mother’s feelings in each part of the story in a grid. If possible, note down reasons. Graphic organizers, p.147 Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>part Gillian’smother</exercise>
<exercise>d) Gillian’s mother tells the story from her point of view. How do you think Gillian feels in each part? What might be her reasons? Complete the grid. WB B1, p.10</exercise>
<exercise>1 Firstrathernervous–becauseGwynniscomingto meetGillian Laterhappy–because…</exercise>
<gap>Miserable–probablybecause…</gap>
<exercise>B3 Target task v " Project Portfolio P5, P6</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at p.23.</exercise>
<exercise>In groups of four write the story from Gillian’s point of view.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the information in the grid (B2c) to write about how Gillian felt at different times in the story.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the simple past tense to tell the story. Check the list of irregular verbs on page 255. Writing, pp.144/145 Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Check that the different parts of the story fit together.</exercise>
<exercise>Writing, pp.144/145 3 When you are happy with your story, present it to another group.</exercise>
<exercise>Give some feedback.</exercise>
<exercise>Look at the criteria in 1 .</exercise>
<exercise>Speaking 2, p.140 WB B2, p.10</exercise>
<exercise>12 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>1 Each of you should rewrite one part of the story.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write about her thoughts.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the first person singular.</exercise>
<exercise>2 In your group:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Correct each other’s parts of the story.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='17'>
<chapter>1/B</chapter>
<exercise>Part 1</exercise>
<sentence>The next day was Saturday – the day Gwynn was coming to meet Gillian for the first time.</sentence>
<sentence>I was rather nervous about the visit so I decided to get up early and make Gillian’s favourite breakfast, pancakes with maple syrup.</sentence>
<sentence>Then Gillian came down looking really miserable.</sentence>
<sentence>I gave her a big smile and put the pancakes on the table but she said: “I’m not hungry!”</sentence>
<sentence>I had been afraid this might happen. I was quite upset but I decided to fight back my tears.</sentence>
    <sentence>While I was preparing breakfast, I turned the radio on and started singing along.</sentence>
<sentence>I was feeling so happy about the wedding.</sentence>
<sentence>“Why don’t we go into town together?” I suggested to cheer her up.</sentence>
<sentence>But she just went into her room and slammed the door shut.</sentence>
<sentence>I felt really hurt and even a bit angry.</sentence>
<exercise>Part 2</exercise>
<sentence>So I had my coffee, took a deep breath and went up to her room.</sentence>
<sentence>It was such a special day and I just wanted everyone to be happy.</sentence>
<sentence>However, when I went in, she looked very sad.</sentence>
<sentence>I sat down on her bed and put my arms around her.</sentence>
<sentence>I could see that her eyes were red from crying and I felt for her.</sentence>
<sentence>After a while I started to talk about Gwynn.</sentence>
<sentence>I told her about his job as a palaeontologist at Aberystwyth University.</sentence>
<sentence>He’s so intelligent and does all this exciting work with fossils.</sentence>
<sentence>Just thinking about him made me feel better.</sentence>
<sentence>But Gillian didn’t say anything and didn’t seem to care.</sentence>
    <exercise>Part 3</exercise>
<sentence>Although she had stopped crying, she still ignored me.</sentence>
<sentence>So I said: “Gwynn and I are expecting a baby!”</sentence>
<sentence>She just sat there looking tense.</sentence>
<sentence>I thought she was acting rather strangely but I decided to ignore it and to tell her the news.</sentence>
<sentence>I thought it was best to do it then and not wait for Gwynn as we had originally planned.</sentence>
<sentence>At these words Gillian seemed to go into a state of shock.</sentence>
<sentence>She just looked at me as if I had dropped a bombshell.</sentence>
<sentence>I must admit I was a bit disappointed by her reaction.</sentence>
<exercise>Part 4</exercise>
<sentence>Then she asked me angrily: “Will I have to share a room with this new baby?”</sentence>
<sentence>I tried not to show my disappointment although she must have noticed my reaction.</sentence>
<sentence>“There will be enough room for everyone in our big new house in Wales,” I answered.</sentence>
<sentence>I didn’t expect such a strong reaction from her.</sentence>
<sentence>“Why don’t you just get out of my room?” she shouted.</sentence>
    <sentence>I tried to kiss her on the cheek but she turned away angrily.</sentence>
<sentence>So I went into the kitchen.</sentence>
<sentence>Even if Gillian seemed upset about moving, I was relieved that I had told her everything.</sentence>
<sentence>I was confident that she would be fine once she met Gwynn.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 13</footnote>
</page>
<page id='18'>
<chapter>1/B</chapter>
<exercise>B4 Look at the following pictures and describe them.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Remember to use the present progressive for ∙ Write at least two sentences for each picture. Example: 1.Gillianispackingherbag.Sheis… LiF 1Rb: Present progressive, p.153 WB B3, B4 pp.11/12</exercise>
<exercise>B5</exercise>
<exercise>With a partner discuss what Gillian might do next and speculate on what might happen.</exercise>
<gap>She will probably … Maybe she will …</gap>
<exercise>1 2 3</exercise>
<exercise>B6 S 1, L 1/2 a) This is the song Gillian is listening to on the</exercise>
<exercise>bus.</exercise>
<exercise>Close your books and listen to it.</exercise>
<exercise>What is the mood of the person in the song?</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>The person singing the song sounds … ∙ He seems to be … ∙ My impression is that …</exercise>
<exercise>Simple Plan: Welcome to my life</exercise>
<sentence>Do you ever feel like breaking down?</sentence>
<sentence>Do you ever feel out of place?</sentence>
<sentence>Like somehow you just don’t belong / And no one understands you / Do you ever want to run away?</sentence>
<sentence>Do you lock yourself in your room?</sentence>
<sentence>With the radio on, turned up so loud / That no one hears you screaming</sentence>
<sentence>No, you don’t know what it’s like / When nothing feels alright</sentence>
<sentence>You don’t know what it’s like to be like me …</sentence>
<sentence>To be hurt, to feel lost / To be left out in the dark / To be kicked when you’re down / To feel like you’ve been pushed around / To be on the edge of breaking down / And no one’s there to save you</sentence>
<sentence>No, you don’t know what it’s like</sentence>
<sentence>Welcome to my life</sentence>
<exercise>5 Do you ever want to run away?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Now read the song lyrics. Collect five phrases which illustrate the person’s mood and the situation he or she is in.</exercise>
<exercise>c) v Choose: Write down Gillian’s thoughts while she is listening to the song. or: Describe a situation in which you would listen to this song. WB B5 p.12</exercise>
<gap>Do you lock yourself in your room? With the radio on, turned up so loud That no one hears you screaming No, you don’t know what it’s like When nothing feels alright You don’t know what it’s like to be like me …</gap>
<gap>To be hurt, to feel lost To be left out in the dark To be kicked when you’re down To feel like you’ve been pushed around To be on the edge of breaking down And no one’s there to save you No, you don’t know what it’s like Welcome to my life …</gap>
<exercise>14 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>Where is Gillian and what is she doing?</exercise>
<exercise>actions that are happening as you speak.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='19'>
<chapter>1/B</chapter>
<exercise>B7 L 1/3 a) Listen to the dialogue. Were you right in B5?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ what her father wants/doesn’t want.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Talk to a partner. What do you think about Gillian’s behaviour?</exercise>
<exercise>B8 L 1/4 a) Later on, Gillian’s parents both sit down and talk to her. Read the dialogue and say what happens to Gillian.</exercise>
<sentence>Mother: Oh, Gillian. I was so worried when I got back home and found your note.</sentence>
<sentence>How could you do that to me?</sentence>
<sentence>It’s not fair.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: What about me?</sentence>
<sentence>Having a baby and getting married is not fair, either.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: But I want my own dog here in Camden, not in stupid Wales!</sentence>
<sentence>Mother: Will you please stop shouting, Gillian?</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: Dad, why can’t I come and live with you?</sentence>
<sentence>Mother: I’m sorry, darling.</sentence>
<sentence>I hate keeping secrets from you.</sentence>
<sentence>I know I should have told you earlier.</sentence>
<sentence>Father: Er, I don’t think that will work, Gillian.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: Why not?</sentence>
<sentence>The flat’s big enough and I promise I’ll always tidy my room.</sentence>
<sentence>Father: Running away is not the answer, Gillian.</sentence>
<sentence>Father: Living with me isn’t an option.</sentence>
<sentence>Why didn’t you tell us how upset you were?</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: Mum was so happy about everything and I was so shocked.</sentence>
<sentence>Mother: But Gillian, having a baby sister or brother can be lots of fun and Gwynn is such a nice guy.</sentence>
<sentence>You know how little time I spend at home.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: What about Carol?</sentence>
<sentence>I can stay with her when you’re away.</sentence>
<sentence>Father: But Carol works too.</sentence>
<sentence>You can come and visit us in the holidays.</sentence>
<sentence>Then we can do things together.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian: I don’t care what he’s like.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m not going to Wales with him.</sentence>
<sentence>Mother: Let’s talk about this reasonably.</sentence>
<sentence>Moving house has its advantages.</sentence>
<sentence>We can go cycling and you can meet your friends.</sentence>
<sentence>Mother: Leaving you behind would make me very sad, Gillian.</sentence>
<sentence>Please come home with me.</sentence>
<sentence>Gwynn lives in the country and he’s got a dog.</sentence>
<sentence>Gwynn really wants to meet you.</sentence>
<sentence>You always wanted to have a dog, didn’t you?</sentence>
<exercise>Mother Father</exercise>
<exercise>b) Make a list of the arguments Gillian’s parents use to try to persuade her to accept the situation.</exercise>
<gap>Havingababysister or…</gap>
<sentence>Running away is not the answer.</sentence>
<exercise>B9 Grammar detective: gerund 1 Look at these sentences from the dialogue. The words in blue are called gerunds. Having a baby ... is not fair. I hate keeping secrets from you. Find other examples from the dialogue and write them down.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Gerunds are verbs used as nouns. They can be part of the subject or the object of a sentence. Look at the examples again. Are the gerunds</exercise>
<exercise>the subject or the object of these exercises?</exercise>
<exercise>3 How do you form a gerund?</exercise>
<exercise>Write a grammar card and check LiF 2 on page 155.</exercise>
<exercise>P7</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 15</footnote>
<exercise>b) Listen again and note down</exercise>
<exercise>∙ what Gillian wants/doesn’t want,</exercise>
</page>
<page id='20'>
<chapter>1/B</chapter>
<exercise>B10</exercise>
<exercise>Look at the following situations and write about them using a gerund.</exercise>
<exercise>You can use some of the following adjectives:</exercise>
<exercise>LiF 2: Gerund, pp.155/156 WB B6, p.13 Example: 1.Eatingwithchopstickscanbedifficult.</exercise>
<listing>scary · difficult · dangerous · easy · hard · exciting · …</listing>
<exercise>B11 Target task v P8, P9</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at pp.23/24.</exercise>
<exercise>Hot seat: Talk about the changes in Gillian’s life.</exercise>
<exercise>Ask and answer questions in the hot seat.</exercise>
<exercise>Use all the background information you have from A1, B2 and B8.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Prepare questions you would like to ask Gillian,</exercise>
<exercise>her mother, her father and Gwynn.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Put yourself in the situation of the character you have chosen.</exercise>
<exercise>Prepare for your role in the hot seat.</exercise>
<gap>Support Mrs Collins, why didn ’ t you …? Mr Collins, why can ’t Gillian …? Gillian, what do you think you …?</gap>
<exercise>∙ What is your biggest problem at the moment? ∙ How do you expect your life to change?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ How can you help Gillian? 3 Take turns to sit in the hot seat.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the gerund to answer some of the questions. Hot seat, p.149 WB B7, p.13</exercise>
<sentence>Why can’t you live in London, Gwynn?</sentence>
<sentence>Living in London is not possible because I work at a university in Wales.</sentence>
<exercise>16 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>Think about:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What is important to you?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ How do you feel about it?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What do you want to do next?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Ask your questions.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='21'>
<chapter>1/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 L 1/5 a) Read Emma’s text message</exercise>
<exercise>∙ who she sent it to ∙ what they will talk about at that meeting.</exercise>
<exercise>C2</exercise>
<sentence>Hi every1, Just got a phone call.</sentence>
<sentence>U won’t believe what I’ve just heard.</sentence>
<sentence>We MUST talk asap.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s meet @ 5 @ the Canal Café. Emma</sentence>
<exercise>b) Listen to what is happening at the Canal Café and check if your ideas from a) were right.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Listen again and take notes on</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the friends’ reaction to Emma’s news. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>a) Think – pair – share: Collect ideas on what you can organize/make/buy to cheer up and say goodbye to a friend who has to move away. Think – pair – share, p.149</exercise>
<exercise>b) Complete a survey to find out what your class’s top three ideas are.</exercise>
<exercise>C3 Later Caroline and Charlie are chatting online to discuss their ideas for Gillian’s farewell. a) Read the chat room dialogue. Note down any chat room language you don’t understand and work it out with a partner. WB C1, p.14</exercise>
<exercise>b) Write down Caroline’s and Charlie’s ideas.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Note down your opinion on Caroline’s and Charlie’s ideas. Give reasons for your opinion.</exercise>
<sentence>C-LINE: Hi, Charlie!</sentence>
<sentence>Have U got a good idea 4 Gillian?</sentence>
<sentence>CHABATZ: Thought about it all evening.</sentence>
<sentence>It isn’t easy, but IMO there R a few things we cud do.</sentence>
<sentence>C-LINE: Oh, sounds gr8. Tell me more.</sentence>
<sentence>CHABATZ: When all of U were talking bout how shocked Gillian was, I remembered wot happened a yr or 2 ago.</sentence>
<sentence>U remember Oscar?</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian was so :D while she was lukin after him.</sentence>
<sentence>and thn she got so upset when her mum told her she cudn’t keep him.</sentence>
<sentence>If she moves away, maybe she cud get a dog now.</sentence>
<sentence>We cud talk 2 her mum bout it.</sentence>
<sentence>Or we cud @ least buy a “Toy Oscar“ 4 her.</sentence>
<sentence>C-LINE: That wud b gr8, but I’m not sure if Mrs Collins wants 2 move in with her new bf AND have a puppy in her new home.</sentence>
<sentence>and we must b careful w a “Toy Oscar“.</sentence>
<sentence>She still takes the real Oscar 4 a walk.</sentence>
<sentence>If we give her a toy labrador, she will start 2 cry again cuz Oscar is staying here as well.</sentence>
<sentence>CHABATZ: IC what U mean.</sentence>
<sentence>Nothing bout dogs then.</sentence>
<sentence>C-LINE: We just have to b careful.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s bad enough as it is – no need to upset her even more.</sentence>
<sentence>CHABATZ: Yeah, yeah, I get your point – don’t worry.</sentence>
<sentence>We cud do something w photos.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m just checking my mobile and my files on my PC 4 good photos of Gillian and the things we did 2gether.</sentence>
<sentence>Some of them are v funny.</sentence>
<sentence>It wud be gr8 2 use those 4 a present.</sentence>
<sentence>C-LINE: I’m sure Gillian wud like that.</sentence>
<sentence>Or maybe a CD w our favourite music.</sentence>
<sentence>I think she is listening 2 music a lot @ the moment.</sentence>
<sentence>She doesn’t have 2 TLK 2 any1 then.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma met her and wanted 2 find out more bout her mum and her new bf, but she was listening 2 her MP3 player the whole time.</sentence>
<sentence>CHABATZ: Oh, I have 2 go.</sentence>
<sentence>My mobile’s ringing.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s Rajiv.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe he’s come up w another good idea.</sentence>
<sentence>CU tomorrow.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 17</footnote>
<exercise>and speculate on</exercise>
<exercise>and why,</exercise>
<exercise>∙ any new information about</exercise>
<exercise>Gillian and her situation,</exercise>
</page>
<page id='22'>
<chapter>1/C</chapter>
<exercise>C4 a) Complete the grid with sentences from the chat room dialogue.</exercise>
<gap>simple progressive present OK,soundsgreat. I’mjustchecking…</gap>
<exercise>b) Say when you use the simple and progressive forms. If you are not sure, check your grammar cards or LiF. LiF 1R: Tenses, p.153 P10, P11</exercise>
<gap>… past …</gap>
<gap>…</gap>
<exercise>WB C2, p.15</exercise>
<exercise>C5 Look at the pictures and write down what Emma’s friends were doing when she sent them her text (see C1). P12 WB C3, p.15</exercise>
<exercise>C6 Target task v Portfolio WB C4, p.16 Write Emma’s and Rajiv’s online chat.</exercise>
<exercise>Work with a partner: Emma and Rajiv are chatting online that night as well.</exercise>
<exercise>One of you is Emma, the other one Rajiv.</exercise>
<exercise>Write down their online chat.</exercise>
<exercise>Use pens in different colours.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Study your role card and collect ideas on what you could write about, e.g. ideas about what you could do for Gillian and how you feel about her situation.</exercise>
<exercise>Your ideas from C2 can help you.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Go through the chat in C3 again and collect words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ to express what you think about someone else’s</exercise>
<exercise>comment.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Your chat should also answer the following</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What was Gillian doing when you last saw her?</exercise>
<exercise>at the moment?</exercise>
<exercise>You can start like this: Writing, pp.144/145</exercise>
<gap>When Emma sent Charlie her text, he was …</gap>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at p.25.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ You are good with computers and at writing. You would like to use that to produce</exercise>
<exercise>∙ You know that Gillian likes animals very much. You want to cheer her up by telling her the advantages of living in the country.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ You feel sorry for Gillian.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Music is very important to you and you would like to do something for Gillian with music.</exercise>
<exercise>RJV: Hi, how R U?</exercise>
<gap>M-A: I’m still a bit worried about Gillian …</gap>
<exercise>18 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>Role card: Emma</exercise>
<exercise>something for Gillian.</exercise>
<exercise>and phrases</exercise>
<exercise>∙ to express your opinion and</exercise>
<exercise>Role card: Rajiv</exercise>
<exercise>∙ You have already asked</exercise>
<exercise>Sheree for some tips.</exercise>
<exercise>questions:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What are you doing at the moment?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What do you think Gillian is doing</exercise>
</page>
<page id='23'>
<chapter>1/C</chapter>
<exercise>C7 L 1/6 P16 a) The friends have agreed on what they want to do for Gillian. Listen to</exercise>
<exercise>b) v Extra: What do you think about the friends’ radio message? Discuss in class.</exercise>
<exercise>the clip from a radio show and explain what they have done.</exercise>
<exercise>C8 S 2, L 1/7</exercise>
<gap>What the friends have done is fantastic, but I still don’t think that …</gap>
<gap>It’s strange/ embarrassing to …</gap>
<exercise>a) Listen to the song that Gillian’s friends b) Listen to the song again and read the lyrics.</exercise>
<exercise>have chosen for her.</exercise>
<exercise>Try to understand as much of the lyrics as possible.</exercise>
<exercise>Imagine that your friends have chosen this song for you.</exercise>
<exercise>Describe your feelings</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Comment on whether the song that the friends chose for Gillian is right for her.</exercise>
<gap>I think/don’t think the song is the right one for Gillian in her situation because …</gap>
<exercise>about it.</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Imagine you are Gillian. Write down what she could tell her friends about the song.</exercise>
<gap>The lyrics of the song express that/how … I’m not sure what to think of the music</gap>
<gap>because … The lyrics make me feel … I was delighted/embarrassed because … Although it’s a very sweet way to show how …, I feel that …</gap>
<exercise>WB C5, p.16</exercise>
<gap>Support The music sounds happy/upbeat/sad/angry. The music makes you feel full of energy/depressed because … The music is fast/slow. The music has a catchy melody/has a powerful beat. The lyrics (don’t) fit Gillian’s situation.</gap>
<exercise>Hannah Montana (Miley Cyrus), True Friend</exercise>
<sentence>We sign our cards and letters BFF</sentence>
<sentence>You’ve got a million ways to make me laugh You’re lookin’ out for me; you’ve got my back It’s so good to have you around</sentence>
<sentence>You know the secrets I could never tell And when I’m quiet you break through my shell Don’t feel the need to do a rebel yell ‘cause you keep my feet on the ground</sentence>
<sentence>Chorus: You’re a true friend You’re here till the end You pull me aside When something ain’t right Talk with me now and into the night ‘til it’s alright again You’re a true friend</sentence>
<sentence>You don’t get angry when I change the plans Somehow you’re never out of second chances Won’t say “I told you” when I’m wrong again I’m so lucky that I’ve found</sentence>
<exercise>Chorus</exercise>
<sentence>True friends will go to the ends of the earth ‘till they find the thing you need Friends hang on through the ups and the downs ‘cause they’ve got someone to believe in</sentence>
<exercise>c) v Extr Ex Extra: tr 1 Choose a song that you would play for someone in Gillian’s situation.</exercise>
<exercise>Note down why you think it is a good song to play for someone like Gillian.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Bring the song and the lyrics to class and present your songs to each other in small groups.</exercise>
<exercise>Choose the best song for Gillian in your group.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 19</footnote>
<exercise>v Choose:</exercise>
<exercise>or:</exercise>
<exercise>rite d what he</exercise>
</page>
<page id='24'>
<chapter>1/C</chapter>
<exercise>C9 L 1/8 Listen to the friends. Say what they think about the song and the other ideas for Gillian. P13, P17</exercise>
<exercise>C10</exercise>
<exercise>Charlie has made an online album for Gillian.</exercise>
<exercise>All the friends can upload some photos.</exercise>
<exercise>They should write what they remember about their time with Gillian and comment on the pictures.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Look at some of Charlie’s photos and what he has written about them. Note down what his comments tell you about Gillian’s character and her interests.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Go through Theme 1 and add more information about Gillian to your list.</exercise>
<exercise>Gillian ’ scharacter • braveenoughtoaska footballstarfora photo • ...</exercise>
<sentence>Do you remember this?</sentence>
<sentence>We were just shopping happily at Camden Lock Market when we saw this man.</sentence>
<sentence>You said that it was Darren Johnson from Arsenal but I wasn’t sure at first.</sentence>
<sentence>We even had a little fight over it.</sentence>
<sentence>As we couldn’t agree, you went over bravely and just asked him if he was Darren Johnson.</sentence>
<sentence>That was so cool of you!</sentence>
<sentence>When you spoke to him rather nervously, he laughed and I took a photo of you and him.</sentence>
<sentence>Do you still have the autograph he gave you?</sentence>
<sentence>Wasn’t it on one of your exercise books?</sentence>
<sentence>You’re such a great football expert.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m going to miss our conversations about the latest Arsenal news.</sentence>
<sentence>I think this is one of the funniest pictures I have of you.</sentence>
<sentence>You look so uncomfortable in it.</sentence>
<sentence>We went to Notting Hill Carnival that day with my family.</sentence>
<sentence>I think Josephine was dancing wildly on one of the floats.</sentence>
<sentence>Everyone in my family was wearing a costume.</sentence>
<sentence>You didn’t want one, but my mum made you wear this funny hat.</sentence>
<sentence>I think you waited politely for the right moment to take it off, but my mum was always around.</sentence>
<sentence>It all comes back to me when I look at this photo.</sentence>
<sentence>That’s what I like about it.</sentence>
<exercise>c) Buzz groups: Compare your lists and add relevant information. Buzz groups, p.149</exercise>
<exercise>d) Look at Charlie’s comments. Find example sentences for the following categories:</exercise>
<exercise>1 Talking directly to Gillian 2 Saying how he feels about this memory 3 Speculating on how Gillian felt at the time</exercise>
<exercise>4 Describing her character 5 Complimenting her 6 Explaining why he chose that particular photo</exercise>
<exercise>20 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='25'>
<chapter>1/C</chapter>
<exercise>C11 a) Find examples of adjectives and adverbs in Charlie’s comments. When do you use which? Check your grammar cards or LiF if you aren’t sure. LiF 3R: Adverbs of manner, p.156 P14</exercise>
<exercise>b) Look at Charlie’s comments again. Complete the following sentences using happy or sad, or the adverbs happily or sadly .</exercise>
<gap>WB C6, p.17 1 As Gillian is going to leave soon, Charlie is very … 2 He writes … about the fact that Gillian loves football, too. 3 But he writes … that he can no longer talk to Gillian about Arsenal. 4 He is … when he thinks about his family’s behaviour at Notting Hill Carnival. 5 When he looks at that photo, he remembers … what happened on that day.</gap>
<exercise>C12 Target task v Portfolio Need help? Look at p.26.</exercise>
<exercise>Write comments for photos for Charlie’s website.</exercise>
<exercise>Writing, pp.144/145</exercise>
<exercise>1 Read the profiles of Gillian’s friends (pp.4/5). Choose to be</exercise>
<exercise>one of them – Charlie, Caroline, Emma, George or Rajiv.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Then choose at least four of the pictures below and write your comments for them like Charlie did (see C10).</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the useful words and phrases you collected in C6. You are free to make up a situation if the picture does not give you a clear idea what it is about.</exercise>
<exercise>2 3</exercise>
<exercise>4 5</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 21</footnote>
<exercise>Make sure you use</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the ideas you collected about Gillian,</exercise>
</page>
<page id='36'>
<chapter>2/A</chapter>
<exercise>First impressions</exercise>
<exercise>A1 a) Look at the photos and the map. What do you learn about Wales?</exercise>
<exercise>b) v Extra: Speculate on how</exercise>
<exercise>Prestatyn Llandudno</exercise>
<exercise>Beaumaris Castle</exercise>
<exercise>Conwy Castle</exercise>
<exercise>1062 Bangor Denbigh Caernarfon Castle Tryfan</exercise>
<exercise>Wrexham</exercise>
<exercise>Gillian feels about moving to Wales.</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank People, p.174 WB A1, p.25</exercise>
<exercise>Pwllheli</exercise>
<exercise>Snowdon</exercise>
<exercise>Portmeirion</exercise>
<exercise>Harlech Castle</exercise>
<exercise>Blaenau Ffestiniog</exercise>
<exercise>Snowdonia National Lake</exercise>
<exercise>t 892</exercise>
<exercise>D e e</exercise>
<exercise>Llangollen</exercise>
<exercise>Berwyn Mountains</exercise>
<exercise>Lake Vyrnwy</exercise>
<exercise>Bellevue Park Pontcysyllte Aqueduct</exercise>
<exercise>Chirk Castle</exercise>
<exercise>Cader Idris n Welshpool</exercise>
<exercise>Powis Castle & Gardens S e v e r n</exercise>
<exercise>M Newtown</exercise>
<exercise>Map of Wales Aberystwyth</exercise>
<exercise>(Population: 3,064,000)</exercise>
<exercise>Railway Motorway Road</exercise>
<exercise>Castle Church Place of interest</exercise>
<exercise>National Library of Wales W a l e s</exercise>
<exercise>Offa’s Dyke Path</exercise>
<exercise>River, lake Water sports Mountains Pony trekking National Park Zoo</exercise>
<exercise>miles 10 km 10</exercise>
<exercise>St. David’s Cathedral</exercise>
<exercise>Fishguard</exercise>
<exercise>Pembrokeshire Coast</exercise>
<exercise>National Park</exercise>
<exercise>Cardigan</exercise>
<exercise>Llandysul</exercise>
<exercise>C</exercise>
<exercise>Carmarthen</exercise>
<exercise>i r m</exercise>
<exercise>T o w y</exercise>
<exercise>Builth Wells</exercise>
<exercise>Hay-on-Wye</exercise>
<exercise>Brecon Black Brecon Beacons</exercise>
<exercise>886 National Park Brecon Beacons</exercise>
<exercise>A2 L 1/10</exercise>
<exercise>Milford Haven Pembroke</exercise>
<exercise>Pembroke Castle</exercise>
<exercise>Pembrey Country Park Llanelli</exercise>
<exercise>Swansea</exercise>
<exercise>National Waterfront Museum</exercise>
<exercise>Big Pit National Coal Museum Neath Ta f f Pontypool</exercise>
<exercise>Caerphilly Castle Chepstow Port Talbot Newport Cardiff Castle The LC Bridgend Millennium Stadium Wales Millennium Centre National History Museum</exercise>
<exercise>a) Listen to Gillian and her mother. Which places are they talking about? Find them on the map.</exercise>
<exercise>Barry</exercise>
<exercise>Cardiff National Museum Cardiff dw 4</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What does her mother say about Wales? Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>c) Say why they are talking about Aberystwyth and Llandysul.</exercise>
<exercise>32 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>o n w y</exercise>
<exercise>a</exercise>
<exercise>i</exercise>
<exercise>n</exercise>
<exercise>s</exercise>
<exercise>Holyhead</exercise>
<exercise>Anglesey</exercise>
<exercise>Rhyl</exercise>
<exercise>Colwyn Bay</exercise>
<exercise>Penrhyn Castle V a l e o f C l w y d</exercise>
<exercise>C</exercise>
<exercise>Bala</exercise>
<exercise>Park</exercise>
<exercise>u</exercise>
<exercise>o</exercise>
<exercise>n</exercise>
<exercise>20 30</exercise>
<exercise>20 40</exercise>
<exercise>a</exercise>
<exercise>T e i fi</exercise>
<exercise>b</exercise>
<exercise>W y e</exercise>
<exercise>Mountains</exercise>
<exercise>Merthyr Tyd fi l</exercise>
<exercise>U s k</exercise>
<exercise>Rhondda</exercise>
<exercise>Caerphilly</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and take notes:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What does Gillian say about Wales?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='37'>
<chapter>2/A</chapter>
<exercise>A3 a) Gillian and her mother go for a walk in Aberystwyth. Look at the map of Wales and the brochure about Aberystwyth below. Collect words and phrases to talk about places in a grid like this: Wordbank Places, p.175 P1</exercise>
<sentence>transport sights location</sentence>
<sentence>Help! I have landed on the moon!</sentence>
<sentence>Wales is very strange.</sentence>
<sentence>At least we found a KikiCoffee here in Aberystwyth!</sentence>
<sentence>Miss London already.</sentence>
<sentence>Say hi to everyone!</sentence>
<gap>railway …</gap>
<gap>lake …</gap>
<gap>bythesea …</gap>
<sentence>We miss U 2!!!</sentence>
<sentence>Is A. a big town?</sentence>
<sentence>There must be something interesting to do</sentence>
<exercise>b) You already know many things about Wales. Read Gillian’s text message to Caroline first. Then read the brochure and answer Caroline’s questions. P15, P16 WB A2, A3, p.26</exercise>
<exercise>on the seafront!</exercise>
<exercise>What kind of shops do they have?</exercise>
<exercise>A4 L 1/11 a) Mrs Collins is listening to a radio programme on Wales. Which places are mentioned? Note down the most important information on the places. Wordbank Places, p.175</exercise>
<exercise>b) Mrs Collins wants to show Gillian more of Wales. Choose one place you think</exercise>
<sentence>Aberystwyth is asmall town by the sea (population 13,500) on the west coast of Wales.</sentence>
<sentence>The town lies between three hills and has a seafront with two beaches, some castle ruins, a pier and a harbour.</sentence>
<sentence>One of the three hills, Pen Dinas to the south, has a monument to the Duke of Wellington.</sentence>
<sentence>To the north is Constitution Hill with its cliff railway.</sentence>
<sentence>Rising to the east is Penglais Hill with the hospital, the National Library of Wales and the main Aberystwyth University Campus.</sentence>
<sentence>From the centre of town you can get to almost everywhere in Aberystwyth in 10-15 minutes.</sentence>
<sentence>Aberystwyth is full of shops that you can see on anyhigh street in Britain – with afew seaside shops thrown in.</sentence>
<sentence>There are also some markets which sell products from the region.</sentence>
<exercise>A5 Target task v " Project P2 WB A4, p.26 Need help? Look at p.44.</exercise>
<exercise>Work in groups of four.</exercise>
<exercise>Look at the map of Wales and choose a place.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Do some research on the Internet to find out information about it. Searching the Internet, p.143</exercise>
<exercise>2 Make notes and prepare a short presentation. Talk about where your place is, what is special about it and what you can do/see there. Use your words and phrases from A3a). Speaking 1, pp.139/140</exercise>
<exercise>3 Give your presentation. Each group member should say a few sentences.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 33</footnote>
</page>
<page id='38'>
<chapter>2/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 L 1/12</exercise>
<exercise>a) Listen to Gillian’s conversation with her mother and Gwynn. What is the problem?</exercise>
<exercise>B2</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and make notes on</exercise>
<exercise>∙ how Gillian reacts. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>c) Work with a partner. Talk about how you would feel if you had to change schools.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Scan the websites to find out where the schools are. Find the places on the map on page 32. Reading, p.142</exercise>
<exercise>b) Decisions, decisions … Which is the right school for Gillian? 1 Read the websites again and note down information</exercise>
<exercise>about the schools in a grid.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Compare the schools.</exercise>
<exercise>Which aspects might Gillian find positive/negative?</exercise>
<exercise>Check Gillian’s profile on page 5 if you are not sure.</exercise>
<gap>WildingsSchool StDavid’sCollege … …</gap>
<exercise>Wildings School</exercise>
<exercise>Home Intranet News Riding School Information</exercise>
<sentence>Girls Day and Boarding School</sentence>
<sentence>You can find Wildings School near Denbigh in North Wales.</sentence>
<sentence>The school is 45 minutes away from the city of Chester, and one hour away from Liverpool and Manchester International Airport.</sentence>
<sentence>Wildings is the only school in the country with a riding school, a sailing centre, a swimming pool and a recording studio.</sentence>
<sentence>We also have a special dance and music programme.</sentence>
<sentence>Many students choose to study at Wildings because English is the school’s first language.</sentence>
<sentence>Students can study Welsh as an extracurricular subject.</sentence>
<sentence>Boarding is great for girls who want to live and learn together with all their friends.</sentence>
<sentence>Our housemothers prepare breakfast for the girls each morning and do all cleaning and laundry for the first three years.</sentence>
<sentence>We expect our students to take part in 2-3 after-school activities per week.</sentence>
<sentence>They have plenty of options to choose from: film club, choir, electronics club, art club, lacrosse, creative writing and many more.</sentence>
<sentence>Students can have riding lessons at all times of the day and evening, too.</sentence>
<sentence>Fees: Boarding £ 4,350 to £ 4,850 per term</sentence>
<exercise>34 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ what Gwynn and Gillian’s</exercise>
<exercise>mother suggest,</exercise>
</page>
<page id='39'>
<chapter>2/B</chapter>
<exercise>c) Discuss your results from B2b) with a partner. Speaking 3, p.141</exercise>
<exercise>d) v Extra: Which of the two schools do you like better? Explain why.</exercise>
<gap>Support I think Gillian would prefer … because … … is a more suitable school for Gillian because … Gillian would feel happier at … because … What Gillian would enjoy at … is that …</gap>
<exercise>St David’s College, Llandudno, North Wales</exercise>
<exercise>Home The School SEN Outdoor Education Sport 6th Form News and Events Intranet Old Davideans Contact Us</exercise>
<sentence>With the sea on one side and Snowdonia on the other, where better to improve your education?</sentence>
<sentence>It’s not all water and mountains, though!</sentence>
<sentence>Your talents may lie in the laboratory, in design or on the sports field.Together with you and your parents, we aim to improve those talents.Welsh is also a compulsory subject.</sentence>
<sentence>St David’s is small enough to provide a real ‘family atmosphere’ for boarding school students There are three houses for boys and one for girls.</sentence>
<sentence>Our houseparents look after our boarders.That means they have a housemother and a housefather.</sentence>
<sentence>Most boarders are full boarders, but we also offer weekly and flexi-boarding.</sentence>
<sentence>Each house offers a leisure room and a kitchen for snacks.</sentence>
<sentence>Dormitories are small, with no more than 4-6 pupils per room.</sentence>
<sentence>6th Formers have single or double bedrooms.</sentence>
<sentence>Every Davidean becomes a member of a ‘house’: Cader Idris, Snowdon or Tryfan.</sentence>
<sentence>Day pupils, too, belong to these houses and take part in academic and cultural activities and sports for the House Cup each year.The House Cup includes football, swimming, hockey, cricket and tennis.</sentence>
<sentence>Outdoor education Making the most of the beautiful mountains, rivers, lakes, forests, beaches and sea near Snowdonia National Park, our pupils take part in different outdoor activities: climbing, kayaking, caving, sailing, orienteering, team tasks, mountain walking and beach activities are just a few examples.We use this huge outdoor classroom to add to the traditional classroom subjects.</sentence>
<sentence>Annual boarding fee: £ 16,950- £ 20,787 Entry is by selection or scholarship exam following an interview with the headmaster.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 35</footnote>
</page>
<page id='40'>
<chapter>2/B</chapter>
<exercise>B3 a) Read Gillian’s diary entry. Make notes on what her problems are and how she feels. Keep your notes for later.</exercise>
<exercise>Friday23rdSeptember</exercise>
<exercise>Reading, p.142</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>P3</exercise>
<sentence>Friday 23rd September. We’ll drive to the north coast tomorrow and have a look at two boarding schools with Gwynn.</sentence>
<sentence>His sister went to Wildings and he says itwould be great for me.</sentence>
<sentence>If they had a football team, it wouldn’t be so bad, but it’s all so girly-girly with horses and ballet dancing and everything, yuk!</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t want to go to the school in Llandysul either.</sentence>
<sentence>It still feels like Gwynn and Mum just want me to go to boarding school because of the new baby.</sentence>
<sentence>Miss my pals like crazy, miss London and my old school.</sentence>
<sentence>If my friends were here, boarding school would actually be fun.</sentence>
<sentence>Being the new girl at school without any friends will be horrible.</sentence>
<sentence>:-( And it’s all Gwynn’s fault!</sentence>
<sentence>The village wherewe live now is theworst.</sentence>
<sentence>20 minutes to the nearest supermarket.</sentence>
<sentence>If there was a shopping centre, I could at least go shopping.</sentence>
<sentence>But there’s nothing, no shops, no cinema, no nothing… only sheep!</sentence>
<sentence>My room is really nice and big though and we have a fab garden which is great for playing football.</sentence>
<sentence>If I made some friends in the village, we could have a great time there.</sentence>
<sentence>I met Gruffudd, the boy from next door, this afternoon.</sentence>
<sentence>He seems nice. He started talking to me in Welsh and I couldn’t understand ANYTHING.</sentence>
<sentence>He then spoke English and told me he plays rugby.</sentence>
<sentence>Well, it’s not football but I might have to learn to like it.</sentence>
<sentence>They all love rugby here.</sentence>
<sentence>Aargh, if I had some credit on my phone, I could call Caroline.</sentence>
<sentence>Hope I get some pocketmoney tomorrow.</sentence>
<exercise>b) Scan Gillian’s diary entry again and complete the following sentences. 1 If they had a football team at Wildings School, … 2 If Gillian’s friends were there, … 3 If Gillian had some credit on her phone, …</exercise>
<exercise>WB B1, B2, p.27</exercise>
<exercise>B4 Grammar detective: conditional clauses, type 2 1 Look at these sentences: conditional, type 1: If Caroline comes to Wales, we will go shopping in Aberystwyth. conditional, type 2: If I had some credit on my phone, I could call Caroline.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Find two more sentences which use the conditional, type 2 from B3 and write them down.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Add the grid to your grammar card on conditionals. Then look at your sentences and complete the grid.</exercise>
<gap>if-clause mainclause conditional,type1 simplepresent will+in fi nitive conditional,type2 … …or…+in fi nitive</gap>
<exercise>4 When do you use conditional, type 2? Add this information to your grammar card. Look at LiF 7 on page159 to check your grammar card. WB B3, p.28</exercise>
<exercise>B5</exercise>
<exercise>What would you do if you were in Gillian’s, Caroline’s or Gruffudd’s situation?</exercise>
<exercise>Talk to a partner about it.</exercise>
<exercise>LiF 7: Conditional clauses, type 2, p.159</exercise>
<exercise>P4, P5, P13 WB B4, p.28</exercise>
<exercise>If I lived in a very small village, If I had a new neighbour, If I had to go to boarding school, If my family moved away, If my best friend moved away, If I met someone new,</exercise>
<gap>I would/I’d … I wouldn’t … I could … I couldn’t …</gap>
<exercise>36 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='41'>
<chapter>2/B</chapter>
<exercise>B6 S 4, L 1/13 a) Look at the pictures to find out more about Gruffudd. Work with a partner and ask and answer questions about him. LiF 4R: Questions, p.157</exercise>
<gap>What are his I think his hobbies? hobbies are …</gap>
<exercise>b) Listen to Gruffudd. Check your answers from a) and find out more about him. WB B5, p.29</exercise>
<exercise>B7 S 5, L 1/14 a) Look at the picture. What are Gillian and Gruffudd doing? Describe what you can see. Wordbank Pictures, p.176</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen to Gillian and Gruffudd. Are these statements right or wrong?</exercise>
<exercise>1 In a football match the other players can hurt you more seriously.</exercise>
<exercise>Gruffudd yw f’enw i.</exercise>
<exercise>– My name is Gruffudd.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Football players have to train more regularly than rugby players.</exercise>
<exercise>Llandysul</exercise>
<exercise>2 Gillian thinks that rugby players must train harder than football players.</exercise>
<exercise>c) v Extra: Correct the statements that are wrong.</exercise>
<exercise>B8 Grammar card: comparison of adverbs 1 Look at these exercises from B7 to find out about the comparison of adverbs. Football players earn money more easily . Gillian thinks that rugby players must train harder than football players.</exercise>
<exercise>B9 v Extra: Viewing: Rugby a) Watch the clip about rugby. Write down the most important facts about this sport. Viewing, p.139</exercise>
<exercise>4 Football players earn money more easily. 5 Arwyn Lloyd ran the fastest.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Look at LiF 9 on page 160. Write a grammar card for the comparison of adverbs. Include information on superlatives. Write down irregular forms as well and learn them by heart. P12 WB B6, p.30</exercise>
<listing>ground the ball · forwards · backwards · catch · throw · tackling · in-goal area · scrum · mouth guard</listing>
<exercise>b) Use your notes to describe rugby.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 37</footnote>
</page>
<page id='42'>
<chapter>2/B</chapter>
<exercise>B10 a) Gwynn has a surprise for Gillian. Scan her diary entry for Saturday and find out what it is.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the diary entry again and say why and how Gillian’s mood has changed. Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<sentence>Saturday 24th September, Just spoke to Caroline and told her the good news!</sentence>
<sentence>She can come and visit me, woohoo!</sentence>
<sentence>Mum told me in the car today.</sentence>
<sentence>She said it was Gwynn’s idea and he’s also buying the train ticket for Caroline.</sentence>
<sentence>How generous is that? I was so pleased I even gave him a hug.</sentence>
<sentence>Embarrassing, I know… but he tries to be friendly and is actually quite funny sometimes.</sentence>
<sentence>Ohh, if only Caroline was here already.</sentence>
<sentence>We will have so much fun.</sentence>
<sentence>Gwynn said he can take us all to Aberystwyth one day so we can do some shopping and go to the cinema while he is at the university.</sentence>
<sentence>:-) Will have to work hard until then if I want to go to St David’s.</sentence>
<sentence>Have my assessment next week and lots of things to study, eek!</sentence>
<sentence>Gruffudd said he can help with my studies because he is two years older and knows all the stuff.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m so glad he lives next door.</sentence>
<sentence>His family are great, too.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe it wouldn’t be so bad to go to school here in Llandysul after all???</sentence>
<sentence>Must talk to Caroline about it…</sentence>
<exercise>d) Read Gillian’s diary entry for Friday (p. 36) again and find more examples to fill in the grid. WB B7, p.31</exercise>
<exercise>B11 Target task v Portfolio Need help? Look at pp.44/45. Write Caroline’s or Gruffudd’s diary entry for Saturday. Make sure you use the appropriate language. Use your results from B10c) for help. Writing, pp.144/145 Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>Choose: or:</exercise>
<exercise>Support You can use Gillian’s diary entries as models for your texts.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write what you think about Gillian ∙ Say how you feel about visiting</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Describe how you would feel if you had to move far away from your friends.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Think about how you feel about ∙ Say which school you think Gillian</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Describe how you would feel if you had to move far away from your friends.</exercise>
<exercise>38 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>Write Caroline’s diary entry.</exercise>
<exercise>Write Gruffudd’s diary entry.</exercise>
<exercise>moving away.</exercise>
<exercise>Gillian, your new neighbour.</exercise>
<exercise>your friend in Wales soon.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write about what you did on Saturday.</exercise>
<exercise>should go to.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write about what you did on Saturday.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='43'>
<chapter>2/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 Gillian has passed her assessment and her first day at St David’s is near. Imagine what it is like to go to a new school. Speculate on how Gillian might feel at the new school. What could her hopes and worries be?</exercise>
<exercise>C2 a) Gillian has been at St David’s for b) Read Gillian’s email on page 40. a week. What would you like to ask her about her new school? questions from a), note them Note down questions and collect ∙ Note down more information them in class. LiF 4R: Questions, p.157 about Gillian’s new school.</exercise>
<exercise>C3 a) Scan Gillian’s email on page 40 and collect school words in Support</exercise>
<exercise>c) v Extra: Find the missing answers to your questions about St David’s on the Internet. Searching the Internet, p.143</exercise>
<exercise>WB C1, p.32</exercise>
<exercise>a word web.</exercise>
<exercise>Add other school words that you know already.</exercise>
<exercise>Graphic organizers, p.147 b) Describe what is special about going to a boarding school.</exercise>
<exercise>Check the websites on pp.34/35 for more words.</exercise>
<exercise>C4 a) Read Gillian’s email again and say if the following statements are right or wrong. Which line(s) can you find the information in?</exercise>
<gap>The first statement is … because Gillian writes “…” in lines …</gap>
<exercise>1 Gillian likes the buildings at her new school. 2 Gillian is glad that St David’s is a mixed</exercise>
<exercise>school.</exercise>
<exercise>3 She hates lessons in small groups.</exercise>
<exercise>4 There is one compulsory subject that Gillian doesn’t like.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Compare Gillian’s new school to your school.</exercise>
<exercise>5 Gillian realizes that there are advantages in</exercise>
<exercise>having a school uniform.</exercise>
<exercise>6 The students who have come back from their</exercise>
<exercise>expedition didn’t enjoy it.</exercise>
<exercise>7 St David’s supports a school project in Uganda.</exercise>
<exercise>8 Gillian wishes she could go home after school.</exercise>
<exercise>Which aspects of St David’s do you like?</exercise>
<exercise>What do you prefer at your school?</exercise>
<exercise>Say why.</exercise>
<exercise>WB C2, p.32</exercise>
<exercise>C5 Grammar card: relative clauses 1 Find examples of relative clauses with who , which and that from Gillian’s email on page 40. Example: The students who have just come back talk about nothing else.</exercise>
<exercise>2 When do you use who ? When do you use which ? When can you use that ? Look at LiF 10a on page 161 for help. Write a grammar card for relative clauses. P6, P7</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 39</footnote>
<exercise>∙ If you find answers to your</exercise>
<exercise>down.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='44'>
<chapter>2/C</chapter>
<sentence>Hi Caroline and George, What a week – but I survived.</sentence>
<sentence>St David’s is just so different!</sentence>
<sentence>Even the buildings seem quite scary at first.</sentence>
<sentence>St David’s is this big country house – well, not like the Harry Potter halls – but still very posh.</sentence>
<sentence>Luckily, the dorms are in modern buildings, so it’s more like a normal place.</sentence>
<sentence>I share my room with five girls who seem OK, but I think it’ll take years to make friends here, you know, they’ve been pals for a long, long time …</sentence>
<sentence>The good news is that there are lots of boys at this school!</sentence>
<sentence>However, the first day in class was a shock: only 12 students in our class, and the groups are even smaller for maths and English, it’s just 8!!!</sentence>
<sentence>Can you imagine? You have to concentrate all the time.</sentence>
<sentence>NO chatting, which is quite a challenge!</sentence>
<sentence>But I must admit lessons seem to be more fun.</sentence>
<sentence>It would even improve your maths, George.</sentence>
<sentence>;-) Of course, there is one compulsory subject that I don’t really like: Welsh!</sentence>
<sentence>It looks like a secret code to me which seems like a waste of time!</sentence>
<sentence>But maybe I can surprise Gruffudd.</sentence>
<sentence>I must have told you that I have to wear school uniform now which I was sure I would hate.</sentence>
<sentence>But it saves lots of time in the morning when you have to get ready for school ;-).</sentence>
<sentence>And the school uniform we have to wear looks OK.</sentence>
<sentence>Actually it makes me feel a bit better.</sentence>
<sentence>As all the students wear uniform, you can’t really spot the girls who come from very rich families.</sentence>
<sentence>I’ve attached the daily timetable.</sentence>
<sentence>Hard, isn’t it? You two should count yourselves lucky.</sentence>
<sentence>But it’s fun, too, since the choice of subjects is just amazing.</sentence>
<sentence>You can do them all for GCSE and for A levels, too!!!</sentence>
<sentence>And there are lots of extracurricular activities which are fantastic …</sentence>
<sentence>Can you imagine a husky expedition in Scandinavia or sea kayaking in Alaska? Sounds cool, right? – The students who have just come back talk about nothing else.</sentence>
<sentence>And now it’s time to choose next year’s expedition.</sentence>
<sentence>I just wonder who can afford to go.</sentence>
<sentence>Our school is also big on supporting school children in Africa.</sentence>
<sentence>Students go to Uganda and help at a centre for kids who live in Kampala.</sentence>
<sentence>I might do that when I’m older …</sentence>
<sentence>It would be great to be one of the students in day school who can go home after lessons.</sentence>
<sentence>But Mum has promised that I can come home every weekend.</sentence>
<sentence>It feels so strange not to be there when the “new family” is starting their life in Llandysul.</sentence>
<sentence>They try to make it easier for us boarders.</sentence>
<sentence>My tutor is in my house and there are houseparents so there is a family feeling, but I’d much rather be with my own family…</sentence>
<sentence>Miss you all! Gillian</sentence>
<exercise>New Timings of Academic Day</exercise>
<exercise>Arrival 8.35 am Registration &amp; tutor time 8.45 am Assembly 9.00 am Period 1 9.20 am Period 2 10.00 am Break 10.40 am Period 3 11.10 am Period 4 11.50 am Lunch for Years 6–9 Period 5 for Years 10–13 12.30 pm Lunch for Years 10–13 Period 5 for Years 6–9 1.10 pm Period 6 1.50 pm Period 7 2.30 pm Break 3.10 pm Period 8 3.40 pm Period 9 4.20 pm Day pupils depart 5.00 pm Optional prep support 5.00 pm to 5.45 pm</exercise>
<exercise>40 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='45'>
<chapter>2/C</chapter>
<exercise>C6 a) Read statements 1-8 and work out the answers. You can find them in Gillian’s email.</exercise>
<exercise>1 This is a room which is very big. 2 This is a room in which students sleep. 3 This is a person who is a friend. 4 This is a subject that students have to take. 5 This is something that you have to wear at</exercise>
<exercise>many English schools.</exercise>
<exercise>6 These are activities from which you can</exercise>
<exercise>choose.</exercise>
<exercise>7 These are people who look after students at</exercise>
<exercise>a boarding school.</exercise>
<exercise>8 These are exams that all students have to take at the age of 15/16.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ With a partner write school words on cards and turn them upside down. Take a card and use relative clauses to give definitions. Example: Schoolfeesarethemoneythatyour parentshavetopayforyourschool. ∙ Make a crossword puzzle. Use relative clauses for the definitions.</exercise>
<exercise>Support ∙ Look at your word web from C3 for more ∙ Check LiF 10a on page 161 for help.</exercise>
<exercise>C7 Grammar card: contact clauses 1 Now look at this exercise from Gillian’s email: And the school uniform we have to wear looks OK. This relative clause doesn’t have a relative pronoun</exercise>
<exercise>( who, which or that ).</exercise>
<exercise>It is called a contact clause .</exercise>
<exercise>2 Check LiF 10b on page 161 to find out when you can leave out the relative pronoun.</exercise>
<exercise>Write a grammar card for contact clauses.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Look at the exercises from C6a) and your definitions from C6b). Rewrite the definitions using contact clauses where possible. Add three examples to your grammar card. Example: Thisisasubjectstudentshavetotake.</exercise>
<exercise>C8 Target task v " Project Portfolio P8-P10 Caroline and George read Gillian’s email.</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at pp.45-47.</exercise>
<exercise>Choose one of the twins and write an answer to Gillian’s email.</exercise>
<exercise>Use relative clauses and contact clauses when necessary.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Note down what Gillian likes about her new school ∙ Decide which points you want to deal with.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Take Gillian’s hopes and worries seriously, ∙ Think of suggestions that can help Gillian in her situation. Use the phrases in the box for help. Writing, pp.144/145 LiF 11: Word order, p.162</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Check the spelling and the grammar and make suggestions to improve the text where necessary. Writing, pp.144/145 WB C3, p.32</exercise>
<gap>You say that … You are worried about … You seem sad/glad that … Why don’t you … You could try to … I’m sure you will soon … Show everyone that …/how … It’s not the end of the world if … Don’t worry about … You needn’t worry … I see why …</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 41</footnote>
<exercise>b) v Choose:</exercise>
<exercise>or</exercise>
<exercise>school words.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Plan your email.</exercise>
<exercise>and what she is worried about.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Write your email.</exercise>
<exercise>refer back to them and try to comfort her.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Peer editing:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Exchange your email with a partner.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='46'>
<chapter>2/C</chapter>
<exercise>C9 Jigsaw: Caroline wants to know more about Gillian’s school. She has found three articles on the Internet.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Use the jigsaw method to work on the three articles on page 43. Try to answer the questions Who?, What?, When?, Where?, How? and Why?</exercise>
<exercise>2 Discuss what you think about the different activities as part of school life. Formulate your views in a short statement.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Exchange your ideas in class. Jigsaw, p.149</exercise>
<exercise>Reading, p.142</exercise>
<exercise>Speaking 3, p.141</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank School, p.175</exercise>
<exercise>P11, P14 WB C4- C6 , pp.33-35</exercise>
<exercise>C10 L 1/15 a) Listen to Mark, a pupil from St David’s. Find out how he feels about outdoor activities. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and make notes:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What makes them difficult?</exercise>
<exercise>c) Compare your notes with your partner.</exercise>
<exercise>C11 Target task v Need help? Look at pp.47/48.</exercise>
<exercise>Discuss different aspects of school life at St David’s College.</exercise>
<exercise>What do you think about St David’s?</exercise>
<exercise>1 Put each of the aspects from the grid</exercise>
<exercise>for against notsure</exercise>
<exercise>to the vote in class.</exercise>
<exercise>Count the votes for/against/not sure and note down the results.</exercise>
<gap>schooluniform … schoolfees … smallclasses …</gap>
<gap>boarding …</gap>
<gap>Who is for …?</gap>
<gap>Who is not sure about …?</gap>
<gap>exoticschooltrips … fundraising/communitywork …</gap>
<gap>Who is against …?</gap>
<exercise>∙ Work in groups of four. Each group deals with one of the aspects from the grid. Make sure that there is at least one</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Then note down your ideas in your part of the placemat. Turn the placemat so that the other pupils in your group can</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Finally discuss your ideas and write down your results in the centre of the placemat. Placemat, p.150</exercise>
<exercise>3 Present your results in class and discuss them. Argue for your position and try to convince the others. Speaking, p.139</exercise>
<exercise>4 After your discussion, have a vote again and compare these results with the ones from your first vote.</exercise>
<exercise>42 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What different outdoor</exercise>
<exercise>activities is he talking about?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ How do they help Mark?</exercise>
<exercise>2 Placemat:</exercise>
<exercise>group dealing with each aspect.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write down your topic as a heading in the middle.</exercise>
<exercise>read your ideas and comment on them.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='47'>
<chapter>2/C</chapter>
<sentence>A very big ‘Hello’ from all at St David’s College</sentence>
<sentence>This is the first fundraising event for the St David’s College Sprinters (SDCS).</sentence>
<sentence>Can you help us raise £1000+?</sentence>
<sentence>We are really motivated to do a sponsored run for Hope House Hospice Ty GOBAITH in Conwy.</sentence>
<sentence>We are delighted to have so many amazing children, teachers and parents who want to raise awareness for a truly meaningful project.</sentence>
<sentence>Our runners are getting into their training programmes as they concentrate on running 10 miles over the challenging roads of Llandudno.</sentence>
<sentence>In true St Davidean style we will do our best!</sentence>
<sentence>With your support of our fundraising event YOU will help Hope House Hospice.</sentence>
<sentence>Thank you so, so very much from all of us.</sentence>
    <sentence>St David’s College has been the starting point of a link between Llandudno and Kampala.</sentence>
<sentence>The aim of this link is to bring young people together and give young people from the UK a chance to help some of the poorest communities in Africa.</sentence>
<sentence>Children from St David’s College have had a long history of working with communities in Uganda.</sentence>
<sentence>On their last trip the main task was to begin the building phase of a new school.</sentence>
<sentence>At the end of this part of the programme the local team was making 400 bricks per day!</sentence>
<sentence>Our young people also visit families within this community and work in the school.</sentence>
<sentence>The school has already begun to build two new classrooms since the visit last October …</sentence>
<sentence>There is no day without a new experience and very emotional moments.</sentence>
<sentence>It may be that we make a small difference to a number of lives and several very poor communities, but what is certain is that we will never be quite the same again.</sentence>
<sentence>This year’s husky expedition team have just come back from northern Sweden.</sentence>
<sentence>They have successfully completed a fantastic journey through the cold wilderness.</sentence>
<sentence>We had a warm trip this year with typical daytime temperatures of ‘only’ minus 6ºC with the coldest nighttime temperature of ‘only’ minus 22ºC for our last night in bivvy bags.</sentence>
<sentence>It is a serious challenge for the boys to spend the nights outside.</sentence>
<sentence>Each boy has his ‘bed’ in the snow with just his bivvy bag to keep him warm.</sentence>
<sentence>The pupils have to learn to look after the huskies, which are very important in this expedition.</sentence>
<sentence>It is a team building experience that is so important for young people.</sentence>
<sentence>At the same time this outdoor tour shows the beauty of nature even under extreme conditions: It was an amazing experience to see the Northern Lights, the ‘Aurora Borealis’.</sentence>
<sentence>The journey ‘round the back’ of the mountains was a big challenge this year.</sentence>
<sentence>It took us 4 ½ hours, and we needed 100% concentration to keep the sleds going.</sentence>
<sentence>A big well done and a big thank you to this year’s team for making the experience such a fantastic one!</sentence>
    <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 43</footnote>
</page>
<page id='60'>
<chapter>3/A</chapter>
<exercise>Doctor Who</exercise>
<exercise>A1</exercise>
<exercise>Work with a partner.</exercise>
<exercise>Imagine you were able to travel through time and space.</exercise>
<exercise>Answer the following questions and</exercise>
<gap>Support I’d like to … because … It might be interesting to … It would be fantastic/great to …</gap>
<exercise>give reasons for your answers.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What would you like to see?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Who would you like to meet?</exercise>
<gap>The place I would like to see is … The person I would like to meet is … If I had the chance to travel into the</gap>
<gap>LiF 7: Conditional clauses, type 2, p.159 P9 past/future, I would …</gap>
<exercise>A2 L 1/18 George and Rajiv meet after school. a) Listen to them and find out about their project ‘Famous Brits – truth and legend’. What is it about? What are their ideas? Collect the information in a grid. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>George’sideas Rajiv’sideas</exercise>
<gap>… b) Talk about George’s and Rajiv’s ideas. Say which ideas you like or don’t like and explain why.</gap>
<exercise>A3 a) Read about Doctor Who , a famous BBC series. Find the pictures that go with texts 1-6.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ write down any questions that you have about the series.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Collect words from texts 1-6 to talk about science fiction (e.g. spaceship ) and conflicts (e.g. fight ). P1 WB A1, A2, p.43</exercise>
<exercise>A4 L 1/19 a) Listen to Rajiv and George and note down more information about the series.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Compare your notes with a partner’s and correct or complete your notes. P12</exercise>
<exercise>c) Explain why Rajiv says, “Maybe we could really use the Doctor Who idea for our project”.</exercise>
<sentence>This is the sonic screwdriver , a tool which helps the Doctor to open any lock.</sentence>
<sentence>He can also use it to get into any computer without a password.</sentence>
<sentence>This is the time vortex .</sentence>
<sentence>It looks like a tunnel through which the Tardis and other time machines can travel.</sentence>
<exercise>A</exercise>
<exercise>E</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Where would you go?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What would you bring back?</exercise>
<exercise>sc sc re</exercise>
<exercise>ma ch in es es c an</exercise>
<exercise>tr av</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the texts again and</exercise>
<exercise>∙ take notes on the series Doctor Who,</exercise>
</page>
<page id='61'>
<chapter>3/A</chapter>
<exercise>A5 v Extra Visit the Doctor Who website from the BBC to find out more</exercise>
<exercise>A6 Target task v Portfolio P2 Make and present a collage about your time travel ideas from A1.</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at p.68.</exercise>
<exercise>about the series and the characters.</exercise>
<exercise>Try to find answers to your questions from A3b).</exercise>
<exercise>Report back to the class.</exercise>
<exercise>Searching the Internet, p.143</exercise>
<exercise>WB A3, pp.44/45</exercise>
<exercise>1 Think of objects/creatures/people/places and decide</exercise>
<exercise>on names for them.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Find or draw pictures and prepare a collage.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Note down words and phrases to describe your objects/ creatures/people/places. You can use your list from A3c) or read thetexts on the Doctor Who series again.</exercise>
<exercise>You can use texts 1-6 as models.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Gallery walk: Put up your collages for a gallery walk.</exercise>
<exercise>Present your collage and learn about your classmates’ collages.</exercise>
<exercise>Speaking 1, pp.139/140 Gallery walk, p.150</exercise>
<sentence>This is one of the Daleks.</sentence>
<sentence>They are the Doctor’s worst enemies.</sentence>
<sentence>They look like robots and belong to an extraterrestrial race.</sentence>
<sentence>They have no feelings except hate and their aim is to conquer the world.</sentence>
<sentence>B</sentence>
<sentence>This is the Tardis.</sentence>
<sentence>It looks like an old police telephone box, but is a spaceship that allows the Doctor to travel through time and space.</sentence>
<sentence>It does not really fly but dissolves in one place and appears in another.</sentence>
<sentence>This is the Doctor, the hero of a science fiction series on British TV.</sentence>
<sentence>He is an alien from the extraterrestrial civilization of the Time Lords but he looks like a human.</sentence>
<sentence>He helps human civilization on planet Earth to fight against their many enemies.</sentence>
<sentence>With the Tardis he can travel into the past or the future so that he can be part of important historical events.</sentence>
<exercise>6 6</exercise>
<sentence>This is the interior of the Tardis.</sentence>
<sentence>It is the console room where the Doctor can control the Tardis.</sentence>
<sentence>It is only one of the many rooms, as the Tardis may seem small from the outside, but inside it is huge.</sentence>
<exercise>3 Prepare a short presentation of your collage.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write a description of at least 100 words.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='62'>
<chapter>3/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 a) Start an A to Z of history. How many words and phrases to talk about historical events</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Think of people, buildings, objects, ∙ You may note down more</exercise>
<exercise>B2 George’s teacher Mr Blake shows the boys how they can present their project results in more interesting ways. He shows them a cartoon from a book on British history.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Scan the cartoon on page 59 and name the</exercise>
<exercise>than one word for each</exercise>
<exercise>letter.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Compare your lists in class.</exercise>
<exercise>Who has got the most</exercise>
<exercise>words and phrases?</exercise>
<exercise>c) Organize your words and phrases in a word web.</exercise>
<exercise>Graphic organizers, p.147</exercise>
<exercise>B3</exercise>
<exercise>A B C castle,crown D E enemy F G</exercise>
<exercise>four historical characters that are mentioned.</exercise>
<exercise>Where are they from and what can you find</exercise>
<exercise>out about their aims?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the cartoon to find more words for your word web from B1c).</exercise>
<exercise>Add them in a different colour.</exercise>
<exercise>How many more could you find?</exercise>
<exercise>Reading, p.142 P3</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank History, p.176</exercise>
<exercise>Read the statements and say if they are right or wrong.</exercise>
<exercise>Correct the statements that are wrong.</exercise>
<sentence>Before he became king, William had been a prisoner in France.</sentence>
<sentence>After the kidnappers had captured William, Harold came to rescue him.</sentence>
<sentence>Before Harold returned to England, he had promised to support William.</sentence>
<sentence>After King Edward had died, William wanted to be king of England.</sentence>
<sentence>Harold had fought against the Norwegian king before he went south to fight against William’s army.</sentence>
<sentence>After William had become King of Norway, he built many castles.</sentence>
<exercise>Number 1 is wrong.</exercise>
<exercise>Before he became king, Harold had been a prisoner in France.</exercise>
<exercise>B4 Grammar detective: past perfect 1 Look at the cartoon again and find exercises with the past perfect.</exercise>
<exercise>Example: After King Edward had died , Harold became the new king.</exercise>
<exercise>2 In some of the exercises two different tenses are used.</exercise>
<exercise>The new tense is called</exercise>
<exercise>past perfect .</exercise>
<exercise>When do you use the simple past?</exercise>
<exercise>When do you use the past perfect ?</exercise>
<exercise>3 Find out how the past perfect is formed.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Look at LiF 13 on page 163 and write a grammar card for the past perfect .</exercise>
<exercise>P4</exercise>
<exercise>B5 Read the information about two famous British people. Write at least three statements about each person using the past perfect. LiF 13: Past perfect, p.163</exercise>
<exercise>WB B1-B3, pp.45/46 Example: BeforeBeckhamjoinedReal Madridin2003,hehadplayedfor ManchesterUnitedfrom1992to2003.</exercise>
<exercise>David Beckham (* 1975) 1992-2003 plays for 1999 wins Champions</exercise>
<exercise>2000 becomes captain of 2011 wins Major League Soccer cup 2012 carries the Olympic torch</exercise>
<exercise>Joanne K. Rowling (* 1965) 1987 works as a secretary in London 1993-1996 writes the first Harry</exercise>
<exercise>first Harry Potter 1997-2007 writes seven September 2012 writes a</exercise>
<exercise>58 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>can you find in two minutes?</exercise>
<gap>activities, …</gap>
<exercise>Manchester United</exercise>
<exercise>League with</exercise>
<exercise>Manchester United</exercise>
<exercise>the national team</exercise>
<exercise>2003 joins Real Madrid</exercise>
<exercise>with Los Angeles Galaxy</exercise>
<exercise>1983-1987 studies at university</exercise>
<exercise>1992 teaches English in Portugal</exercise>
<exercise>1993 moves back to Edinburgh</exercise>
<exercise>June 1993 has a daughter</exercise>
<exercise>Potter book in a café</exercise>
<exercise>June 1997 publishes the</exercise>
<exercise>book</exercise>
<exercise>Harry Potter books</exercise>
<exercise>new book for adults</exercise>
</page>
<page id='63'>
<chapter>3/B</chapter>
<sentence>The Norman Conquest – How it might have happened</sentence>
<sentence>In 1064, kidnappers in France captured Harold Godwinson, King Edward’s brother-in-law.</sentence>
<sentence>You’ve saved my life!</sentence>
<sentence>I promise to help you become the next king of England.</sentence>
<sentence>Great!</sentence>
<sentence>We want money or you’re a dead man.</sentence>
<sentence>Wait! I’m sure someone will help me.</sentence>
<sentence>As soon as William of Normandy had heard the news, he went to rescue Harold. But Harold had to make a promise …</sentence>
<sentence>When I rescued Harold, he promised to help me become king.</sentence>
<sentence>I really am.</sentence>
<sentence>And I’m going to fight for the crown of England.</sentence>
<sentence>You seem very angry.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s no problem to cross the Channel.</sentence>
<sentence>We can take 5,000 men and even our horses.</sentence>
<sentence>And food – and wine!</sentence>
<sentence>January 1066: After King Edward of England had died, Harold became the new king.</sentence>
<sentence>In Normandy, William was not very pleased …</sentence>
<sentence>William planned to go to England with many ships and a huge army to fight against Harold.</sentence>
<sentence>My feet are aching!</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t really feel fit to fight.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s pretend we have given up.</sentence>
<sentence>Why?</sentence>
<sentence>Meanwhile Harold was having problems with another enemy.</sentence>
<sentence>The King of Norway had landed in the north of England.</sentence>
<sentence>So Harold and his army marched north to fight against him and defeated him.</sentence>
<sentence>But the price was high.</sentence>
<sentence>Harold’s army was tired and now they had to fight against William and his army in the south.</sentence>
<sentence>When Harold’s soldiers follow us, we will turn round.</sentence>
<sentence>Our troops can then surround them from all sides and attack them.</sentence>
<sentence>Harold’s men were tough and held their position against the Normans.</sentence>
<sentence>After King Harold’s soldiers had almost won the battle, the Normans played a trick on the Saxons.</sentence>
<sentence>I’ve built some castles to protect my new kingdom.</sentence>
<sentence>Wow!</sentence>
<sentence>William’s plan worked and he won the Battle of Hastings.</sentence>
<sentence>Harold died because an arrow went right through his eye.</sentence>
<sentence>So William became the new king and was called William the Conqueror.</sentence>
<sentence>One of the many castles that William built was the White Tower, later known as the Tower of London.</sentence>
</page>
<page id='64'>
<chapter>3/B</chapter>
<exercise>B6 L 1/20 a) Rajiv has a new idea for their history project. Listen to the boys and find out which famous person in British history they are talking about. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and collect information in a timeline.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Then note down what happened.</exercise>
<exercise>date: 1558</exercise>
<gap>whathappened: …</gap>
<exercise>c) Work with a partner and check your results from b). WB B4, p.47</exercise>
<exercise>B7 a) George has done some research for their project. He has highlighted the most important information and started taking notes. Read the texts on page 61 and find the highlighted passages A to E that go with George’s notes 1 to 5 .</exercise>
<exercise>b) When you research a topic, you often find a lot of material on the Internet or in books. If you want to use it for your own text or presentation, you usually need to simplify the language and rephrase the information. To do this, you can use some strategies. You can … A use simple words (like make easier for simplify ), B combine words from different exercises so that</exercise>
<exercise>you aren’t just copying word for word, C shorten exercises/leave out unnecessary details, D put the information in a new order.</exercise>
<exercise>Look at your results from a).</exercise>
<exercise>Find at least three of the strategies A - D that George has used for his notes.</exercise>
<sentence>Queen Elizabeth I, the Virgin Queen</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth I was a great ruler of England.</sentence>
<sentence>She was born in 1533. Her parents were Henry VIII and Anne Boleyn.</sentence>
<sentence>She had a terrible childhood because Henry VIII had hermother killed.</sentence>
<sentence>Her father was angry because he wanted a boy to followhim on the throne.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth livedwith her stepmother and had many teachers so that she had a very good education.</sentence>
<exercise>c) Try to work out the meanings of these words and phrases from the texts:</exercise>
<listing>monarch · displeased · throne · prisoner · have somebody executed · succeed · surviving</listing>
<exercise>Support ∙ Try to work out the meaning from the context. ∙ Check if a prefix or suffix can help you understand the word.</exercise>
<exercise>Reading, p.142</exercise>
<exercise>d) Look at the other passages that George has highlighted F to L . Rephrase at least four of them using the strategies from b). Reading, p.142 WB B5 - B7, pp.47-49</exercise>
<exercise>60 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ First note down the different dates.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Think of a similar German/French/… word.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='65'>
<chapter>3/B</chapter>
<sentence>Queen Elizabeth I (1533-1603)</sentence>
<sentence>Queen Elizabeth was one of England’s most outstanding rulers.</sentence>
<sentence>She was born on September 7th 1533 in Greenwich Palace near London as the daughter of King Henry VIII and his second wife, Anne Boleyn.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth’s father, King Henry VIII, had his wife Anne Boleyn executed when Elizabeth was only three years old, so her childhood was a very unhappy one.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth had a half sister, Mary, who was Catherine of Aragon’s only surviving child.</sentence>
<sentence>After her mother died, lots of different people raised Elizabeth.</sentence>
<sentence>She lived with her stepmother Catherine Parr for a time.</sentence>
<sentence>She had an excellent education and was probably better educated than most ladies in society at that time.</sentence>
<sentence>he King was displeased that Elizabeth was a girl because he had hoped for a boy to succeed him as his heir and become king after him.</sentence>
<sentence>At the age of 25, Elizabeth was tall and her health was excellent.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth Tudor was 25 years old when she became Queen of England in 1558, after the death of her half sister Mary.</sentence>
<sentence>The period when Elizabeth was queen is called the Elizabethan Age.</sentence>
<sentence>She loved sports like riding.</sentence>
    <sentence>Elizabeth’s cousin, Mary, Queen of Scots, was next in line to the throne.</sentence>
<sentence>But Queen Elizabeth was worried that Mary was plotting against her.</sentence>
<sentence>When Mary had to leave Scotland and come to England, Elizabeth made her a prisoner and kept her locked away for almost twenty years.</sentence>
<sentence>People sometimes called Queen Elizabeth the Virgin Queen, or Good Queen Bess.</sentence>
<sentence>She was very good at what she did and ruled England very well.</sentence>
<sentence>Queen Elizabeth had a great influence on all parts of life in Elizabethan England, like arts, drama, fashion and politics.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth didn’t know what to do with Mary.</sentence>
<sentence>She also led her army very well and showed that she was as good as any male ruler.</sentence>
<sentence>She decided to have her executed in 1587.</sentence>
<sentence>However, she felt very sorry after Mary’s death because Mary was her cousin.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth I was a remarkable monarch.</sentence>
<sentence>She ruled England for 45 years.</sentence>
<exercise>B8 v Extra a) Prepare five quiz questions using the texts on this page. Write them down on pieces of paper.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Work in groups of four. Put the questions face down and mix them up. Choose a piece of paper and read the question. Try to answer it. LiF 4R: Questions, p.157</exercise>
<exercise>Who was Elizabeth’s father?</exercise>
<gap>…</gap>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 61</footnote>
</page>
<page id='66'>
<chapter>3/B</chapter>
<exercise>B9 Complete the exercises using the definite article the or no article at all. If you need help, check LiF 15a on page 165. LiF 15a: The definite article, p.165</exercise>
<exercise>P10</exercise>
<exercise>1 From 1568 on, ??? life Mary had to lead was that of a prisoner. 2 Although Mary wasn’t a normal prisoner, ??? life wasn’t easy for</exercise>
<exercise>her.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Elizabeth needed ???</exercise>
<exercise>time to decide what to do with Mary.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Elizabeth was very important in all aspects of ???</exercise>
<exercise>life in England.</exercise>
<exercise>5 ???</exercise>
<exercise>music was an important form of entertainment at the time.</exercise>
<exercise>B10 Target task v " Project Portfolio P5, P6, P13 Need help? Look at p.68-70.</exercise>
<exercise>With a partner prepare and give a two-minute presentation about a ‘famous Brit’.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Choose one of the people from the picture gallery or another ‘famous Brit’.</exercise>
<exercise>This can also be a legendary person or a literary character.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Do some research on your person using books or the Internet and collect your material in a file.</exercise>
<exercise>You can find some useful links at http://bit.ly/1lm95QX.</exercise>
<exercise>Keep your file for later.</exercise>
<exercise>You will need it for C12.</exercise>
<exercise>Searching the Internet, p.143</exercise>
<exercise>Robin Hood William Shakespeare</exercise>
<exercise>Henry VIII Florence Nightingale Queen Victoria</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Read the texts again and note down information about your ‘famous Brit’. Make sure that you include all the important facts. You can include some surprising information as well to make your presentation more interesting.</exercise>
<exercise>Use the strategies from B7b).</exercise>
<exercise>Your presentation should be easy to follow.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Prepare cue cards for your presentation. Look at P6 if you need help with your cue cards. ∙ Practise your presentation.</exercise>
<exercise>Speaking 1, pp.139/140 Wordbank History, p.176 4 Get together with two other pairs and take turns to give your presentations.</exercise>
<exercise>Give feedback on your classmates’ presentations.</exercise>
<exercise>Speaking 1, pp.139/140 Speaking 2, p.140</exercise>
<exercise>62 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>King Arthur</exercise>
<exercise>3 Use your file to prepare a presentation of two minutes:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Rewrite your notes to make them as simple and clear as possible.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Be prepared to explain difficult words or phrases to your classmates.</exercise>
<exercise>Look up definitions and the pronunciation if necessary.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the past perfect when necessary.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='67'>
<chapter>3/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 S8, L 1/21 For their project week the boys and their teachers decide to present their results to parents in the form of a play.</exercise>
<exercise>a) Look at these photographs that were taken while the boys were trying on costumes.</exercise>
<exercise>Guess which famous Brits they represent.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen to the statements and write down the names of all the characters.</exercise>
<exercise>Match them to the photographs.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Listen again and note down what each boy thinks is good and bad about his role.</exercise>
<exercise>Use a grid like this:</exercise>
<exercise>Listening, p.138 WB C1, p.50 d) Write down what other information you get about these famous people.</exercise>
<exercise>Example: 1.thelookofQueen Elizabeth’shair,...</exercise>
<exercise>character goodaboutrole badaboutrole 1 QueenElizabethI -makespeoplelaugh -awoman</exercise>
<gap>-uncomfortabledress 2 SherlockHolmes …</gap>
<exercise>C2 a) These are the summaries of the scenes in the programme that the boys wrote for their performance. Read one summary each to yourselves.</exercise>
<exercise>b) In your group talk about any problems you have with your text.</exercise>
<exercise>c) In each of the scenes the reader is told what is done to the main characters. Tell the others what is done to your character. Example: FirstArthuris declaredking.Thenheis…</exercise>
<exercise>d) Which scene will be the most exciting to watch? Which one will be the most difficult to perform? Give reasons. Example: TheBattleof Hastingsscenemightbethe mostexcitingscenetowatch because… WB C2, p.50</exercise>
<sentence>The (True) Story of Some Very Famous People in British History</sentence>
<sentence>Written and performed by Year 8 – William Ellis School for Boys</sentence>
<sentence>Scene 1: The Life of King Arthur</sentence>
<sentence>The knights of England have come together for a tournament.</sentence>
<sentence>Merlin challenges them to pull the famous sword Excalibur out of the stone.</sentence>
<sentence>Only Arthur can do this so he is declared king.</sentence>
<sentence>Some time later he is married to Guinevere and it looks as if they will be happy.</sentence>
<sentence>But there are some surprises.</sentence>
<sentence>First Arthur is almost killed by the Black Knight.</sentence>
<sentence>Later he is betrayed by Guinevere and finally he is killed by his ‘friend’ Sir Lancelot.</sentence>
<sentence>A scene full of action.</sentence>
<sentence>Scene 2: The Battle of Hastings</sentence>
<sentence>It’s the year 1066.</sentence>
<sentence>King Edward dies and Harold of Wessex is crowned king.</sentence>
<sentence>But his position is not safe.</sentence>
<sentence>He is challenged by the King of Norway and marches his army to the north of England.</sentence>
<sentence>The Norwegian army is defeated at Stamford Bridge but another enemy is waiting in the south.</sentence>
<sentence>William of Normandy wants the English throne.</sentence>
<sentence>Hundreds of tired British soldiers are murdered and Harold is killed by an arrow in his eye.</sentence>
<sentence>Or is he?</sentence>
<sentence>This scene about the most famous battle in British history is full of surprises.</sentence>
<sentence>Scene 3: Shakespeare’s Great Tragedy</sentence>
<sentence>William Shakespeare is having problems again.</sentence>
<sentence>He cannot pay his bills.</sentence>
<sentence>He is offered a lot of money to write a new play for the Globe Theatre.</sentence>
<sentence>Shakespeare’s plays are often performed there.</sentence>
<sentence>But this time William is asked to write a comedy and not a tragedy and he only has three days to finish it.</sentence>
<sentence>This scene is full of surprises about England’s greatest writer.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 63</footnote>
</page>
<page id='68'>
<chapter>3/C</chapter>
<exercise>C3 Grammar detective: the passive (1) 1 The passive voice is used when the focus of a statement is on the action rather than on the person who does it. Look at these sentences from the programme on page 63:</exercise>
<gap>Arthur … is declared king. He is killed by his ‘friend’ Sir Lancelot. 2 Find out how to form the passive in the simple present. 3 Find more examples from the programme and start a grammar card. 4 Look at this passive sentence from the programme: Later Arthur is betrayed. How can you add who betrayed Arthur? Check LiF 14a, b and c on page 164 and complete your grammar card.</gap>
<exercise>C4 Look at the notes Rajiv and George have made for their scene about Elizabeth. Write a short description for the programme on page 63. Use the passive in the simple present.</exercise>
<gap>LiF 14: Passive, pp.164/165 Example: Elizabethiscrownedqueenin1558.Peace…</gap>
<exercise>• theycrownElizabethqueenin1558 • shebringspeacetoEngland • MaryStuart(hercousin)threatens</exercise>
<exercise>Elizabeth • RomanCatholicssupportMary • MaryblackmailsElizabeth • ElizabethputsMaryintheTower</exercise>
<exercise>C5 L 1/22 a) Listen to the conversation between George, Rajiv, Keith and Tom about the scene they have written for the play. What is special about the roles of Elizabeth and Mary? Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the conversation and find out what parts the boys play and why.</exercise>
<sentence>George: I think our scene is getting better and better.</sentence>
<sentence>It should be fun to act.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: But we still have a lot to discuss.</sentence>
<sentence>Tom: Definitely!</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t want to play Elizabeth.</sentence>
<sentence>They’re bigger parts and I think I’m the best actor.</sentence>
<sentence>Keith: And the most modest person here!</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: OK. George is Elizabeth.</sentence>
<sentence>Does anyone disagree?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: But the roles have already been chosen.</sentence>
<sentence>Tom: I’m certainly not playing a woman. No way!</sentence>
    <sentence>Keith: I think I’m quite happy with being a guard.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m not very good at learning things by heart.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, two of us will have to play the main parts of Queen Elizabeth and Mary, Queen of Scots.</sentence>
<sentence>What about you, Rajiv?</sentence>
<sentence>Mary, Queen of Scots, must be played by a dark-haired person.</sentence>
<sentence>George: Women were played by men in the sixteenth century, anyway, so I don’t mind playing Elizabeth if Tom doesn’t want to</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, I don’t mind.</sentence>
<sentence>I hope I can wear a nice dress!</sentence>
<sentence>They all laugh.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Elizabeth and Mary can wear wigs.</sentence>
<sentence>George: That’s decided then.</sentence>
<sentence>When is the first rehearsal?</sentence>
<sentence>Wigs were worn by lots of people in those days … And white make-up, of course.</sentence>
<sentence>Women were considered attractive if they were light-skinned.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, we need some time to learn our parts.</sentence>
<sentence>Is everybody happy with the scene?</sentence>
<sentence>Keith: I’m still not sure about this idea of making Elizabeth a man.</sentence>
<sentence>Tom: Make-up. Are you serious?</sentence>
<sentence>That’s another good reason not to be Elizabeth.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: But that’s the reason why she is blackmailed by Mary.</sentence>
<sentence>George: We can swap roles then, Tom.</sentence>
<sentence>You can be one of the guards.</sentence>
<sentence>As I said, I don’t mind playing Elizabeth or Mary.</sentence>
<sentence>We need it for the plot.</sentence>
<sentence>Tom: Well, I suppose you’re right.</sentence>
<exercise>64 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='69'>
<chapter>3/C</chapter>
<exercise>C6 a) Read C5 again and collect words and phrases the boys use to express how they feel about playing their roles. Example: Itshouldbefunto… · I’mcertainlynotplayinga woman.Noway! · Iseverybodyhappywith…?</exercise>
<exercise>b) How would you feel about playing a man/woman? Talk to your partner.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Choose a role in a play or a film for each other. Tell your partner why you would or wouldn’t like playing this part. WB C3, p.51</exercise>
<exercise>C7 v Choose ∙ Write Tom’s email to his friend about the play. What is your view of George, Rajiv and Keith and the way the roles were decided on? Writing, pp.144/145 WB C4, p.52</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write the conversation between Rajiv and his sister Sheree about the play. What is his view of how the roles were decided on? Writing, pp.144/145 WB C4, p.52</exercise>
<exercise>C8 Grammar detective: the passive (2) Find passive forms in the dialogue from C5, for example: Women were played by men in the sixteenth century. Find out how to form the passive in tenses other than the simple present. Add your examples to your grammar card. LiF 14: Passive, pp.164/165 P7 WB C5, p.52</exercise>
<exercise>C9 Look at the pictures and write captions. Use the passive voice in different tenses.</exercise>
<exercise>LiF 14: Passive, pp.164/165 WB C6, p.53 Example: 1.Theorangeteamhasjustbeenbeaten3:0.</exercise>
<exercise>1 2 3</exercise>
<exercise>the orange team / just beat 3:0 America / discover in 1492 Halley’s Comet / can see again in 2061</exercise>
<exercise>4 5 6</exercise>
<exercise>the Tower of London / build in 1066</exercise>
<exercise>whale-hunting / must stop</exercise>
<exercise>dinosaurs / can find in the Natural History Museum</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 65</footnote>
<exercise>or:</exercise>
</page>
<page id='70'>
<chapter>3/C</chapter>
<exercise>C10 a) Why did Queen Elizabeth I really lock Mary, Queen of Scots, away? Rajiv, George, Keith and Tom have written their own version of events. Read the scene on page 67 and note down what you find funny or surprising.</exercise>
<exercise>C11 S9, L1/23</exercise>
<exercise>b) Go through the scene again and think about how the main characters feel as the scene goes on. Write down stage directions like those in lines 6 and 12.</exercise>
<exercise>angry ∙ frightened ∙ terrified ∙ shocked ∙ excited ∙ surprised ∙ determined ∙ to threaten ∙ to command ∙ to beg</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank People, p.174 LiF 16: Countable and uncountable nouns, p.166 P11 Example: Line15:(Elizabethis)shockedwhensherecognizesMary.</exercise>
<exercise>Lines43-45:(Mary)threatenstotelleveryoneElizabeth’ssecret.</exercise>
<exercise>Work in groups of four and do a dramatic reading of the scene.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Listen to the CD and concentrate on your role. Pay special attention to pace, pronunciation and intonation.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Practise reading out loud. Use a facial expression that fits the situation.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Read the scene and ask your classmates to give you some feedback. P8</exercise>
<gap>Support You spoke clearly and not too fast. You spoke with feeling. Try to speak more slowly next time. Try to speak with more feeling. Your facial expression was great for line … Why don’t you try looking more shocked when you say the text in line …?</gap>
<exercise>C12 Target task v " Project Portfolio</exercise>
<exercise>Work in groups of four.</exercise>
<exercise>Write a short scene about a famous person.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the information you collected in your</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at pp.70/71.</exercise>
<exercise>v Extra:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Think about costumes, props and scenery.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Plan the details: Who are the characters? ∙ Divide the plot up into two parts. ∙ In pairs write the dialogue for one part of the play ∙ Use the passive when the focus of a statement is on the action rather than on the person who did it. Writing, pp.144/145 Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank History, p.176 LiF 14: Passive, pp.164/165 3 Edit your scene: Read, edit and talk about each part in your group.</exercise>
<exercise>Make sure the two parts fit together.</exercise>
<exercise>Writing, pp.144/145</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the plot: (not) convincing, exciting, surprising, full of suspense, boring, …</exercise>
<gap>convincing, funny, …</gap>
<exercise>Use the language support from C11.</exercise>
<exercise>Speaking 2, p.140</exercise>
<exercise>66 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>1 Plan your scene:</exercise>
<exercise>Put your scene on stage.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Practise reading your scene and present</exercise>
<exercise>files in B10 and decide on a person.</exercise>
<exercise>What is the plot?</exercise>
<exercise>2 Write your scene:</exercise>
<exercise>and add the stage directions.</exercise>
<exercise>it to the class.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Give feedback on:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the characters: (not) realistic,</exercise>
<exercise>∙ the presentation:</exercise>
</page>
<page id='71'>
<chapter>3/C</chapter>
<sentence>Scene 4: The Story of Queen Elizabeth I – A different version</sentence>
<sentence>by Rajiv Khan, George Lambraki, Keith Harrison and Tom Webber</sentence>
<sentence>In the bedroom of Queen Elizabeth I.</sentence>
<sentence>There is a person putting on a wig.</sentence>
<sentence>Suddenly two guards arrive.</sentence>
<sentence>Guard 1: There is someone who wishes to see you, Your Majesty.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: (angry because she has been disturbed) Who is it?</sentence>
<sentence>Guard 2: She won’t say her name, Your Majesty.</sentence>
<sentence>But she says it’s important.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: Send her in.</sentence>
<sentence>A cloaked figure comes in.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: Please give me some time to think about it.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: (frightened) Who are you?</sentence>
<sentence>It’s not easy.</sentence>
<sentence>Mary: Don’t you recognize me, cousin?</sentence>
<sentence>Mary: OK, I’ll give you one night!</sentence>
<sentence>But if you don’t leave the country, the world will be told your secret!</sentence>
<sentence>She shows her face.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: Mary, Mary Stuart!</sentence>
<sentence>What are you doing here?</sentence>
<sentence>You should be in Scotland!</sentence>
<sentence>Mary: Yes, cousin Elizabeth. Or should I call you Edward?</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: What do you mean?</sentence>
<sentence>Mary: I know your secret.</sentence>
<sentence>The real Queen Elizabeth died when she was ten.</sentence>
<sentence>They couldn’t find a girl to replace her so a young boy was chosen – Edward, the child of a servant.</sentence>
<sentence>You are not the true Queen of England.</sentence>
<sentence>You are a man.</sentence>
<sentence>I know your secret at last.</sentence>
<sentence>Mary goes to Queen Elizabeth and pulls the wig away.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: Who has betrayed me?</sentence>
<sentence>Mary: I am not going to tell you who gave me this piece of information.</sentence>
<sentence>You must give up your throne and let me become queen.</sentence>
<sentence>England must be ruled by a Catholic monarch and the true religion must be brought back to this country.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: You scoundrel!</sentence>
<sentence>Mary: I think another scoundrel will be discovered when I tell everyone your secret.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: Please! Don’t tell my secret!</sentence>
<sentence>Mary: Then let me become queen!</sentence>
<sentence>See you tomorrow, Edward!</sentence>
<sentence>Mary leaves the bedroom.</sentence>
<sentence>Queen Elizabeth calls the guards.</sentence>
<sentence>Two guards come in.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: Follow the person who was just in my room.</sentence>
<sentence>Guards 1 and 2: Yes, Your Majesty.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: And take her to the Tower.</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t believe anything she tells you.</sentence>
<sentence>She’s completely mad.</sentence>
<sentence>The two guards run out.</sentence>
<sentence>After a few minutes the two guards come back.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: Has she been locked in the Tower?</sentence>
<sentence>Guard 1: Yes, Your Majesty.</sentence>
<sentence>You were right, she is completely mad.</sentence>
<sentence>She said you were a man.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: Yes, well. That’s what I thought.</sentence>
<sentence>She’s dangerous. She must never be let free again.</sentence>
<sentence>Tell the Lord Chamberlain to come and see me.</sentence>
<sentence>It is time that Mary, ‘Queen of Scots’ was silenced.</sentence>
<sentence>Guard 2: I’ll get him immediately, Your Majesty.</sentence>
<sentence>The guards leave and Elizabeth is alone again.</sentence>
<sentence>Elizabeth: The Queen of England will never be blackmailed. Adieu, cousin Mary.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 67</footnote>
</page>
<page id='82'>
<chapter>4/A</chapter>
<exercise>Get connected</exercise>
<exercise>A1 a) Start a word web with words and phrases you can use to talk about online activities and computers. Wordbank Computers, p.176 WB A1, p.61</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What kinds of online activities are popular?</exercise>
<exercise>on them?</exercise>
<exercise>Say which of your results you find the most interesting.</exercise>
<exercise>A2 a) Skim Caroline’s PalPlace page (on p. 79). Say in your own words what you can find out about the cinema, the rugby match and the party. Reading, p.142</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read Caroline’s PalPlace profile and complete the following statements. 1 When Caroline arrives in Aberystwyth,</exercise>
<gap>she … 2 First Gillian and Caroline want to watch</gap>
<gap>DVDs and eat pizza, but then … 3 Caroline thinks Gillian has already become</gap>
<gap>a bit of a Welsh girl because … 4 On the last evening of her stay Caroline …</gap>
<exercise>A4 L 1/25</exercise>
<exercise>A3 a) Work with a partner. Choose the comments of either the girls (Caroline, Emma, Gillian) or the boys (George, Rajiv, Charlie, Gethin). Note down possible reasons for these comments. Examples: George:“noneedforsuntanlotion ”</exercise>
<exercise>makesfunofCaroline Caroline:“coolplace ” ,“bestchocolatecake ever ” isenthusiasticabouthertrip</exercise>
<exercise>b) Work together with a pair who concentrated on the other group of characters. Present your findings. Then discuss what they might tell you about the characters’ feelings towards each other. Speaking 1, pp.139/140 WB A2-A4, pp.61-63</exercise>
<exercise>… seems to feel … ∙ … is close to … ∙ … knows how to express his/her feelings about … …’s entry sounds to me as if he/she …</exercise>
<exercise>c) v Extra Use your results from b) to create a diagram that shows the relationship between the friends and how they act towards each other on PalPlace .</exercise>
<exercise>b r o t h e r a n d s i s t e r Caroline George g o o d f r i e n d s</exercise>
<exercise>If Caroline asked</exercise>
<exercise>a) Listen to Caroline and Gillian. Speculate on what Caroline’s PalPlace relationship status might</exercise>
<exercise>b) Take notes on Caroline’s problem and Gillian’s suggestions.</exercise>
<gap>me for advice, I’d tell her to …</gap>
<exercise>look like later that day.</exercise>
<exercise>Explain your choice.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Say what advice you would give to Caroline.</exercise>
<gap>If I were Caroline, I’d …</gap>
<exercise>It’s complicated ∙ In a relationship ∙ Single LiF 7: Conditional clauses, type 2, p.159 P8 WB A5, p.63</exercise>
<exercise>A5 Target task v Portfolio P1 Need help? Look at p.88.</exercise>
<exercise>Write comments on Caroline’s PalPlace page for the posts</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use what you know about the characters and your results from A3 and A4.</exercise>
<exercise>78 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>b) Do a survey in class:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ How much time do people spend</exercise>
<exercise>m a k e s f u n o f C a r o l i n e</exercise>
<exercise>Gillian</exercise>
<exercise>Charlie</exercise>
<exercise>Caroline I’d</exercise>
<exercise>from Jan 24, 7:06 pm, Jan 25, 11:30 pm and 11:33 pm.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write comments from Gillian, Emma, George, Charlie and Rajiv.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='83'>
<chapter>4/A</chapter>
<sentence>PalPlace</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline Lambraki</sentence>
<sentence>Lives in Camden, London, UK</sentence>
<sentence>Jan 24 – 9:11 pm</sentence>
<sentence>From Manchester, UK Born on August 23</sentence>
<sentence>++Add Friend Message</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian , Emma and Gethin like this.</sentence>
<sentence>Jan 25 – 11:33 pm Last post from Wales.</sentence>
<sentence>So sad I have 2 leave 2moro!</sentence>
<sentence>Just back from Aberystwyth.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian’s stepdad took us 2 the cinema there.</sentence>
<sentence>The film was</sentence>
<sentence>U seem 2 be enjoying the party, Caroline.</sentence>
<sentence>Good for U!</sentence>
<sentence>;-) George Don’t embarrass the family.</sentence>
<sentence>No Welsh boys 4 U, sis.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline Oh, just shut up and don’t “sis“ me.</sentence>
<sentence>George Is that how U talk 2 your own brother?</sentence>
<sentence>;-)</sentence>
<sentence>gr8!</sentence>
<sentence>Had so much fun – we cudn’t stop laughing on the way back.</sentence>
<sentence>Jan 25 – 11:30 pm</sentence>
<sentence>Gethin Nice pic!</sentence>
<sentence>We look gr8.</sentence>
<sentence>Could U send it 2 me, plz?</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline Sure.</sentence>
<sentence>The photo is OTW.</sentence>
<sentence>Jan 24 – 7:06 pm</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t get jealous, boys!</sentence>
<sentence>No more boring pizza and TV night 4 us.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s party time!</sentence>
<sentence>Jan 24 – 10:13 am What a cute cottage Gillian’s “stepdad“ has!</sentence>
<sentence>Looks old and quirky from the outside but is a cool mix of old and new inside.</sentence>
<sentence>We’ve just walked along the only (?!) street here.</sentence>
<sentence>Yeah, the countryside is beautiful but this village is sooo boring.</sentence>
<sentence>Jan 25 – 5:24 pm We’ve just been 2 a rugby match.</sentence>
<sentence>Thnx, Gill, 4 telling me all of the rules – UR almost a real Welsh girl now!</sentence>
<sentence>No wonder Gill is happy 2 be at boarding school.</sentence>
<sentence>It was quite exciting 2 watch and the local team won (so congrats, Gethin)!</sentence>
<sentence>It’s getting more and more exciting here in Wales.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian , Emma and Gethin like this.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv and Gillian like this.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian I’m so glad Caroline’s here – we’re really out in the sticks.</sentence>
<sentence>And rain doesn’t help – just like right now.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma So what are your plans 4 2night thn?</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian Pizza and DVDs!</sentence>
<sentence>George Caroline in London: Why wud anyone want 2 watch a football match?</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline likes this.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie Sounds like a girls’ night.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline in Wales: Rugby, rugby, rugby, exciting, exciting, exciting.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv If U love it so much, why don’t U just stay there thn, Caroline?</sentence>
<sentence>George I bet they’re just chatting all the time anyway.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv Pizza – U can have that any day.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie No way, thn George will make fun of US!</sentence>
<sentence>That’s what Caroline is there 4.</sentence>
<sentence>Jan 23 – 8:29 pm OMG, I thought I’d never arrive in Aberystwyth, but it’s actually quite a cool place – @ least if U like the sea, like me.</sentence>
<sentence>George likes this.</sentence>
<sentence>Gillian I had almost forgotten how “funny“ U R.</sentence>
<sentence>But Gill and I have already had the best chocolate cake ever!</sentence>
<sentence>CUL8R!</sentence>
<sentence>Emma U 2 MUST call me and tell me all about</sentence>
<sentence>what’s going on.</sentence>
<sentence>I seem 2 miss all the fun.</sentence>
<sentence>:-(</sentence>
<sentence>Jan 24 – 10:22 pm Caroline and Gethin Phillips are now friends.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv and Emma like this.</sentence>
<sentence>George I’m not sure if U knew, sis: Wales isn’t Greece.</sentence>
<sentence>No need 4 suntan lotion there …</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie Why did it take so long? Wrong train? Or did some sheep block the tracks?</sentence>
<sentence>LOL Rajiv Good 2 hear that U R having a gr8 time!</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 79</footnote>
</page>
<page id='84'>
<chapter>4/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 L1/26 a) Rajiv has changed his profile picture on his PalPlace account. Look at the old and the new photos and speculate on why he changed it.</exercise>
<exercise>Rajiv Khan updated his profile picture:</exercise>
<listing>Possibly Rajiv … · Maybe he … · I think he might have done it because … It could be because …</listing>
<exercise>b) Listen to his conversation with George and find out why he changed the picture. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>Jan 26 Jan 3</exercise>
<exercise>c) Listen again and write down at least four of George’s questions. Try to find answers to all those questions in class even if Rajiv does not answer them. P2 WB B1, p.64</exercise>
<exercise>B2 L1/27</exercise>
<exercise>a) George talks to Caroline to find out more about what is going on with her. Before you listen to them, discuss if he should tell Caroline about how Rajiv feels. Speaking 3, p.141</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen to their conversation and find out what George does. Compare it to the results of your discussion in a). Listening, p.138</exercise>
<sentence>George: Is everything OK, Caroline?</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: What’s got into you?</sentence>
<sentence>No ‘sis’ or ‘Welshwoman’ today?</sentence>
<sentence>George: Oh, good to know that you already miss my jokes.</sentence>
<sentence>Well, I don’t really know what is going on.</sentence>
<sentence>What really happened in Wales?</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: It was just a normal weekend trip to Wales to visit Gillian.</sentence>
<sentence>George: Well, I don’t know.</sentence>
<sentence>You are the talk of the town with your ‘It’s complicated’ relationship status and the Gethin photo.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: What do I care?</sentence>
<sentence>George: It’s embarrassing – you and your Welsh boy.</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t forget there are people who are not hundreds of miles away and who like you very much.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: I don’t know what you are all so excited about.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Who would that be?</sentence>
<sentence>George: Rajiv, for example.</sentence>
<sentence>He’s really upset because it says ‘It’s complicated’ on your PalPlace page.</sentence>
<sentence>Gethin is just a friend.</sentence>
<sentence>George: A few days ago you didn’t even know him and now he’s your friend?</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: I like him. He’s funny, but that’s it.</sentence>
<sentence>George: I don’t know.</sentence>
<sentence>Is he your boyfriend?</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: That’s none of your business, nor Rajiv’s for that matter.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv? Why does he care about it?</sentence>
<sentence>Like I said, Gethin’s a nice guy, but we haven’t texted each other since Wales.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: That’s none of your business.</sentence>
<sentence>I can be friends with anyone I want.</sentence>
<sentence>George: Are you still in touch online?</sentence>
<sentence>George: But you needn’t do that online in front of the whole world.</sentence>
<sentence>You know that everyone can follow your posts.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Yes, we are still in touch online, but I’m not saying anything else.</sentence>
<sentence>George: OK, OK …</sentence>
<exercise>80 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='85'>
<chapter>4/B</chapter>
<exercise>c) Later that day, Rajiv calls George. Read and find out if the statements 1-6 below are right or wrong. Correct the statements that are wrong.</exercise>
<sentence>Rajiv: Rajiv here, hi, George.</sentence>
<sentence>Have you already spoken to Caroline?</sentence>
<sentence>George: Yes, I have.</sentence>
<sentence>She told me that it had just been a normal weekend trip.</sentence>
<sentence>She said that she didn’t know what we were so excited about.</sentence>
<sentence>George: She sounded convincing, but my sister always sounds like that.</sentence>
<sentence>To be honest, she also said she was still in touch with Gethin online.</sentence>
    <sentence>And she said that Gethin was just a friend.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Just a friend?</sentence>
<sentence>The photo and what she wrote on PalPlace don’t look like that.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: In other words, we don’t really know what’s going on.</sentence>
<sentence>George: That’s what I explained to her as well.</sentence>
<sentence>George: No, but don’t worry.</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t really know why you care so much about my sister.</sentence>
<sentence>But she claimed that they hadn’t texted each other since the weekend in Wales.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Mmmh … do you believe her?</sentence>
<sentence>If you lived with her day in, day out, you would buy her the train ticket to Aberystwyth with your pocket money.</sentence>
<gap>George tells Rajiv … 1 that Caroline said that Gethin was just a friend. 2 that Caroline explained that her PalPlace status</gap>
<exercise>was none of Rajiv’s business.</exercise>
<exercise>3 that Caroline told him that she hadn’t texted Gethin since the trip to Wales.</exercise>
<exercise>4 that Caroline thought that Gethin was funny. 5 that he pointed out to Caroline that Rajiv was</exercise>
<exercise>upset about her PalPlace status.</exercise>
<exercise>6 that Caroline mentioned that she and Gethin were still in touch online.</exercise>
<exercise>d) v Extra: Comment on what George tells Rajiv about his conversation with Caroline and what he keeps secret. Why might he do that? Do you think he was right to do so? Give reasons.</exercise>
<exercise>B3 Grammar detective: reported speech</exercise>
<exercise>1 Look at these statements from B2: “It was just a normal weekend trip.” “I don’t know what you are all so excited about.” Copy the statements and write down how they are reported in Rajiv and George’s dialogue.</exercise>
<exercise>B4 Hi Caroline,</exercise>
<exercise>2 Find out how the tenses are changed when you report what someone said.</exercise>
<exercise>Start a grammar card on reported speech.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Look at LiF 17 (p. 167) to check your grammar card.</exercise>
<exercise>Check what else changes in reported speech in LiF 17b.</exercise>
<exercise>P3, P4 WB B2-B4, pp.64-66</exercise>
<exercise>a) Read Gethin’s email to Caroline. Decide which of Gethin’s statements might have the strongest effect on Caroline. Give reasons for your choice.</exercise>
<sentence>It has become very boring again since you left.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe it is time for me to travel a little bit.</sentence>
<sentence>You know it’s Valentine’s Day soon.</sentence>
<sentence>It would be so nice to meet that day.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe I can stay in your brother’s room.</sentence>
<sentence>Then I can get to know you and Gillian’s other friends.</sentence>
<sentence>I hope you will say yes. Love, Gethin</sentence>
<exercise>b) Caroline is very confused about the email and calls Gillian to tell her about it. Write down what she tells Gillian. Use reported speech. Don’t just use say or tell as reporting verbs. You can also use verbs like hope , explain , write , suggest , insist . LiF 17: Reported speech, pp.167/168</exercise>
<sentence>Hi, Gillian, I miss you so much.</sentence>
<sentence>Gethin sent me an email.</sentence>
<sentence>You’ll never believe what he wrote.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie and Rajiv would never do anything like that.</sentence>
<sentence>I wish I had never met him.</sentence>
<sentence>I don’t really know what I should do now.</sentence>
<exercise>He said that …</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 81</footnote>
</page>
<page id='86'>
<chapter>4/B</chapter>
<exercise>B5 Target task v " Project Do a role play.</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at p.88-90.</exercise>
<exercise>Work with a partner and choose a set of role cards (blue or green) and study them.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Note down what your characters may know about Caroline and Gethin’s relationship –</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Note down how they feel about this. Wordbank People, p.174 2 Silent dialogue: Prepare notes for a dialogue between your characters. Silent dialogue, p.150 3 Practise your dialogue with a partner. 4 Present your dialogue to another pair. Give feedback on how well you used the information from the role cards. Speaking 2, p.140 WB B5, p.66</exercise>
<exercise>∙ tells Charlie what he has heard from Caroline about Gethin and his plans</exercise>
<exercise>∙ doesn’t want to get to know Gethin ∙ explains that he can’t understand why Rajiv likes his sister so much</exercise>
<exercise>∙ thinks it is all just a lot of girls’ talk that is going on on</exercise>
<exercise>∙ thinks it would be fun to see what would happen if Gethin really came for Valentine’s Day</exercise>
<exercise>∙ thinks the whole story with Caroline and Gethin is very exciting</exercise>
<exercise>Gethin (15) is too old for Caroline</exercise>
<exercise>about Rajiv, who is in love with Caroline</exercise>
<exercise>∙ tells Emma about the latest developments with Gethin (what she has heard from Caroline about</exercise>
<exercise>∙ thinks it would be better to keep things as they are</exercise>
<exercise>because she introduced Caroline to Gethin</exercise>
<exercise>B6 v Extra: Viewing: Dangers on the Internet a) In B2b) George says: “But you needn’t do that online in front of the whole world. You know that everyone can follow your posts.” (lines 20-22) Explain what he means by that statement.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Watch the two clips about teenagers and how they use the Internet. Say what the clips are about. Viewing, p.139</exercise>
<exercise>c) Watch the clips again and explain what you like/don’t like about them. Think of both their message and the way they are filmed. WB B6, p.67</exercise>
<gap>The first clip gives you a good idea why … The second clip doesn’t make it clear why … What I like about the storyline in the … clip is … The … clip makes me really think about what I do online because …</gap>
<exercise>82 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>1 Go through pages 78-81 and collect information:</exercise>
<exercise>either directly from their own experience or from others.</exercise>
<exercise>Role card: George</exercise>
<exercise>Role card: Charlie</exercise>
<exercise>for Valentine’s Day</exercise>
<exercise>or share a room with him</exercise>
<exercise>PalPlace</exercise>
<exercise>Role card: Emma</exercise>
<exercise>Role card: Gillian</exercise>
<exercise>∙ is a bit worried that</exercise>
<exercise>∙ tells Gillian what she has heard</exercise>
<exercise>Gethin’s email)</exercise>
<exercise>∙ isn’t sure what Gethin wants from Caroline</exercise>
<exercise>∙ is worried that she is responsible for all the trouble</exercise>
</page>
<page id='87'>
<chapter>4/B</chapter>
<exercise>B7 P5, P6 a) Imagine you found this list on a US website for a discussion in your social studies class. Say in German what this website lists as four positive things about social networks. Mediation, p.148</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Which aspects do/don’t you find important and positive?</exercise>
<exercise>Give reasons for your opinion.</exercise>
<exercise>Speaking 3, p.141 Wordbank Computers, p.176 c) Placemat: Write down ideas for a list of four negative things that people could do on social networking sites.</exercise>
<exercise>Placemat, p.150 P13 d) v Choose: Illustrate your ideas of positive and negative aspects of social networking sites in a a) poster or: b) video clip.</exercise>
<sentence>ON SOCIAL NETWORKING SITES</sentence>
<sentence>What better way to keep your distant relatives up-to-date with your activities?</sentence>
<sentence>From animal rights to green ideas, social networking sites are the place to go for social activists.</sentence>
<sentence>Connect and discuss your interests with other people.</sentence>
<sentence>Stars are born online every day.</sentence>
<sentence>No need to move to California to get that recording contract; with one hit video everyone will come to you!</sentence>
<exercise>B8 Target task v " Project Portfolio Need help? Look at pp.90/91.</exercise>
<exercise>Write and present tips for a website about using your social networking profile responsibly.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Read the tips in boxes 3, 5 and 6. Think of examples</exercise>
<exercise>of what might happen if you don’t follow the advice.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Present your examples in class.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Work with a partner.</exercise>
<exercise>Write tips for boxes 1, 2, 4 and 7.</exercise>
<exercise>Write each tip on a separate sheet of A4 paper.</exercise>
<exercise>Writing, pp.144/145 Wordbank Computers, p.176</exercise>
<exercise>4 Find another pair and read their tips. Choose the best four tips and present them in class. WB B7, p.67</exercise>
<exercise>PROFILE PICTURE:</exercise>
<exercise>PalPlace Home Account Inbox</exercise>
<exercise>PatrickD</exercise>
<sentence>ACCOUNT/SETTINGS: Here you can choose which people can see your profile.</sentence>
<sentence>You can also decide how much and exactly what people can see.</sentence>
<sentence>INFORMATION/ABOUT ME:</sentence>
<sentence>Information Birthday: January 17, 2001</sentence>
<sentence>FRIENDS/CONTACTS:</sentence>
<sentence>Location: Virginia</sentence>
<sentence>Check all of the options carefully.</sentence>
<sentence>You might have some friends that you don’t know in real life.</sentence>
<sentence>You need to ask yourself: Do you really want them to know everything about you?</sentence>
<sentence>Are they who they say they are?</sentence>
<sentence>Why are they your friends?</sentence>
<exercise>Friends</exercise>
<exercise>Photo Album</exercise>
<exercise>Comments</exercise>
<sentence>Beach later!</sentence>
<sentence>Sooooooo jealous :(</sentence>
<sentence>Worst day ever.</sentence>
<sentence>It’ll get better!</sentence>
<sentence>Awwwww, sorry!</sentence>
<sentence>Me too!!!!</sentence>
<sentence>!</sentence>
<sentence>USERNAME: You could use your real name, or a nickname.</sentence>
<sentence>It isn’t bad to use your real name.</sentence>
<sentence>Just be even more careful with your security settings.</sentence>
<sentence>Remember to keep control of who sees what.</sentence>
<exercise>4 PHOTOS/ALBUMS: COMMENTS/WALL: 7</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 83</footnote>
<exercise>4 POSITIVETHINGSYOUCANDO</exercise>
<exercise>1 CREATEFAMILYPHOTOALBUMS</exercise>
<exercise>b) Discuss the list in class.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What would you have added to the list?</exercise>
<exercise>2 SUPPORTACAUSE</exercise>
<exercise>3 JOINAGROUP</exercise>
<exercise>4 SHOWYOURTALENT</exercise>
</page>
<page id='88'>
<chapter>4/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 It is almost Valentine’s Day. How do you, your friends and your family celebrate this day? P12</exercise>
<exercise>C2 v Extra a) Valentine’s cards are very popular in Britain. The cards can be funny or romantic. Read the rhymes out loud first. Then finish the last rhyme. Which is your favourite?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use one of the rhymes as a model to write your own. Then make a Valentine’s card. WB C1, p.68</exercise>
<exercise>C3</exercise>
<exercise>Violets are blue Andsoareyou</exercise>
<sentence>I’ve texted, I’ve tweeted, I’ve emailed ten times This is the last chance For us to be Valentines!</sentence>
<sentence>Roses are red But grass is green You are the silliest boy I’ve ever seen</sentence>
<sentence>Rain or sunshine? Just be my Valentine!</sentence>
<exercise>a) Read the emails and say what they are about.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Describe the boys’ reactions to the Valentine’s card that Rajiv got.</exercise>
<exercise>c) v Extra How can Rajiv find out who sent him the card? Collect ideas in class. WB C2, p.68</exercise>
<sentence>Hi Charlie, Guess what!</sentence>
<sentence>I got a secret Valentine’s card today!</sentence>
<sentence>What if it is from some strange girl?</sentence>
<sentence>Could be embarrassing if we looked at each other and I didn’t know she was the girl who sent me the card.</sentence>
<sentence>How can I find out who sent it?</sentence>
<sentence>Can’t be from C. because she seems to have a boyfriend in Wales now.</sentence>
<sentence>Oh well, whoever sent me the card made it herself.</sentence>
<sentence>It says: “Come to the Youth Club and you’ll see that you are the only one for me!” Do you think I should go?</sentence>
<sentence>George says there is going to be a DJ and a buffet where we can help ourselves to sandwiches and drinks.</sentence>
<sentence>Hi Rajiv, We have to go to the party!</sentence>
<sentence>I hurt myself at football training today and won’t be able to dance.</sentence>
<sentence>But we’ll enjoy ourselves, don’t worry!</sentence>
<sentence>Forget C.!</sentence>
<sentence>Just look at yourself in the mirror: You are a cool guy!</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe the card is from Alicia?</sentence>
<sentence>Remember, Jamie’s younger sister?</sentence>
<sentence>Dark hair, blue eyes, great smile.</sentence>
<sentence>I think she really likes you.</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s meet at your house later, OK?</sentence>
<sentence>Must hurry up now: I’m still in my football clothes.</sentence>
<sentence>Need to quickly get washed and dressed!</sentence>
<exercise>C4 Grammar card: reflexive pronouns 1 Start a grammar card on reflexive pronouns. Copy the grid and complete it with reflexive pronouns from the emails in C3.</exercise>
<exercise>2 There are many reflexive verbs in German which are not reflexive in English. Example: Be quiet, I can’t concentrate! Sei leise, ich kann mich nicht konzentrieren!</exercise>
<exercise>personal pronoun I you she he it</exercise>
<gap>re fl exive pronoun … …</gap>
<gap>… himself itself</gap>
<exercise>Find three more verbs from the emails which are reflexive in German but not in English.</exercise>
<exercise>Use them to write exercises for your grammar card.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Look at LiF 19 on page 169 to check your grammar card. You can also check the use of reflexive pronouns and each other in LiF 20 on page 170. P9, P10 WB C3, p.69</exercise>
<gap>we …</gap>
<exercise>yourselves they themselves</exercise>
<exercise>84 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>Rosesarered</exercise>
<exercise>Sugarissweet</exercise>
<exercise>b) Make your own Valentine’s card:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Collect words that rhyme, e.g. blue – you .</exercise>
<exercise>Roses are red</exercise>
<exercise>But ravens are ...</exercise>
<exercise>And never come ...</exercise>
</page>
<page id='89'>
<chapter>4/C</chapter>
<exercise>C5</exercise>
<exercise>Work in groups.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Write down the following verbs on pieces of paper</exercise>
<exercise>burn cut</exercise>
<exercise>and put them face down.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Pick up a verb.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Take turns to act out a exercise that uses your verb.</exercise>
<exercise>The others must guess what you are doing and write it down.</exercise>
<exercise>Example: Youhaveburntyourself.</exercise>
<exercise>Youareconcentrating.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Check your exercises.</exercise>
<exercise>Not all the verbs take reflexive</exercise>
<exercise>help</exercise>
<exercise>introduce</exercise>
<exercise>concentrate</exercise>
<exercise>enjoy</exercise>
<exercise>hurt</exercise>
<exercise>remember</exercise>
<exercise>pronouns.</exercise>
<exercise>If you need a reflexive pronoun, make sure you use the right form.</exercise>
<exercise>LiF 19: Reflexive pronouns, p.169</exercise>
<exercise>C6 S11, L1/28</exercise>
<exercise>wash</exercise>
<exercise>dress hurry</exercise>
<exercise>a) After reading Charlie’s email, Rajiv calls him. Listen to the boys. Say what Rajiv is worried about and how Charlie reacts. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the boys’ conversation. Note down phrases that Charlie uses to reassure Rajiv.</exercise>
<sentence>Charlie: Hi, Rajiv!</sentence>
<sentence>Did you get my email?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Sure.</sentence>
<sentence>But listen, I really don’t know whether to go to the party or not.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Of course we’ll go.</sentence>
<sentence>It’ll be fun, don’t worry.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: But I won’t know what to say if I see Alicia or any other girl.</sentence>
<sentence>I’ll just feel awkward.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Don’t panic!</sentence>
<sentence>You’ll know what to do.</sentence>
<sentence>Just be cool and say hi.</sentence>
<sentence>George is coming too, so you won’t be on your own.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Hm … OK then. Have you told George when and where to meet us?</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Yup, we’re going to meet him outside the youth club in 20 minutes.</sentence>
<sentence>Hurry up!</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: But I should at least have a shower!</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Good idea.</sentence>
<sentence>Remember you might be getting close to Alicia!</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Stop it, Charlie, or I won’t come!</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Relax, everything will be fine.</sentence>
<sentence>Oh, and don’t forget to bring your secret card …</sentence>
<exercise>C7 Grammar card: infinitive after question words 1 Look at the following sentence from C6: I really don’t know whether to go to the party or not. Collect more sentences like this from C6. Use different colours for the question word and the infinitive. How would you say these sentences in German?</exercise>
<exercise>2 Start a grammar card for the infinitive after question words. Look at LiF 21 on page 170 to check your grammar card. P11</exercise>
<exercise>C8 Caroline asks Gillian for advice. Use these verbs and the infinitive after question words to write down what Caroline asks Gillian. LiF 21: Infinitive after question words, p.170</exercise>
<listing>ask · be not sure about · want to know · wonder</listing>
<exercise>Example: Carolineiswondering whattodoaboutGethin.</exercise>
<sentence>When should I talk to Rajiv?</sentence>
<sentence>Should I text Rajiv before the party?</sentence>
<sentence>What can I wear to the party?</sentence>
<sentence>What shall I do about Gethin?</sentence>
<sentence>How can I meet Rajiv without George or Charlie?</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 85</footnote>
</page>
<page id='90'>
<chapter>4/C</chapter>
<exercise>C9 P7 a) Read the photo story to find out what happened at the Valentine’s Day party at the youth club. Say how … 1 Caroline feels at the beginning of the party. 2 Rajiv feels before the party. 3 George feels when he sees the card.</exercise>
<gap>I think … feels …</gap>
<gap>Rajiv seems to be/ appears to be … … could be/ might be excited because ...</gap>
<exercise>excited ∙ jealous ∙ nervous ∙</exercise>
<exercise>4 Caroline feels when she checks Gethin’s PalPlace status. 5 Rajiv feels when he asks Caroline to dance. 6 George and Charlie feel when Gethin turns up at the party. 7 Gethin feels when he sees Caroline and Rajiv dancing. Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>embarrassed ∙ surprised ∙ worried ∙ disappointed ∙ upset ∙ irritated ∙ confused ∙ amused ∙ cheerful</exercise>
<exercise>b) Look at the photo story again. Which character do you most/least sympathize with?</exercise>
<exercise>Explain why.</exercise>
<sentence>Hi Rajiv!</sentence>
<sentence>Do you think Rajiv will come?</sentence>
<sentence>Let’s see your mystery card.</sentence>
<sentence>Here you are.</sentence>
<sentence>But it’s really embarrassing.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline and Emma arrive at the youth club.</sentence>
<sentence>Meanwhile the boys meet outside the youth club.</sentence>
<sentence>But who can it be from?</sentence>
<sentence>George solves the mystery.</sentence>
<sentence>Well … I know my sister’s handwriting.</sentence>
<sentence>Wow! Are you sure?!?</sentence>
<sentence>Oh no! I don’t believe it!</sentence>
<sentence>At the same time inside …</sentence>
<sentence>Look!</sentence>
<sentence>What’s wrong?</sentence>
<sentence>You look terrible.</sentence>
<sentence>Euston Station, Tuesday 6:45</sentence>
<sentence>@ Camden Youth 2 hours ago</sentence>
<sentence>Emma Me too!</sentence>
<sentence>CU soon!</sentence>
<sentence>53 minutes ago</sentence>
<sentence>It will be a fantastic surprise!</sentence>
<sentence>At Euston Station Gethin is excited about seeing Caroline soon.</sentence>
<exercise>86 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<sentence>Check in: London, 2 minutes ago</sentence>
<sentence>Looking forward to V-Day party @ Camden Youth Club tonight!!!</sentence>
</page>
<page id='91'>
<chapter>4/C</chapter>
<exercise>C10 Target task v " Project Portfolio Choose: Write an ending to the story. or: Finish the photo story.</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at p.91.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Think of a storyline. Remember how the characters have acted in parts A, B and C of this Theme.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Collect words and phrases for your (photo) story. Writing, pp.144/145 Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>2 Write:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the present tense. ∙ Include adjectives and adverbs to describe ∙ Use different words for say . Look at B4b) for help or use a dictionary.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write speech bubbles and captions before you ∙ Make sure that your speech bubbles and captions support the photos.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ You can use your computer to design your pages.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Check the task again. Have you done everything that is expected?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Swap your ending of the (photo) story with a partner’s. Give feedback to each other. Speaking 2, p.140; Writing, pp. 144/145 WB C4, C5, pp.70/71</exercise>
<sentence>Right, now just keep cool, Rajiv.</sentence>
<sentence>She likes me.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s over with Gethin.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv is looking for Caroline.</sentence>
<sentence>Look who’s here.</sentence>
<sentence>Oh no, there’s Rajiv!</sentence>
<sentence>What a nightmare!</sentence>
<sentence>What should Caroline do?</sentence>
<sentence>What am I doing?!?</sentence>
<sentence>The Welsh boy!</sentence>
<sentence>Now what?</sentence>
<sentence>Oh no!</sentence>
<sentence>Gethin has finally found the youth club.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 87</footnote>
<exercise>1 Plan:</exercise>
<exercise>What happens next?</exercise>
<exercise>How do the characters feel?</exercise>
<exercise>What do they say to each other?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Organize your ideas under these headings: What? ∙ Who? ∙ Where? ∙ When? ∙ Why?</exercise>
<exercise>For your story:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use direct speech.</exercise>
<exercise>For your photo story:</exercise>
<exercise>take photos.</exercise>
<exercise>the characters’ feelings and their actions.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Take photos.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Edit:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Check LiF if you are not sure about the grammar.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Check the spelling of difficult words in the dictionary.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='102'>
<chapter>5/A</chapter>
<exercise>The German exchange</exercise>
<exercise>A1 a) Look at this photograph and describe it.</exercise>
<exercise>Wordbank Pictures, p.174 WB A1, p.79 b) Speculate about the context of this</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Who are the people in it?</exercise>
<exercise>P11</exercise>
<gap>They could be …</gap>
<gap>Maybe/Perhaps …</gap>
<gap>I think/ I suppose …</gap>
<gap>It looks as if …</gap>
<gap>They seem to be …</gap>
<exercise>A2 L 2/1 a) Listen to the CD. What is happening? Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again. Make a list of all the points the boys should consider when they write an email to their exchange partner.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Compare your notes with your partner’s and complete them. WB A2, p.80</exercise>
<exercise>A4 Target task v Portfolio P1</exercise>
<exercise>A3 a) Read Rajiv’s email on page 99. Check whether he has written everything Mr Lewis told the class to include. Use your list from A2 and say what is missing.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Would you like to have Rajiv as an exchange partner? Tell your partner why or why not.</exercise>
<exercise>I would/wouldn’t like to have Rajiv as a partner because … ∙ I’m not sure if Rajiv would be the right partner for me</exercise>
<exercise>because … ∙ On the one hand he seems to be … On the other hand he …</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at p.108.</exercise>
<exercise>Write an email to Rajiv as his German exchange partner.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Look at the profiles of four German students taking part in the exchange with William Ellis School (p. 99). Choose the girl or boy that you think fits Rajiv best.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Write an answer to Rajiv’s email as his German exchange partner.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Think of other relevant information that you can include.</exercise>
<exercise>3 In his email Rajiv uses words like: however, that’s why, when, because, after, as soon as, while, so. Use at least five of these connectives in your email.</exercise>
<exercise>4 In pairs read the emails and give feedback. Check if you answered all of Rajiv’s questions and used the information in the profiles. Writing, pp.144/145 LiF 12: Connectives, pp.162/163 P2 WB A3, A4, pp.80/81</exercise>
<exercise>98 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>photograph, e.g.</exercise>
<exercise>:</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Why are they together?</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the information in the profile.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Answer Rajiv’s questions.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='103'>
<chapter>5/A</chapter>
<german>Dear partner, Ich heiße Rajiv Khan und ich bin 13 Jahre alt.</german>
<german>Ich wohne mit meiner Familie in Camden Town, London.</german>
<sentence>So that’s about as far as my German goes, I’m afraid.</sentence>
<sentence>I’ve only had German lessons for a few months.</sentence>
<sentence>However, I’m sure you speak good English.</sentence>
<sentence>When did you start to learn English at school?</sentence>
<sentence>I’m really looking forward to coming to Germany so that I can improve my German.</sentence>
<sentence>Firstly, I would like to tell you something more about my family.</sentence>
<sentence>My parents’ families originally came from India.</sentence>
<sentence>That’s why we sometimes speak Hindi at home – but don’t worry, everyone speaks really good English.</sentence>
<sentence>My parents have a shop and our flat is above it.</sentence>
<sentence>When you stay with us, you will share a room with me, or, if you are a girl, with my sister Sheree.</sentence>
<sentence>Have you got any brothers or sisters?</sentence>
<sentence>My hobbies are playing football and cricket – I’m in the school cricket team.</sentence>
<sentence>Do you know what cricket is?</sentence>
<sentence>Perhaps we can watch a game when you come.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m also keen on music and play the guitar.</sentence>
<sentence>What about you?</sentence>
<sentence>What are you interested in?</sentence>
<sentence>After school and at the weekend I spend time with my friends.</sentence>
<sentence>We often play football in the park.</sentence>
<sentence>As soon as you come, George, my best friend, wants to organize a game between England and Germany.</sentence>
<sentence>Do you play football?</sentence>
<sentence>Sometimes I have to help my parents in their shop.</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t worry, though!</sentence>
<sentence>While you are here, we can do lots of nice things together and I won’t have to work.</sentence>
<sentence>I have attached a photograph of me in my school uniform.</sentence>
<sentence>Could you please send me one of you?</sentence>
<sentence>Hope to hear from you soon.</sentence>
<sentence>Yours, Rajiv Khan</sentence>
<sentence>Student name: Leyla Aydin Age: 13 Email: leyla.aydin@cybmail.de Family information: I have two brothers, aged 15 and 19.</sentence>
<sentence>There is a guest room for my partner.</sentence>
<sentence>My family is from Turkey.</sentence>
<sentence>Personal information: I very much like football.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m in the school team and I play football almost every day with my friends.</sentence>
<sentence>I’d love to see Arsenal play.</sentence>
<sentence>I like music a lot, especially pop music.</sentence>
<sentence>Medical information: – Dietary restrictions: –</sentence>
<sentence>Student name: Bruno Schmidt Age: 12 Email: bschmidt@yoosurf.de Family information: I’ve got one younger brother and I live in a flat with my mother and father.</sentence>
<sentence>My partner can share a room with me.</sentence>
<sentence>Personal information: I like listening to music and I play the piano.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m not so keen on sports but I’m very interested in science and maths and would love to visit the Science Museum.</sentence>
<sentence>Medical information: I have asthma.</sentence>
<sentence>Dietary restrictions: I don’t like fish.</sentence>
<sentence>Student name: Helena Müller Age: 13 Email: helena.mueller@yoosurf.de Family information: I have a sister and two brothers.</sentence>
<sentence>My parents are divorced and I live with my father.</sentence>
<sentence>We have a guest room.</sentence>
<sentence>Personal information: I like meeting friends, shopping, playing the guitar and dancing, and I love horses.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m looking forward to shopping in London.</sentence>
<sentence>Medical information: I’m allergic to cats.</sentence>
<sentence>Dietary restrictions: I’m a vegetarian.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 99</footnote>
</page>
<page id='104'>
<chapter>5/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 Placemat: What do you know about other countries? What is different from Germany? Note down your ideas. Think of</exercise>
<exercise>∙ places to live. Placemat, p.149</exercise>
<exercise>B2 L 2/2</exercise>
<exercise>a) Listen to the dialogue. What are your first impressions of Rajiv’s exchange partner Leon? Give reasons. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<gap>He seems to be He appears to be I have the impression that he is …</gap>
<gap>polite friendly rude …</gap>
<gap>because he …</gap>
<exercise>b) Speculate on why the two boys were matched and how you think they will get on with each other. Give reasons.</exercise>
<exercise>B3 a) Now read the following conversations between Rajiv and Leon during their weekend together at the Khan house.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What do you think about Leon’s behaviour in each situation?</exercise>
<exercise>b) How do you think Rajiv feels about Leon’s visit after the weekend? Explain your opinion. Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>A</exercise>
<exercise>B</exercise>
<sentence>Rajiv: Would you like a cup of tea and a biscuit?</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Well, I don’t actually drink tea.</sentence>
<sentence>Can I have a glass of water?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Sure, I’ll get you some tap water.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Mmh! Do you have any bottled water?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, no. Everyone drinks tap water here.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Oh, don’t worry.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m not really thirsty.</sentence>
<sentence>I’ll just have a biscuit.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, don’t eat too many.</sentence>
<sentence>Mum has made a special curry for you!</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Oh! Do you always eat curry?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Let me show you my room, Leon.</sentence>
<sentence>This is where you are going to sleep.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Oh, that’s great, Rajiv.</sentence>
<sentence>Thanks. Er. Who are those people on the posters?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: They are famous Indian musicians.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Famous? Do English people listen to them?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, I’m English and I listen to them!</sentence>
<sentence>Look, I’ve got lots of their CDs.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Really? I’m sure nobody in Germany has ever heard of them.</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t you have any other music?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Here’s the bathroom.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: That’s strange. Why haven’t you got a carpet on the floor?</sentence>
<sentence>My English teacher, Mr Riether, told us that English people usually have carpets on the floor.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, obviously your English teacher hasn’t been to England for a long time!</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Sorry, Rajiv. I didn’t mean to upset you.</sentence>
<sentence>It’s just that everything is so different from home.</sentence>
<sentence>Can you show me how the shower works?</sentence>
<sentence>The taps look so strange!</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Where’s Sheree this evening?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: She’s out with her boyfriend.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: Is she allowed to have a boyfriend?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Of course she is.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: I thought Indian parents were very strict with their daughters.</sentence>
<sentence>Can she choose her own husband later?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Of course she can!</sentence>
<exercise>100 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ food and drink,</exercise>
<exercise>∙ customs and behaviour and</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What problems do they have with each other?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='105'>
<chapter>5/B</chapter>
<exercise>c) What should Leon do differently? Give him some tips.</exercise>
<gap>polite to … It It would be better not to …</gap>
<gap>You ought to …</gap>
<exercise>B4 v Extra Rajiv talks to his mother about Leon. He is upset about Leon’s comments and wants to tell his mother about his worries. As Mrs Khan was once a foreigner in England herself, she understands Leon better and tries to calm Rajiv down. Finish their conversation.</exercise>
<sentence>Rajiv: Leon’s not very polite, you know.</sentence>
<sentence>He asks all these personal questions.</sentence>
<sentence>Mrs Khan: Well, I’m sure he doesn’t mean to be rude.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: But he’s got such strange ideas about Indian families.</sentence>
<gap>He…</gap>
<exercise>B5 L2/3 On Monday Leon is on a trip to Cambridge with the other Germans. Rajiv and his classmates are talking to Mr Lewis about the weekend. Listen to their conversation. Find out what problems the other boys had with their exchange partners. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<sentence>Mr Lewis: How are you getting on with Leon, Rajiv?</sentence>
<sentence>He seems very nice.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, he isn’t always easy to get on with.</sentence>
<sentence>He’s really choosy about food and drink.</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Lewis: Oh, is he?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: He asked me if he could have a glass of water.</sentence>
<sentence>But he didn’t want the glass of tap water I gave him.</sentence>
<sentence>He asked me if we had any bottled water!</sentence>
<sentence>There’s nothing wrong with our tap water!</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Lewis: But he usually drinks bottled water, Rajiv.</sentence>
<sentence>He doesn’t know that it’s not what you usually drink here.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: OK. But when I told him that Mum had made a special curry for him, he asked me if we always ate curry.</sentence>
<sentence>And he didn’t look very happy.</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Lewis: Well, I suppose it is sometimes difficult for young people coming here for the first time.</sentence>
<sentence>Not everyone likes spicy food, you know.</sentence>
<sentence>Nigel: But Mr Lewis, my partner had lots of personal questions, too.</sentence>
<sentence>He asked me if my dad earned a lot of money because we’ve got a swimming pool.</sentence>
<sentence>Holden: Well, he does, doesn’t he? But I know what you mean.</sentence>
<sentence>My partner, Lina, asked me why my mum made tea with tea bags.</sentence>
<sentence>She said, “We use real tea in Germany.”</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Lewis: Well, that is one of the things you’ll be able to check when we go there.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m sure you’ll find other cultural differences as well.</sentence>
<sentence>That’s what makes it interesting.</sentence>
<sentence>Robin: But they seem to think everything is better in Germany, sir.</sentence>
<sentence>My partner asked me why my dad didn’t drive a German car.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Well, one difference seems to be that Germans ask lots of rather direct questions.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon asked me if I had any other music when I tried to get him interested in Indian music.</sentence>
<sentence>Nigel: Well, I’m not surprised.</sentence>
<sentence>Who wants to listen to that awful rubbish?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Perhaps Leon should stay with you.</sentence>
<sentence>Neither of you seem to like Indian people.</sentence>
<sentence>Mr Lewis: That’s enough, Rajiv.</sentence>
<sentence>I’m sure that’s not true.</sentence>
<sentence>Now Nigel, I don’t want you making comments like that.</sentence>
<sentence>If you can’t be more tolerant, I might have to change my mind about taking you to Germany.</sentence>
<sentence>Nigel: Sorry, sir.</sentence>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 101</footnote>
<exercise>It isn’t very</exercise>
<gap>You shouldn’t …</gap>
</page>
<page id='106'>
<chapter>5/B</chapter>
<exercise>B6 a) Read the conversation from B5. Say which personal questions the boys reported to Mr Lewis.</exercise>
<exercise>My partner Leon Lina</exercise>
<exercise>asked me wanted to know</exercise>
<exercise>if why</exercise>
<exercise>my parents my mum my dad I we</exercise>
<exercise>made tea with tea bags.</exercise>
<exercise>earned a lot of money.</exercise>
<exercise>had any other music.</exercise>
<exercise>always ate curry.</exercise>
<exercise>didn’t buy a German car.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Explain why you think the boys were upset about these questions.</exercise>
<exercise>B7 Grammar detective: reported questions 1 What do you remember about reported speech? Look at this example: Mrs Khan said: “I hope you will enjoy your stay.“</exercise>
<exercise>Mrs Khan said that she hoped he would enjoy his stay.</exercise>
<exercise>2 How did Leon’s questions change when Rajiv reported them to Mr Lewis?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at these examples: “Do you have any bottled water?”</exercise>
<exercise>› He asked me if we had any bottled water.</exercise>
<exercise>“Who are those people on the posters?”</exercise>
<exercise>› He asked me who the people on the posters were.</exercise>
<exercise>3 What are the rules for reported questions?</exercise>
<exercise>Write them down on your grammar card on reported speech and add examples of reported questions from the dialogue.</exercise>
<exercise>Look at LiF 22 on page 171 for help.</exercise>
<exercise>B8 Read B3 again. What else did Rajiv report to Mr Lewis about Leon? Put Leon’s questions in parts C and D into reported speech. Example: HeaskedmeifEnglish peoplelistenedtoIndianmusic. LiF 22: Reported questions, p.171</exercise>
<exercise>P3 WB B1, B2, pp.82/83</exercise>
<exercise>Support Check your grammar card on reported speech.</exercise>
<exercise>B9 S14, L2/4</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Which phrases could you use in less formal situations? b) Listen to the three different situations where an apology is necessary. Which of the phrases from a) would you choose for each situation? P4 WB B3, p.83</exercise>
<exercise>I’m really sorry.</exercise>
<exercise>Please don’t be</exercise>
<exercise>angry with me.</exercise>
<exercise>Sorry, I didn’t mean it.</exercise>
<exercise>Please accept my apologies.</exercise>
<exercise>I do apologize.</exercise>
<exercise>Sorry.</exercise>
<exercise>It won’t happen again.</exercise>
<exercise>B10 Target task v " Project Portfolio Need help? Look at pp.109/110.</exercise>
<exercise>With a partner write and present a conversation between Rajiv and Leon.</exercise>
<exercise>They want to talk about some of the misunderstandings they have had.</exercise>
<exercise>One of you takes Rajiv’s part, the other one takes Leon’s part.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Talk to your partner about your ideas and note them down. 2 Note down words and expressions you might use to</exercise>
<exercise>explain and apologize.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Silent dialogue: Take turns to write your parts of the dialogue.</exercise>
<exercise>Include reported statements and questions.</exercise>
<exercise>Silent dialogue, p.150</exercise>
<exercise>4 Present your conversation</exercise>
<exercise>to the class.</exercise>
<exercise>5 Give feedback to your classmates about their conversations.</exercise>
<exercise>Writing, pp.144/145 Speaking 2, p.140</exercise>
<exercise>102 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>a) Look at these phrases for apologizing.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Which phrases could you use in formal situations?</exercise>
</page>
<page id='107'>
<chapter>5/B</chapter>
<exercise>B11 a) At the weekend Rajiv takes Leon to meet his uncle in Brick Lane in East London. Look at the photos and talk about what you can find in Brick Lane.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the information from the travel guide. Choose three photographs which best illustrate it and explain your choice.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Would you like to visit Brick Lane? Give reasons.</exercise>
<sentence>Full of noise, colour and life, Brick Lane, near Whitechapel Under- ground station in London’s East End, is a combination of old and new, and a mix of cultures.</sentence>
<sentence>Today it is the centre of a big Bengali community in an area that people call Banglatown.</sentence>
<sentence>The southern part of the lane is one long line of curry and balti houses mixed with fabric shops and Indian supermarkets.</sentence>
<sentence>Sadly, the once high standard of cooking in the curry houses is a distant memory.</sentence>
<sentence>If you want to eat a curry, it’s better to go elsewhere.</sentence>
<sentence>Just past Hanbury St is what was the Old Truman Brewery, a group of buildings on both sides of the lane that was once London’s largest brewery.</sentence>
<sentence>The brewery closed in 1989.</sentence>
<sentence>In the 1990s it opened again and became home to many independent music businesses, small shops and hip clubs and bars.</sentence>
<sentence>North of here, Brick Lane is a very different place, with many different types of clothes stores, some of London’s best bagel bakeries and plenty of cafés and bars.</sentence>
<exercise>B12 v Extra Find out more about other areas in London which have Asian or African-Caribbean communities, e.g. Brixton, Southall, Tower Hamlets. Searching the Internet, p.143 WB B4-B6, pp.84/85</exercise>
<exercise>Choose: a) Prepare a short presentation.</exercise>
<exercise>Speaking 1, pp.139/140 or: b) Make a poster with photographs and descriptions.</exercise>
<exercise>B13 L 2/5 a) Rajiv and Leon visit Rajiv’s uncle, who has a small recording studio. Listen to the dialogue and say what Leon now thinks about the exchange visit. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and note down what Deepak tells Leon about the changes that have taken place in Brick Lane. P12</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 103</footnote>
</page>
<page id='108'>
<chapter>5/B</chapter>
<exercise>B14 a) Read this report for a school magazine that was written by another German exchange student. Match the photographs to the paragraphs.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Choose the best heading for this report. Give reasons for your choice. What a View! ∙ Spectacular South Bank ∙ A Great Day Out ∙ The Best of London</exercise>
<sentence>The best thing that happened to me in England was when we went to see the South Bank.</sentence>
<sentence>I hadn’t realized what a fantastic place it was.</sentence>
<sentence>First we got the tube from Camden Market to Embankment.</sentence>
<sentence>I just love travelling on the Underground in London.</sentence>
<sentence>Those long escalators are amazing!</sentence>
<sentence>Then we went to Embankment and walked across the bridge to the South Bank.</sentence>
<sentence>We got a fabulous view of the London Eye.</sentence>
<sentence>I hoped that we would go on it but there were so many people and it is rather expensive.</sentence>
<sentence>However, I didn’t mind because there was so much to see and do.</sentence>
<sentence>So we walked on towards London Bridge.</sentence>
<sentence>Everywhere there were different kinds of artists, brilliant human statues, singers – it was so entertaining.</sentence>
<sentence>I could have spent hours just watching them.</sentence>
<sentence>After that we bought some fish and chips and ate them while the ships went past on the Thames.</sentence>
<sentence>It seemed like the best meal I had ever had.</sentence>
<sentence>Then we watched some young skaters and cyclists.</sentence>
<sentence>They did some amazing tricks.</sentence>
<sentence>Later we had tea in the café on the 7th floor of the Tate Modern.</sentence>
<sentence>What a fantastic view of St Paul’s Cathedral and Millennium Bridge!</sentence>
<sentence>We walked across the bridge and took a last look at the South Bank before getting the Underground home.</sentence>
<sentence>It really was a great day out.</sentence>
<exercise>c) Collect words and expressions from the text that you can use to make a report interesting to read. Example: thebestthingthathappenedtomein England</exercise>
<exercise>B15 Target task v Portfolio P5</exercise>
<exercise>d) Look at the structure of the report. Which words are used to structure it and make it easier to follow? Make a list. Example: first</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at p.110.</exercise>
<exercise>Write a report.</exercise>
<exercise>Writing, pp.144/145 Choose: a) Leon’s English teacher has asked him to write a report about a day in London.</exercise>
<exercise>Leon has chosen his day in Brick Lane because he had</exercise>
<exercise>such a good time there.</exercise>
<exercise>Write his report.</exercise>
<exercise>or: b) Write a report about a day that you spent visiting an interesting place.</exercise>
<exercise>Support</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Include information about how Leon/you felt.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use adjectives, adverbs and conjunctions to improve your text. Look at your list from B14d).</exercise>
<exercise>104 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Give the report a heading.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write about what Leon/you saw.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Report on what other people told Leon/you</exercise>
<exercise>about the place.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write in the past tense.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Ask a partner to edit your report.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='109'>
<chapter>5/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 a) v Choose: b) Charlie is a big sports fan.</exercise>
<exercise>In groups collect sports Look at the pinboard in his room.</exercise>
<exercise>words in a word web.</exercise>
<exercise>Which sports can you see?</exercise>
<exercise>or: Make an ABC of sports.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Which of these sports do you find most interesting? Give reasons. P8</exercise>
<sentence>Mohamed “Mo” Farah CBE is the Somali-born British international track and field athlete in the long distance and middle-distance.</sentence>
<sentence>He is the current 10,000 metres Olympic and World champion and 5,000 metres Olympic, World and European champion.</sentence>
<sentence>Born in Somalia on 23rd March, 1983, Farah spent the early years of his childhood with his twin brother in Djibouti.</sentence>
<exercise>C2 L 2/6 a) Rajiv and Leon are visiting Charlie at home. Listen to the boys. What are they talking about? Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the following questions first. Then listen again and answer them. 1 Which sports are mentioned? 2 Which of the athletes from Charlie’s pinboard</exercise>
<exercise>3 Whose family is from Jamaica?</exercise>
<exercise>4 Whose family is from Somalia?</exercise>
<exercise>c) v Extra: Choose two of the athletes the boys are talking about. Listen again and note down what you learn about them. Talk to your classmates to find out more about the athletes you didn’t choose.</exercise>
<exercise>C3 v Extra: Viewing: Lewis Hamilton a) Lewis Hamilton is one of the most famous Formula 1 drivers and was the 2008 Formula 1 World Champion. Sport Magazine interviewed him.</exercise>
<exercise>Read the following questions first.</exercise>
<exercise>Then watch the interview with Lewis Hamilton and Sport Magazine and answer the questions.</exercise>
<exercise>1 What kind of dog is Roscoe?</exercise>
<exercise>2 Which superpower would Lewis like to have?</exercise>
<exercise>3 Who sent him a pair of boxer shorts?</exercise>
<exercise>4 Why is music so important to Lewis?</exercise>
<exercise>5 What happened in Montreal?</exercise>
<exercise>Viewing, p.139</exercise>
<exercise>b) Watch the clip again and add any information to your answers that is still missing.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 105</footnote>
</page>
<page id='110'>
<chapter>5/C</chapter>
<exercise>C4 a) Read the profiles of these sports stars. What are the reasons for their success?</exercise>
<exercise>b) Collect words and phrases from the profiles to talk about …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ a person’s character, e.g. intelligence and determination ,</exercise>
<exercise>P6 WB C1, p.86</exercise>
<sentence>Nothing Can Stop Sally Sally Brown from Belfast was born with only one healthy arm.</sentence>
<sentence>Her left arm did not develop below the elbow.</sentence>
<sentence>However, she soon found out that she was a talented sprinter and developed a real passion for the sport.</sentence>
<sentence>Since then, she has competed for many years.</sentence>
<sentence>Probably the biggest event in her career was the 2012 Paralympics in London.</sentence>
<sentence>In addition to her training, Sally is also keen to continue focussing on her education.</sentence>
<sentence>After completing her GCSEs, her ambition is to go on to study for her A levels and attend university.</sentence>
<sentence>From Student to Superstar Life hasn’t always been easy for LeBron James, born in Ohio in 1984.</sentence>
<sentence>His mother, Gloria, was only 16 at the time and had to look after LeBron on her own.</sentence>
<sentence>So Gloria and LeBron moved home many times.</sentence>
<sentence>But LeBron didn’t make friends easily.</sentence>
<sentence>Although he found it difficult to concentrate at school, he could show his intelligence and his determination in sports.</sentence>
<sentence>LeBron was an excellent athlete because he had speed and strength.</sentence>
<sentence>At the age of 19, he started to play basketball in the NBA and he was the best new player of the year 2003.</sentence>
<exercise>C5 Target task v Need help? Look at p.111.</exercise>
<sentence>Sharapova’s Career Grand Slam</sentence>
<sentence>Maria Sharapova is a very determined tennis player and she has never been afraid to work hard.</sentence>
<sentence>She has been used to playing and training a lot to achieve success since she was a child.</sentence>
<sentence>Sharapova always travels a lot and plays in many matches so she admits that she doesn’t have much time for a private life.</sentence>
<sentence>Still, her aim to train hard and be successful is clearly working.</sentence>
<sentence>Between 2004 and 2012 she won all four Grand Slam titles and so became only the 10th woman to complete a Career Grand Slam.</sentence>
<exercise>C6 S15, L2/7</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Collect information, e.g. from the Internet. ∙ Write about where your athlete came from and include information about his/her education and the reasons for</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use words and phrases from C1a) ∙ Improve your profile by using connectives. Writing, pp.144/145 Wordbank Sports, p.177</exercise>
<exercise>LiF 12: Connectives, pp.162/163 WB C2, pp.86/87</exercise>
<exercise>a) In the afternoon Leon and Rajiv meet Caroline, Charlie and his classmate Sam to play football. Listen to the dialogue. What are they discussing? Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the dialogue on page 107. Find arguments for and against choosing a career as an athlete. Write them down in a grid.</exercise>
<exercise>c) In a conversation it is always helpful to be able to react to what someone else has said. Collect useful phrases from the dialogue. Example: Noproblem. WB C3, p.88</exercise>
<exercise>106 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>∙ sports, e.g. a talented sprinter ,</exercise>
<exercise>∙ a person’s education, e.g. to study .</exercise>
<exercise>Write a profile about an athlete.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use the profiles from this page as models.</exercise>
<exercise>his/her success.</exercise>
<exercise>and C4b).</exercise>
</page>
<page id='111'>
<chapter>5/C</chapter>
<sentence>Charlie: Hi everyone! Good to see you again, Leon!</sentence>
<sentence>Sam: Hi Leon, I’m Sam! Let’s start!</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: But Caroline’s not here yet. Let’s wait.</sentence>
<sentence>She said she would be a bit late.</sentence>
<sentence>Sam: No problem. Why don’t we do some warm-up exercises?</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Warm-up exercises? That sounds a bit serious.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie said we would just play for a bit of fun.</sentence>
<sentence>What about a little snack?</sentence>
<sentence>My mum has made some samosas for us.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: They really smell wonderful and I’m sure they taste delicious, but let’s try them later.</sentence>
<sentence>Sam said he could show us some tricks.</sentence>
<sentence>He plays for Arsenal Juniors.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Wow, I didn’t know that.</sentence>
<sentence>What’s the training like?</sentence>
<sentence>Sam: Well, we train really hard and we have a match every weekend.</sentence>
<sentence>Leon: That must be exhausting.</sentence>
<sentence>Sam: It is, but I want to become a professional football player one day.</sentence>
<sentence>Don’t you think it would feel great to score a goal in the World Cup?</sentence>
<sentence>Theo Walcott is my hero!</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Wow, you really are keen on football.</sentence>
<sentence>But when do you have time to study?</sentence>
<sentence>Sam: Well, my parents were a bit worried at first.</sentence>
<sentence>But my work at school is usually OK.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: But Sam, you’re always so tired!</sentence>
<sentence>You even fell asleep during maths last week.</sentence>
<sentence>You told me you were doing your homework until very late at night because football training was so long.</sentence>
<sentence>I think you still need to do your schoolwork.</sentence>
<sentence>Rajiv: Yeah, I think Charlie’s right.</sentence>
<sentence>It would be cool if you became a famous football player, but what if you can’t?</sentence>
<sentence>What if you got seriously hurt and had to get a normal job?</sentence>
<sentence>Sam: Don’t be so negative.</sentence>
<sentence>I’ll be famous and earn lots of money.</sentence>
<sentence>Like Theo! – Oh, look, here’s Caroline. Hi!</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Hi guys! Who’s Theo?</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Theo Walcott. Sam’s hero.</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Oh, he plays brilliantly. And he looks cute, too.</sentence>
<sentence>Charlie: Cute?</sentence>
<sentence>Caroline: Oh, forget it. Let’s start the game!</sentence>
<exercise>C7 Grammar card: adjectives after verbs of perception 1 You know how to use adverbs of manner to describe how someone does something: He sings badly . However, after certain verbs, like feel or taste, you use an adjective , not an adverb: I feel bad today. These verbs are called verbs of perception. Find more examples from C6.</exercise>
<exercise>2 Add the rule for adjectives after verbs of perception and your examples to your grammar card on adverbs. Check LiF 23 on page 171 if necessary. WB C4, p.88</exercise>
<exercise>C8</exercise>
<exercise>C9 Target task v P7 WB C5, p.89</exercise>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at p.111.</exercise>
<exercise>Say what you think of these things.</exercise>
<exercise>Use sound, smell, taste, feel or look .</exercise>
<exercise>Example: Badeggssmellterrible.</exercise>
<exercise>LiF 23: Adjectives after verbs of perception, p.171</exercise>
<exercise>P9, P10</exercise>
<exercise>Discuss this statement in class: “Being a sports star is great.</exercise>
<exercise>You are famous and you earn a lot of money.”</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write down your ideas and your arguments ∙ Think what arguments might be used against you</exercise>
<exercise>working late at night ∙ bad eggs ∙ sports drinks ∙ being famous ∙ vegetables ∙ the school choir ∙ Wayne Rooney ∙ scoring four goals in a match ∙ losing a football match ∙ rock music</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Note down words and phrases you can use</exercise>
<exercise>in a discussion.</exercise>
<exercise>Check your results from C6c).</exercise>
<exercise>2 Have your discussion in class.</exercise>
<exercise>Speaking 3, p.141</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 107</footnote>
<exercise>1 Prepare for the discussion:</exercise>
<exercise>to support them.</exercise>
<exercise>and find answers to them.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='120'>
<chapter>6/A</chapter>
<exercise>A different holiday</exercise>
<exercise>A1 a) It’s the holidays soon and Emma is preparing for them. Look at the books and DVDs below and match the covers with the blurbs. Explain your decisions.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Look at the books and DVDs. What do they show us about Emma’s interests at the moment?</exercise>
<exercise>c) Choose a book or DVD cover. Describe it to your partner. Use the words and phrases on the right. Your partner must close his/her book and guess the right cover. WB A1, p.97 Wordbank Pictures, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>On the cover there is/are … ∙ In the foreground/In the background … ∙ On the left/On the right …∙ In the centre we can see … ∙ In the top left-hand/right-hand corner … ∙ At the bottom there is …</exercise>
<exercise>2 A very entertaining film with Roger Moore playing a woman-hating, cat-loving Scottish expert who lives in his family’s castle.</exercise>
<sentence>When lots of oil gets into the oceans, it has a huge effect on the environment.</sentence>
<sentence>When terrorists threaten to explode an oil rig in the North Sea, he is the only hope, so the government asks him to help.</sentence>
<sentence>The novel is set in the near future.</sentence>
<sentence>Climate change is causing natural disasters like storms and flooding, so the British government decides to control how much carbon everyone is allowed to use.</sentence>
<sentence>16-year-old Laura Brown writes about her experience and those of her family and friends.</sentence>
<sentence>With full-colour photos this book shows the reader how so much oil gets into the oceans, what damage it causes and what methods are used to clean it up.</sentence>
<sentence>It describes the consequences, which are still felt for a long time after it is cleaned up.</sentence>
<sentence>An informative book, not only for young readers.</sentence>
<sentence>He immediately acts to stop the terrorists, save hundreds of lives and prevent a catastrophe on the Scottish coast.</sentence>
<sentence>The film is full of clever wit and action, but no violence, making it a very enjoyable film.</sentence>
</page>
<page id='121'>
<chapter>6/A</chapter>
<exercise>A2 L 2/10 a) Emma is talking to Caroline about her holiday plans. Listen to the girls to find out about Emma’s plans. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and say what Emma’s reasons for her plans are. WB A2, A3, pp.97/98</exercise>
<exercise>A3 Target task v P1 Need help? Look at p.128.</exercise>
<exercise>Choose: Write a blurb for a book.</exercise>
<exercise>or: Write a blurb for a DVD.</exercise>
<exercise>1 Read the blurbs again and collect adjectives and phrases you can use to write your own blurb.</exercise>
<gap>Example: makethemostofyour time,detailedandinformative,…</gap>
<exercise>2 Choose a book or a DVD that you would recommend for the holidays. Write a short blurb to explain what your book/DVD is about and what makes it interesting. Writing, pp.144/145</exercise>
<exercise>3 Present your results in a gallery walk. Gallery walk, p.150</exercise>
<exercise>WB A4, A5, p.99</exercise>
<sentence>Set in the future, this is the incredible story of twelve-year- old Jemima Mallard.</sentence>
<sentence>She lives in a London which has been sinking since the climate change.</sentence>
<sentence>This guide is one of 12 new local UK guides for everyone who wants to discover Britain!</sentence>
<sentence>It is perfect for visitors coming to Britain for the first time, as it highlights all the sights and top attractions that are an absolute must.</sentence>
<sentence>This city guide provides fascinating facts and tips.</sentence>
<sentence>The easy-to-follow maps of sights come with suggestions for places to eat, drink and shop, so that you can make the most of your visit.</sentence>
<sentence>This underwater world provides an eerie background as Jemima tries to survive while police teams of children and of adults fight each other to keep the peace.</sentence>
<sentence>Action and adventure make this novel an original and provocative page-turner, suitable for young teens.</sentence>
<sentence>Make the most of your time with this detailed and informative book: it is the perfect guide to this spectacular region of old castles, fascinating lochs and a wonderful coast.</sentence>
<sentence>The land is full of history while the beautiful views are an attraction to any visitor.</sentence>
</page>
<page id='122'>
<chapter>6/B</chapter>
<exercise>B1 a) Emma is planning to go to Glasgow to visit her cousin. Use the map at the front of your book to find out how far Glasgow is from London.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the websites on this page. Look at the different means of travel and compare the prices and the travelling times. LiF 8R: Comparison, p.160</exercise>
<exercise>It’s cheaper/more expensive to go by … ∙ … is much faster than … ∙</exercise>
<exercise>Flights to Glasgow</exercise>
<exercise>Cheapest fares to Glasgow (one-way) Average flight time: 1 h 10 min</exercise>
<exercise>£ 53</exercise>
<gap>The trip takes much longer by … than by … £ 45 £ 45 £ 45 £ 45</gap>
<exercise>June July August September October</exercise>
<exercise>c) Discuss which way of travelling you think is best for Emma. Wordbank: Places, p.175, Travel, p.177</exercise>
<exercise>Find</exercise>
<gap>Emma might want to travel by …</gap>
<gap>Perhaps she would prefer going by … because …</gap>
<gap>But maybe she should/shouldn’t …</gap>
<exercise>London Glasgow startingat £ 12</exercise>
<sentence>Getting from London to Glasgow by bus</sentence>
<sentence>You can get from London to Glasgow (or Glasgow to London) on the National Express coaches.</sentence>
<sentence>The journey takes 8 hours and 20 minutes on the quickest direct buses.</sentence>
<sentence>Travelling by National Express is the cheapest way to get from London to Glasgow with NX funfare tickets, which are very cheap tickets, starting at £12 one-way.</sentence>
<sentence>There are up to 6 coaches a day between London Victoria Coach Station (Buckingham Palace Road) and Glasgow Buchanan Bus Station (Killermont Street).</sentence>
<sentence>There are three direct London-Glasgow buses a day (each way), while the other coaches are indirect National Express services via Birmingham (1 change).</sentence>
<exercise>fastdirectrail.com</exercise>
<exercise>1. Journey details 2. Train times 3. Choose seats 4. Get tickets 5. Payment</exercise>
<exercise>Return from London to Glasgow Central</exercise>
<exercise>Out Wednesday 1 July London Euston EUS to Glasgow Central GLC</exercise>
<exercise>Return Tuesday 14 July Glasgow Central GLC to London Euston EUS</exercise>
<exercise> Earlier Later  Depart EUS 11:30 EUS 12:30 EUS 13:30 GLC 09:40 GLC 10:00 GLC 10:40 GLC 11:40 Arrive GLC 16:01 GLC 17:05 GLC 18:01 EUS 14:13 EUS 15:05 EUS 15:16 EUS 16:12</exercise>
<exercise>Duration 4h 31m 4h 35m 4h 33m 5h 05m 4h 36m 4h 32m</exercise>
<exercise>Changes 0 i 1 i</exercise>
<exercise>Cheapest Standard Single £56.00 £29.50 £43.50 £56.00 £29.50</exercise>
<exercise>118 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>From</exercise>
<exercise>to</exercise>
</page>
<page id='123'>
<chapter>6/B</chapter>
<exercise>B2 Match the words and the explanations. P11 WB B1, p.100</exercise>
<exercise>B3 L2/11 a) Listen to Emma and her mother. Note down their arguments in a grid. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>fare duration coach change trains via departure arrival single ticket return ticket</exercise>
<exercise>a comfortable bus for long journeys a ticket for the journey to Glasgow and back money you have to pay for a ticket time the journey takes one-way ticket going through a place on the way get off and take a different line time the train or plane leaves time the train or plane reaches its destination</exercise>
<gap>Emma MrsButler car … bus … train … plane …</gap>
<exercise>b) Say whose arguments you think are better. Give reasons. WB B2, p.101</exercise>
<exercise>B4 Talk to three people about travelling without your</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Where did you go and how did you get there?</exercise>
<exercise>B5 Remember what Emma and her mum talked about (B3). Speculate on what might happen to Emma on her journey.</exercise>
<exercise>Milling around, p.149 Wordbank Travel, p.177</exercise>
<exercise>B6 Target task v P2, P3, P9</exercise>
<gap>She could …</gap>
<exercise>Need help?</exercise>
<exercise>Look at pp.128-130.</exercise>
<gap>There might be …</gap>
<gap>She might …</gap>
<exercise>There are two different versions of what happens to Emma, story A (pp.</exercise>
<exercise>120/121) and story B (pp.</exercise>
<exercise>121/122).</exercise>
<exercise>Discuss which of the two stories you like better.</exercise>
<exercise>To be able to do that, follow the steps below:</exercise>
<exercise>1 One half of your class works on story A, and the other half works on story B. Read your story and find a heading for each part of it ( 1 to 4 ). Reading, p.142</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Sum up each part of the story in 3-4 exercises. ∙ Read through your summaries and highlight words or phrases that are important for the story. Note them down on your cue card, but leave</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Use a different card for each part of the story.</exercise>
<exercise>3 Edit your cue cards: Use your cue cards to tell your story to a partner who has worked on the same story. Give feedback to each other on any information that is missing and add it to your cue cards.</exercise>
<exercise>4 Find a partner who has worked on the other story. Use your cue cards to tell each other what happened to Emma in your version. These words and phrases may help you:</exercise>
<exercise>First … ∙ Then … ∙ When … ∙ Later that day … ∙ On the way to … ∙ At the airport … ∙ On the plane … ∙ In the end …</exercise>
<exercise>5 Discuss which version you like better. Explain your views. Speaking 3, p.141</exercise>
<exercise>WB B3-B6, pp.101-103</exercise>
<exercise>more interesting ∙ convincing ∙ exciting ∙ surprising ∙ …</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 119</footnote>
<exercise>parents.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ What did/didn’t you like about the trip?</exercise>
<exercise>2 Prepare cue cards: P4</exercise>
<exercise>Remember to use the present tense.</exercise>
<exercise>enough space so that it is easy to read them.</exercise>
</page>
<page id='124'>
<chapter>6/B</chapter>
<exercise>Story A</exercise>
<sentence>The Butlers arrived at the airport in time and found a space in the car park immediately.</sentence>
<sentence>Mrs Butler took Emma’s suitcase out of the car and they went to check in.</sentence>
<sentence>After check-in Emma was left with her rucksack.</sentence>
<sentence>Her mum went directly to the security gate with her.</sentence>
<sentence>“You never know how long it will take.</sentence>
<sentence>There may be long queues because it’s the beginning of the holidays.</sentence>
<sentence>Better to be on the safe side,” she said and hugged Emma.</sentence>
<sentence>“Got your rucksack? And your boarding pass?”</sentence>
<sentence>“Sure, Mum, don’t worry,“ Emma said, though she didn’t sound as confident as she would have liked.</sentence>
<sentence>When Emma got on the plane, she thought everybody was looking at her.</sentence>
<sentence>Of course there weren’t many seats left so she just had to sit in the nearest empty seat.</sentence>
    <sentence>Mrs Butler realized that Emma was a little nervous after all, so she gave her a big hug.</sentence>
<sentence>“I’m OK, Mum.” Emma said goodbye as she showed her boarding pass.</sentence>
<sentence>“Oh no,” she thought when she looked at the person next to her.</sentence>
<sentence>“What an unpleasant man.” If only she hadn’t been late.</sentence>
<sentence>The man turned towards Emma.</sentence>
<sentence>“Are you interested in the environment?” he asked, pointing at her WWF rucksack.</sentence>
<sentence>Her mum had told her to go to the gate immediately and wait there until she could get on the plane.</sentence>
<sentence>“That’s why I’m going to Glasgow.”</sentence>
<sentence>But there were so many interesting shops and she had a long time before boarding.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma had a look around the shops and suddenly she felt very much like an adult buying a magazine and some sweets, trying different perfumes and looking at clothes.</sentence>
<sentence>“Really?” Emma answered.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma was surprised to find out that the man was Mark Preston from British Television.</sentence>
<sentence>And then he told her all about The Green Gang, a BTV docusoap.</sentence>
<sentence>Suddenly, she heard her name: “Final call for Ms Emma Butler, please proceed to gate 17 immediately. The flight is closing.”</sentence>
<sentence>“There are so many ugly areas in our cities, places everyone hates and nobody looks after.”</sentence>
<sentence>It made Emma think of a place like that in Camden, with lots of litter and broken glass.</sentence>
<sentence>“And we bring in people who change those places and make them beautiful.”</sentence>
<sentence>Emma felt hot and cold – what if she missed the flight?</sentence>
<sentence>She looked up to find directions for the gate numbers and ran quickly to gate 17.</sentence>
<sentence>At the gate there was a flight attendant who was telling her to hurry.</sentence>
<sentence>Mark Preston got out his tablet computer and showed Emma pictures of the last episode where they had built a playground in an area where nobody wanted to go.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma felt herself go red.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma could see that he was really proud of the project.</sentence>
<sentence>It was just so embarrassing.</sentence>
<sentence>And then she couldn’t find her boarding pass.</sentence>
<sentence>She was sure she had put it in her rucksack.</sentence>
<sentence>“It’s there in your pocket, dear,” the flight attendant said in a friendly voice.</sentence>
<sentence>“Sounds fantastic,” she said.</sentence>
<sentence>“And now I’m going to Glasgow to find a place we can use to film one of the next episodes.</sentence>
<sentence>We want to bring lost places back to the community,” he added.</sentence>
<sentence>“Oh, thank you. I’m so sorry … We were here in time. I just didn’t …”</sentence>
<sentence>“It’s OK, just walk down and find a seat.”</sentence>
<sentence>Emma completely forgot the time.</sentence>
<sentence>How lucky she was to be in that particular seat.</sentence>
<exercise>120 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='125'>
<chapter>6/B</chapter>
<sentence>At Glasgow airport Emma felt very glad when she spotted her aunt and her cousin.</sentence>
<sentence>It was great to see them.</sentence>
<sentence>And she had something really interesting to tell them.</sentence>
<exercise>News | Sport Weather | TV Search</exercise>
<exercise>BTV 1 The Green Gang</exercise>
<exercise>Home | Episodes Galleries | Mark Preston</exercise>
<exercise>Birmingham Episode 7</exercise>
<gap>In this episode Mark Preston travels to Birmingham to find a place … Read more</gap>
<sentence>Next on Today 8 pm BTV 1</sentence>
<exercise>Story B</exercise>
<sentence>It didn’t go well from the start.</sentence>
<sentence>On the way to the airport they were in a traffic jam for more than an hour.</sentence>
<sentence>“We’ll be OK, dear,” Mrs Butler said, but Emma knew that her mother was just as worried as she was that she would miss her flight.</sentence>
<sentence>Then they couldn’t find a space in the car park, so Emma was certain the plane to Glasgow would leave without her.</sentence>
<sentence>In the end she got to the gate in time, but then it was one of those flights that made Emma almost feel sick.</sentence>
<sentence>She sat in her seat and wasn’t sure if the trip to Scotland was such a good idea anymore.</sentence>
<sentence>In Glasgow it didn’t take long to collect her suitcase, but when she went through the exit, Emma could only see her aunt Fiona and she felt disappointed again.</sentence>
<sentence>“Where’s Nick?” she asked.</sentence>
<sentence>“At home with his friends. You know his school has been very busy with Clean Glasgow,” her aunt explained.</sentence>
<sentence>“I know, he told me about the project … and I think it’s cool, but it’s a school project and it’s the holidays now,” Emma answered uncertainly.</sentence>
<sentence>“Well, Nick and his team are very busy planning new activities for next term.”</sentence>
<sentence>“He told me you’re interested in environmental projects yourself, aren’t you? So you can join them.” Emma felt disappointed.</sentence>
<sentence>Yes, she was interested in the environment, but she had thought Nick would be there to meet her.</sentence>
<sentence>After all, she had come all the way from London and she hadn’t seen Nick for ages.</sentence>
<sentence>Now he was with his team and she would be left on her own.</sentence>
</page>
<page id='126'>
<chapter>6/B</chapter>
<sentence>When she went into the room, there was Nick with two other boys and two girls.</sentence>
<sentence>Nick turned towards her.</sentence>
<sentence>“Hi, Nick, congratulations. I hear your school has been very successful in the Clean Glasgow project,” Emma said, trying to hide her frustration.</sentence>
<sentence>“Hi, Emma. I hope you had a good flight.”</sentence>
<sentence>Come and meet my friends.</sentence>
<sentence>“Emma is a very big supporter of green ideas,” Nick said to his friends.</sentence>
<sentence>“Maybe she can help us.”</sentence>
<sentence>They all talked to her at the same time and told Emma that their school was quite successful in the Clean Glasgow project: they had collected waste around the school and in the neighbourhood and they had thought about reducing waste and litter at school.</sentence>
    <sentence>There was also an initiative to offer healthier food in the cafeteria.</sentence>
<sentence>But what they actually wanted was something new, something different, something positive – like a school garden or planting apple trees outside the school …</sentence>
<sentence>Emma was thrilled.</sentence>
<sentence>She had wanted to do something different herself and now she was together with this group of friends who shared her view and wanted to act.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma tried to think of an idea.</sentence>
<sentence>Growing things might be good.</sentence>
<sentence>Suddenly Emma remembered a report she had seen.</sentence>
<sentence>“That’s it,” she said.</sentence>
<sentence>“Why don’t you try something like The Edible Bus Stop?”</sentence>
<sentence>An Urban Garden for Your Bus Stop</sentence>
<sentence>It was a small piece of empty land on Landor Road in the Lambeth section of London, as boring as the #322 bus stop it sat behind.</sentence>
<sentence>But last spring, a small group of people got together to take back the area.</sentence>
<sentence>They did a little guerrilla gardening and were able to start a proper garden, called the Edible Bus Stop.</sentence>
<sentence>If possible, they hope their idea will grow and grow, and not just down the #322 route.</sentence>
<sentence>“The what? The edible bus stop? With chocolate ice cream?” the girl with blonde hair laughed.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma laughed, too.</sentence>
<sentence>“No, really, it’s about using the bus stop areas and planting vegetables on them.”</sentence>
<sentence>“It’s a project in London and I think it’s been a great success.” Emma explained how the project helped people to make their area look nicer and feel it belonged to them.</sentence>
<sentence>“So they don’t vandalize it anymore.”</sentence>
<sentence>They all looked at Emma and she wasn’t sure what they thought of her suggestion.</sentence>
<sentence>But then one of the boys said enthusiastically: “Sounds cool.</sentence>
<sentence>Why don’t we check the Internet?</sentence>
<sentence>“There must be something, a video, or maybe they’ve got a website.”</sentence>
<sentence>Everyone got really excited.</sentence>
<sentence>“Yeah, let’s do that – and then we could try it out!</sentence>
<sentence>Make an ugly bus stop look like a little garden.</sentence>
<sentence>That would be a much better start than just project plans or posters, don’t you think?”</sentence>
<sentence>It was a crazy idea, but Nick liked it.</sentence>
<sentence>He was worried that it might seem wrong to start a project like that in secret, but maybe not.</sentence>
<sentence>So the next day they went to a garden centre to buy some flowers and vegetables that weren’t too expensive.</sentence>
<sentence>Later that night Nick, Emma and Nick’s friends started their first guerrilla gardening.</sentence>
<exercise>122 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='127'>
<chapter>6/C</chapter>
<exercise>C1 L 2/12 a) Before you listen to Emma, her cousin Nick and her aunt Fiona, look at the photos and speculate on what they may be talking about.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Listen again and explain what the photos show. You can find some of the place names on the map. Listening, p.138</exercise>
<exercise>c) Say what Emma’s and Nick’s plans are.</exercise>
<exercise>C2 v Extra " Project Choose:</exercise>
<exercise>Work together in a small group.</exercise>
<exercise>Imagine you had to prepare a tour of Glasgow.</exercise>
<exercise>Choose five places you would like to visit.</exercise>
<exercise>Prepare a poster and present it to your classmates.</exercise>
<exercise>Searching the Internet, p.143, Speaking 1, pp.139/140</exercise>
<exercise>WB C1, p.104 or:</exercise>
<exercise>Work together in a small group.</exercise>
<exercise>Imagine you had to prepare a class trip to Scotland.</exercise>
<exercise>Choose five places you would like to visit.</exercise>
<exercise>Prepare a poster and present it to your classmates.</exercise>
<exercise>Searching the Internet, p.143, Speaking 1, pp.139/140</exercise>
<exercise>WB C1, p.104</exercise>
<exercise>Loch Arkaig Mallaig</exercise>
<exercise>Fort William 1343 Ben Loch</exercise>
<exercise>Loch Lochy Castle</exercise>
<exercise>Loch Ericht 354</exercise>
<exercise>Drumochter</exercise>
<exercise>Killiecrankie</exercise>
<exercise>Shiel</exercise>
<exercise>Glencoe</exercise>
<exercise>Nevis</exercise>
<exercise>T u m m e l T a y Loch Rannoch 1214</exercise>
<exercise>Duart Castle</exercise>
<exercise>Oban</exercise>
<exercise>D o c h a r t</exercise>
<exercise>Loch Tay</exercise>
<exercise>Loch Earn</exercise>
<exercise>Jura</exercise>
<exercise>Loch Awe L o c h F y n e</exercise>
<exercise>Loch Katrine Doune</exercise>
<exercise>F o r t h Loch Stirling</exercise>
<exercise>Ardoch</exercise>
<exercise>S o u n d o f J</exercise>
<exercise>Greenock</exercise>
<exercise>Largs</exercise>
<exercise>Arran</exercise>
<exercise>Paisley</exercise>
<exercise>Glasgow Mother-</exercise>
<exercise>well C l y d e East</exercise>
<exercise>F i r t h o f C 25 50</exercise>
<exercise>Kilmarnock</exercise>
<exercise>Ayr Culzean N i t h Thornhill Girvan</exercise>
<exercise>dw 3</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 123</footnote>
<exercise>l y d e</exercise>
<exercise>u r a</exercise>
<exercise>K i</exercise>
<exercise>n t y r e</exercise>
<exercise>Cluny</exercise>
<exercise>Pass of</exercise>
<exercise>Pass of</exercise>
<exercise>L o c h L i n n h e</exercise>
<exercise>Castle</exercise>
<exercise>House</exercise>
<exercise>Lomond</exercise>
<exercise>Falkirk</exercise>
<exercise>Kilbride</exercise>
<exercise>km</exercise>
<exercise>Castle</exercise>
</page>
<page id='128'>
<chapter>6/C</chapter>
<exercise>C3 a) Read the leaflet about the Duke of Edinburgh’s Award (DofE). Find out what the programme is and how it works. Make notes in German.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Work with a partner. Imagine you wanted to convince people in your area to start a programme similar to the Duke of Edinburgh’s Award. Use your notes to write an informative text about the award in German. WB C2, p.105</exercise>
<sentence>What is the DofE all about?</sentence>
<sentence>The DofE programme is a real adventure from beginning to end.</sentence>
<sentence>It is not important who you are or where you’re from.</sentence>
<sentence>You just need to be between 14 and 24 years old and realize there’s more to life than sitting on a sofa.</sentence>
<sentence>You can do programmes at three levels, which, when completed, lead to a Bronze, Silver or Gold Duke of Edinburgh’s Award.</sentence>
<sentence>You achieve your Award by completing a personal programme of activities in four sections (five if you’re doing the Gold award) – Volunteering, Physical, Skills, Expedition and for Gold, a Residential.</sentence>
<sentence>Volunteering is all about making a difference to other people’s lives.</sentence>
<sentence>Getting off your sofa and spending time changing things for the better can be great fun.</sentence>
<sentence>From conservation to fundraising for your favourite charity or looking after animals, there’s a long list of the types of projects you can do.</sentence>
<sentence>You don’t need to be super fit or Olympic standard to achieve the Physical section – trying it and getting better is enough.</sentence>
<sentence>From hockey to dancing, rock climbing to swimming, wheelchair basketball to yoga – almost any dance, sport or fitness activity is possible.</sentence>
<sentence>You can join a team or do it on your own, concentrate on something you’re already doing or try something completely different – it’s your choice.</sentence>
<sentence>The Skills section is all about developing practical and social skills and personal interests.</sentence>
<sentence>From podcasting to playing a musical instrument, fine art to website design, there’s a long list of skills you can do.</sentence>
<sentence>Achieving your Award is an adventure from beginning to end and the Expedition section can give you some of your best memories!</sentence>
<sentence>From sailing along the Norfolk Broads to walking in Canada or horse-riding in the Brecon Beacons, it can be as far away from or as close to home as you want it to be.</sentence>
<sentence>You can also choose how you want to travel – it doesn’t just have to be on foot!</sentence>
<exercise>124 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
</page>
<page id='129'>
<chapter>6/C</chapter>
<exercise>2 3</exercise>
<sentence>Scotland by bike</sentence>
<exercise>Loch Arkaig Loch Lochy Loch Arkaig Loch Lochy</exercise>
<exercise>MountainCamp</exercise>
<sentence>How to Start a Blog</sentence>
<exercise>Article Edit Dicsuss</exercise>
<sentence>I guess I’ll use the Internet andmaps and books about walking in Scotland.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’ll ask my dad and some of his friends, who often go to the Highlands.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’m going to join a group of boys and girls who I’ll meet at Snowgoose Mountain Camp near Fort William.</sentence>
    <sentence>We’re going to take a route around the mountains north of the camp to Loch Arkaig and then around Loch Lochy before we hike back.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’ve never been on such a long hiking trip, definitely not camping at night as well.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’m not sure how easy it will be up there in the Highlands.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’ve never hiked for longer than a few hours and I’ve only just started reading maps and using them to help me find my way.</sentence>
    <sentence>I also hope I can learn how to use a GPS before we start the hike.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’d like to show that I can do a route like this – even as a teenager.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’m really keen to get to know the Scottish countryside.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’d like to do longer routes later so that I can learn more about the environment.</sentence>
    <sentence>We ought to try to clean up some of the rubbish that tourists leave behind.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’ve been in touch with a teacher at my school who does DofE with students every year.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’ve also been in contact with the people at Snowgoose Mountain Centre.</sentence>
    <sentence>Dave, one of their guides, is going to come with us on the tour.</sentence>
    <sentence>I’ll probably combine photos and descriptions on a special blog website.</sentence>
</page>
<page id='130'>
<chapter>6/C</chapter>
<exercise>C5 v Extra: Viewing: Expedition tips Some young people who do the Duke of Edinburgh’s Award make</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Watch two clips about tips for an expedition. Take notes on how useful the tips are.</exercise>
<exercise>Viewing, p.139 LiF 8R, 9: Comparison, p.160</exercise>
<exercise>C6 Write down tips for trips in the Scottish Highlands. LiF 24R: Modal verbs, pp.172/173 P5 WB C3, p.105</exercise>
<exercise>When you walk along a road, The weather can change very quickly, so There are no shops in the mountains, so When you have finished any food or drink, There are certain paths which If you have the right equipment, The paths can be hard to follow, so</exercise>
<exercise>you needn’t you should you ought to you have to you can’t you may not you mustn’t</exercise>
<exercise>remember to take some extra clothes.</exercise>
<exercise>walk on the right-hand side of the road.</exercise>
<exercise>use your map.</exercise>
<exercise>only go there in the summer months.</exercise>
<exercise>leave your litter on the ground.</exercise>
<exercise>buy food when you are hungry.</exercise>
<exercise>use when the weather is bad.</exercise>
<exercise>C7 Grammar card: modal verbs Look at the modal verbs from C6. Add any new ones to your grammar card on modal verbs. Check LiF 24R (pp. 172/173) for help. P10</exercise>
<exercise>Support Remember that there are substitute forms like be allowed to for certain modal verbs.</exercise>
<exercise>C8 At the weekend, Nick and Emma start their expedition. Dave, their guide, and Nick’s friends Jamie, Tim, Tessa and Louise are with them. a) Look at the different materials on page 127.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Put the materials into the correct order so that you know when everything happened.</exercise>
<exercise>b) Read the materials again and say</exercise>
<exercise>∙ what the highlights of the expedition were.</exercise>
<exercise>c) Discuss if you would like to organize and/or take part in such an expedition. Think – pair – share, p.149 P6, P7</exercise>
<exercise>C9 a) Study the materials on page 127 again. Note down words and phrases that express positive or negative feelings, e.g. simply amazing, I was beginning to feel really worried .</exercise>
<exercise>b) Say how Nick, Dave, Emma and Fiona feel when they write their messages/blog entries. Wordbank People, p.174</exercise>
<exercise>c) Take a closer look at the texts from Nick’s blog (materials B and C). He uses different methods to make his writing as interesting as possible and include his view of the events.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ adverbs to make a point stronger, e.g. really ∙ a clause that is used to comment on the rest of the exercise, e.g. what made me more</exercise>
<exercise>I would/wouldn’t like to take part in … ∙ Organizing such an expedition seems very challenging … ∙ I’m not so sure about …</exercise>
<exercise>∙ exclamations, e.g. Poor Louise! WB C4, p.106</exercise>
<exercise>126 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
<exercise>videos of their preparations and activities and post them online.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Decide which clip seems more useful and explain why you think so.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Sum up each message or blog entry in your</exercise>
<exercise>own words.</exercise>
<exercise>Working with words 3, p.146</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Check your order with a partner’s.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ what went wrong and</exercise>
<exercise>Find examples of the following:</exercise>
<exercise>worried ,</exercise>
<gap>angry was …,</gap>
</page>
<page id='131'>
<chapter>6/C</chapter>
<sentence>Nick called. There seems to be some trouble – they couldn’t do the hike as planned.</sentence>
<sentence>Tim had an accident and had to go back.</sentence>
<sentence>Now they are taking an easier route.</sentence>
<sentence>Nick was a bit upset, but Emma sounded relieved.</sentence>
<sentence>Please leave your mobile on.</sentence>
<sentence>If they end the expedition, we might have to pick them up. CU L8R, Fiona</sentence>
    <sentence>I thought we would never start.</sentence>
<sentence>Emma and I were here early – thank you, Mum!</sentence>
<sentence>There weren’t any traffic jams on the way up here from Glasgow.</sentence>
<sentence>I was beginning to get really worried when the others arrived – two hours late!!!</sentence>
<sentence>I asked myself: Why so late?</sentence>
<sentence>There’s only one road up here.</sentence>
<sentence>What made me more angry was that they didn’t really seem to care.</sentence>
<sentence>At that point I already knew that we might not get to where we wanted to be for the night.</sentence>
<sentence>All that planning and then that!</sentence>
    <sentence>Send rescue team.</sentence>
<sentence>Boy slipped on the way up the first hill, just a mile from the centre in the direction of Loch Arkaig on the blue route.</sentence>
<sentence>Maybe broken ankle. Dave</sentence>
    <sentence>Just wanted 2 let U know that everything is fine now.</sentence>
<sentence>We took an easy route (I’m quite happy about that!) &amp; have just put up the tents 4 the night.</sentence>
<sentence>Dave, our guide, is really cool.</sentence>
<sentence>He managed to calm Nick down &amp; knows lots of old Scottish stories.</sentence>
<sentence>He’s from the Isle of Skye (no idea where that is) &amp; is even trying to teach us some Gaelic. Bye, Emma</sentence>
<exercise>C10 Target task v Portfolio P8 Need help? Look at pp.130-132.</exercise>
<exercise>∙ There are some things missing from Nick’s blog. Complete his blog about the expedition. Write at least two more entries. Writing, pp.144/145 WB C5, p.107</exercise>
<exercise>∙ Write Emma’s personal report about the hiking trip for her school magazine. Writing, pp.144/145 WB C5, p.107</exercise>
<exercise>Support ∙ Use the information about the expedition ∙ Use expressions from C9a) or similar phrases. ∙ To make the blog/report more personal you can add more details that fit.</exercise>
<footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo Page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words 127</footnote>
<sentence>Dave really saved the expedition.</sentence>
<sentence>As we didn’t take the route I had planned, there wasn’t really much hiking to do on the second day.</sentence>
<sentence>So Dave surprised us all with an extra activity to cheer us up.</sentence>
<sentence>He called the centre and had some canoes brought up to the lake.</sentence>
<sentence>So we went paddling on the loch, which was simply amazing.</sentence>
<sentence>The weather was perfect, too, although I got a little sunburnt.</sentence>
<sentence>But you need a lot of power and energy for canoeing so we were all exhausted when we got back on land.</sentence>
<sentence>Of course, there had to be another accident on the lake.</sentence>
<sentence>Everyone was already paddling in their canoes when Louise fell into the water. Poor Louise!</sentence>
<exercise>∙ Use the strategies from C9c).</exercise>
</page>
</document>