<document>
    <page id='2'>
        <chapter>1/A</chapter>
        <exercise>A1 a) Write down as many holiday words as you can. You have got one minute. Who has got the most
            words?
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Organize your words in a word web. P1  WB A1, p. 4</exercise>
        <exercise>places to go</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>HOLIDAY</exercise>
        <exercise>activities</exercise>
        <exercise>weather</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>A2 L 1/1 a) The friends are back from holiday.</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <gap>Look at their souvenirs. Say …</gap>
        <exercise>∙ … who brought them back</exercise>
        <gap>There is …/There are …</gap>
        <gap>I think this is Rajiv’s souvenir because he went to … /spent his holiday at/in …</gap>
        <exercise>b) Listen to the friends and complete the grid. Were you right in a)?</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Decide which of the friends’ holidays you like best and say why.</exercise>
        <exercise>souvenir whose?</exercise>
        <exercise>where from?</exercise>
        <exercise>Isle of Lewis Beam House Birmingham Thorpe Park</exercise>
        <gap>I think Caroline had a …</gap>
        <gap>I like Emma’s holiday best because …</gap>
        <gap>great time because …</gap>
        <exercise>July 11 10:40</exercise>
        <exercise>10 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … what they are</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … where they are from.</exercise>
        <exercise>ten</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='2'>
        <chapter>1/A</chapter>
        <exercise>A3 Target task v " Project Prepare a collage about your holidays and present it.</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at pp.</exercise>
        <exercise>20/21.</exercise>
        <exercise>Last year, your teacher asked you to collect souvenirs and/or write a postcard from your holidays (or
            your home town).
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 Work in groups of four. Put all your souvenirs and postcards on a table.</exercise>
        <sentence>Did you have a good holiday?</sentence>
        <sentence>That sounds great.</sentence>
        <sentence>Oh, that’s too bad.</sentence>
        <sentence>Why didn’t you like it?</sentence>
        <exercise>Every pupil says something about his/her holiday and souvenir.</exercise>
        <exercise>The others ask questions to find out more.</exercise>
        <exercise>Where did you stay?</exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 2R: Simple past, p. 136 P2-P5, P14  WB A2, A3, p. 4, 5 How long did you stay?</exercise>
        <listing>What did you do? had a wonderful/exciting holiday went to Spain · stayed at home · went camping · …
        </listing>
        <listing>stayed with my grandparents · went to the beach · … It was warm/cold/sunny/rainy/cloudy/foggy/snowy/…
            stayed for a week/two weeks/a weekend/…
        </listing>
        <sentence>Where did you find this souvenir?</sentence>
        <gap>I found/bought the souvenir …</gap>
        <exercise>2 Together prepare a collage about your holidays and present it to another group. Speaking 1, p. 126
            Wordbank Weather, p. 149
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Support ∙ Practise your presentation. ∙ Look at page 126 for more tips.</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Give the other group some feedback. Don’t forget to say something positive first.</exercise>
        <exercise>Speaking 2, p. 127</exercise>
        <sentence>Your presentation was easy to understand and you spoke clearly.</sentence>
        <sentence>Your poster looks neat and tidy but you should speak up more.</sentence>
        <sentence>Your presentation was fun to listen to/ really interesting.</sentence>
        <sentence>Your poster looks attractive but it could be a bit more informative.</sentence>
        <sentence>Greetings from the Isle of Lewis</sentence>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words eleven 11</footnote>
        <exercise>∙ Speak up.</exercise>
        <exercise>w i s s s s s</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='3'>
        <chapter>1/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B1 L 1/2 a) Think of Caroline’s holiday. Where did she go? What did she do? What was her souvenir?
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Close your books and listen to Gillian and Emma. What are they talking about?</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Read the dialogue and answer the questions to get all the information about Emma and Caroline’s
            holiday. Note down your answers.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ What did they do/happened?  WB B1, p. 5</exercise>
        <sentence>After the holidays Gillian and Emma meet at Westfield Shopping Centre.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Hi Emma, where’s Caroline? Isn’t she coming?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Hi Gill. No, she’s writing an email to Sophie, her friend from Manchester.</sentence>
        <sentence>She wants to tell her all about the pony camp in Wales.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Oh, the pony camp. Did you like it?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Yes, it was great! I had the cutest pony!</sentence>
        <sentence>His name was Donald. He was as white as snow.</sentence>
        <sentence>He really was the prettiest pony of them all.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: So, what did you do at the pony camp?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: We really had a lovely time: we cleaned the stables and went for rides.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was so much fun! We want to go again next year.</sentence>
        <sentence>Hey, why don’t you come with us?</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Well, I really like animals but I don’t think I’m a country person.</sentence>
        <sentence>There are no shops and no cinemas in the country.</sentence>
        <sentence>And London is much more exciting than Wales.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Well, there are some shops, but they’re only small ones.</sentence>
        <sentence>The shops in London are bigger, of course. But it was nice to be in the country.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: But wasn’t it a bit boring?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: No, there was so much to do.</sentence>
        <sentence>One day we had a barbecue. And then there was the pony race.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Caroline won the race, right?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Well … yes, you could say so. The funniest thing happened!</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Why was it funny?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Well, after the start Donald suddenly stopped and I fell off. It was terrible!</sentence>
        <sentence>I think a mouse scared him.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline rode Daisy.</sentence>
        <sentence>At first two other ponies, Lionheart and Princess, were faster than Daisy, but then they both went the wrong way.</sentence>
        <sentence>Nobody could stop them.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: No way!</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Yes, and the story gets even funnier!</sentence>
        <sentence>Only Olivia and Caroline were left.</sentence>
        <sentence>Olivia was really better than Caroline.</sentence>
        <sentence>But her pony suddenly stopped, too, so Caroline came first.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: So, Caroline won the race because she was the only one left?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Yes, but don’t tell anyone, please!</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: OK.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Come on, let’s go shopping – I think I missed shopping a bit after all.</sentence>
        <exercise>12 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Where did they go?</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ When did they go?</exercise>
        <exercise>twelve</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='4'>
        <chapter>1/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B2 Gillian wants to tell her dad about the pony race. Complete her email and use these words and
            phrases to structure your text:
        </exercise>
        <listing>First … · Then … · Next … · In the end …</listing>
        <exercise>B3 Gillian said, “I don’t think I’m a country person”. Are you a country or a city person? Why? Talk
            to a partner. Wordbank In the country; city p. 149, 151
        </exercise>
        <exercise>To: jfcollins@inter.net.co.uk Hello!</exercise>
        <sentence>Hi Dad, How are you?</sentence>
        <sentence>I went to Westfield today and met Emma for some shopping.</sentence>
        <sentence>She went to a pony farm with her parents and Caroline in the holidays.</sentence>
        <sentence>She told me about a really funny pony race: first …</sentence>
        <sentence>Love Gillian xxx</sentence>
        <exercise>B4 Grammar detective: comparison of adjectives</exercise>
        <exercise>‘small – small er – small est ’ ‘exciting – more exciting – most exciting’ Can you solve this
            puzzle?
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 Copy the grid. Look at B1 and fill in the grid.</exercise>
        <gap>adjective comparative superlative cuter …</gap>
        <exercise>2 Find more examples from B1. What is the rule? When do you have to be careful with the spelling?
        </exercise>
        <exercise>prett y exciting big</exercise>
        <gap>prett ier … …</gap>
        <gap>… most exciting biggest</gap>
        <exercise>3 Look at LiF 3 on page 137 for help and write a grammar card. Add the comparative and superlative
            forms of good and bad to your grammar card. P11  WB B2, p. 6
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Emma and Gillian bought a lot of things at Westfield Shopping Centre.</sentence>
        <exercise>Look at them and compare
            them.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>cheap ∙ expensive ∙ interesting ∙ cool ∙ big ∙ delicious ∙ cute ∙ nice ∙ good</exercise>
        <gap>Support … as long as … / … as expensive as … … longer than … / … more expensive than … … the longest … /
            …the most expensive …
        </gap>
        <exercise>Example: The scarf is cheaper than the T-shirt.</exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 3: Steigerung von Adjektiven, p. 137/138  WB B3, p. 6</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirteen 13</footnote>
    </page>
    <page id='5'>
        <chapter>1/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B6 v Extra: Viewing: Adventure holidays KG organizes adventure holidays for children. George went on
            holiday with KG to Beam House.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>a) Read the sentences. Then watch the advert and say which sentences are right and which are wrong.
        </exercise>
        <sentence>At the summer camp there is a river where you can go kayaking.</sentence>
        <sentence>You can go horse-riding on a KG holiday.</sentence>
        <sentence>KG holidays are for boys only.</sentence>
        <sentence>You can come to KG camps for a day, a week or a school holiday.</sentence>
        <sentence>There are pupils from different countries, e.g. from Germany.</sentence>
        <sentence>You can choose which activities you would like to do in the morning and in the afternoon.</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Work with a partner. Are you interested in a KG holiday? Say why/why not.</exercise>
        <exercise>B7 L 1/3 George told his friends everything about his holiday at Beam House – except one thing. Read
            the story and find out.  WB B4, p. 7
        </exercise>
        <sentence>George loved Beam House.</sentence>
        <sentence>He likes action and at Beam House you get a lot of that.</sentence>
        <sentence>On his first day he went surfing and abseiling.</sentence>
        <sentence>The next day, he went on the zip wire after breakfast.</sentence>
        <sentence>Later he also took some cool photos of the older kids doing motorsports on the quad bikes.</sentence>
        <sentence>At five o’clock everyone at Beam House met to go orienteering.</sentence>
        <sentence>In George’s group were Brady, Anna and Claire.</sentence>
        <sentence>The instructor gave them a map.</sentence>
        <sentence>They had to use a compass to find a treasure box and get back to Beam House as fast as possible.</sentence>
        <sentence>The girls were very excited.</sentence>
        <sentence>First Claire took the compass and started to walk towards the woods while Anna, Brady and George followed.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Walking around with a compass doesn’t sound like a lot of fun,” George thought, “but if I have to
            take part, I want to win.”</sentence>
        <sentence>After ten minutes of walking he asked Claire, “Are you sure you know where we’re going?”</sentence>
        <sentence>“Why?” she asked.</sentence>
        <sentence>“I just wanted to check because I can see the river from here and the mark on the map is in the opposite direction.” </sentence>
        <sentence>“If you think you can do a better job, here you go!” Claire gave George the compass and looked at him
            angrily.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Hey, calm down! We’re a team, remember?” said Brady.</sentence>
        <sentence>“OK then, let’s go,” George answered and turned round.</sentence>
        <sentence>The others followed him.</sentence>
        <sentence>However, while Anna and Brady talked and laughed, Claire didn’t say a word.</sentence>
        <sentence>They walked through the woods for twenty minutes.</sentence>
        <sentence>Everything seemed OK until George looked at the map again.</sentence>
        <sentence>Suddenly he wasn’t sure about the right direction anymore and he became nervous.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Do you need help?” Brady asked.</sentence>
        <sentence>“No, no, it’s OK,” said George.</sentence>
        <sentence>He didn’t want to ask Brady for help in front of the girls.</sentence>
        <sentence>He almost started to run and the others followed.</sentence>
        <sentence>“George, stop!” Anna finally shouted.</sentence>
        <sentence>“I can see a hill over there. I think we’re lost!“</sentence>
        <exercise>14 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <sentence>fourteen</sentence>
    </page>
    <page id='6'>
        <chapter>1/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B8 What do you think happens next? Use a grid to organize your ideas.  WB B5, p. 8</exercise>
        <gap>What? Who? Where? When? …</gap>
        <exercise>B9 It is easier to read a story that has a clear structure. Read the story in B7 again and make a list
            of phrases or words you can use ∙ to connect sentences (e. g. and, but ) P6-P8  WB B6, p. 8
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B10 Target task v Portfolio Finish the story from B7. You can make it funny, scary or exciting.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 Plan your story and use your ideas from B8. Writing, p. 128</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Structure your story and make it interesting. LiF 2R: Simple past, p. 135; LiF 4: Connectives, p.
            138
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 Swap your story with a partner’s. Use the checklist and give your partner feedback. Speaking 2, p.
            127
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at pp.</exercise>
        <exercisence>21/22.</exercisence>
        <exercise>3 connectives (e.g. so, but, …) 3 structure words (e.g. first, then, …) 3 direct speech (e.g. “Why?”
            answered Claire.) 3 adjectives, comparatives and superlatives (e.g. exciting, the scariest thing that …)
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Your story is great but you need to add more direct speech to make it more interesting.</sentence>
        <sentence>I like your story but you can use more words like ‘because’ or ‘but’ to connect your sentences.</sentence>
        <sentence>Your story is really good but you can make it more interesting by using different adjectives.</sentence>
        <exercise>4 Gallery walk: Hang up your stories in the classroom. Choose three of your classmates’ stories and
            read them. Which one is your favourite and why? Gallery walk, p. 130  WB B7, p. 9
        </exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</footnote>
        <exercise>fi fteen</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ to structure a story (e. g. on his first day, the next day )</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='7'>
        <chapter>1/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C1 a) It is the first day after the holidays at William Ellis School.</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at the picture and say why Mrs Brogden is angry.</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Think – pair – share:</exercise>
        <gap>Some boys are sitting …</gap>
        <exercise>What can make your teachers angry?</exercise>
        <exercise>Collect ideas and choose the top 5 things that can get you into trouble at school.</exercise>
        <exercise>Think – pair – share, p. 130  WB C1, C2, p. 10</exercise>
        <exercise>C2 L 1/4 a) On the first day of school Rajiv takes his new mobile phone with him. Listen to what he
            records with it. Find out what happens to him.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Speculate on what happens next to George and Rajiv.</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Read how Mr Jackson, their teacher, and Mrs Edwards, the head teacher, talk to George and Rajiv.
            Were you right in b)? P15
        </exercise>
        <gap>I think they must …</gap>
        <gap>I guess they …</gap>
        <sentence>Mrs Edwards: Rajiv, George, please sit down.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mr Jackson told me what you did in his history lesson.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m really angry that you played with your mobile in Mr Jackson’s class.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv: I’m really sorry, Mr Jackson. It was a stupid mistake.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mrs Edwards: The school rules are very clear.</sentence>
        <sentence>Leave your mobiles at home or leave them in your bags. But you recorded parts of the lesson.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m really disappointed in you.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mr Jackson: You should learn about British history in my lessons, not about mobile phones.</sentence>
        <sentence>That was unacceptable.</sentence>
        <sentence>Why didn’t you leave your mobile at home?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv: We’re very sorry.</sentence>
        <sentence>It won’t happen again.</sentence>
        <sentence>All the others talked about their exciting summer holidays, but I stayed at home all the time.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>So I thought, why not talk about my new mobile?</sentence>
        <sentence>But now I know it was wrong to bring it to school.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: It was my mistake, really.</sentence>
        <sentence>I asked Rajiv to give me his mobile and I recorded the lesson.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was just a bit of fun.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mr Jackson: I don’t think so.</sentence>
        <sentence>Who knows what you wanted to do with those clips?</sentence>
        <sentence>Maybe you wanted to put them online.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv: No, really. We were a bit bored and it’s the first day back at school.</sentence>
        <sentence>So we had that stupid idea.</sentence>
        <sentence>But it wasn’t just George, it was my fault, too.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mrs Edwards: It’s good that you both see that you did something wrong.</sentence>
        <sentence>But I’m going to keep the mobile for the moment and I’m going to phone your parents.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mr Jackson and I agree that you should do something for history.</sentence>
        <sentence>As you didn’t follow the history lesson, you must prepare a presentation on the Romans and the Celts.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: The Romans and the Celts?</sentence>
        <sentence>Can’t we choose another topic?</sentence>
        <sentence>Mrs Edwards: No, you can’t. Work hard on your presentation. You may go now.</sentence>
        <exercise>16 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>sixteen</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='8'>
        <chapter>1/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C3 a) Look at C2 again and say how the people feel.</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Look at C2 again.</exercise>
        <exercise>Mr Jackson Mrs Edwards George Rajiv</exercise>
        <exercise>feels is</exercise>
        <gap>sad disappointed angry happy very angry sorry …</gap>
        <gap>that … because …</gap>
        <exercise>Start a grid and collect phrases that express</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … someone feels sorry for what he/she did</exercise>
        <exercise>something wrong P16, P12  WB C3 –C5, p. 11, 12</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Write down how you can feel when your … … teacher gives you a lot of/no extra homework … teacher
            asks you to write something on the board … teacher talks to your parents … teacher is late … classmates are
            noisy
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Look at C2 again and complete the exercises.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 The school rules say that pupils must … 2 Mr Jackson wants to know why … 3 George thinks it was just
            …
        </exercise>
        <exercise>4 Mrs Edwards is going to … 5 George and Rajiv must … 6 George wants to know if they can …</exercise>
        <exercise>C4 George calls his mother to tell her what happened. Work with a partner. Complete the dialogue – one
            of you is Mrs Lambraki and the other one is George. Add phrases from C3b) where possible. LiF 1R: Simple
            present, p. 133/134; 2R: Simple past, p. 135/136  WB C6, p. 13
        </exercise>
        <exercise>George: Hi, Mum. I should tell you about what happened at school today.</exercise>
        <exercise>Mrs Lambraki: Oh no, what did you …?</exercise>
        <exercise>George: I didn’t do anything. It was Rajiv.
            He …
        </exercise>
        <gap>And then I … Mrs Lambraki: Why …? George: Because we were bored. Mrs Lambraki: Oh George. Now what …
            next?
        </gap>
        <exercise>C5 v Extra a) Present your dialogues from C4 to another pair. Decide which of the two dialogues is
            better. Say why.
        </exercise>
        <gap>George: Well, we had to go to Mrs Edwards. Mr Jackson was there, too. What … when</gap>
        <gap>they called you? Mrs Lambraki: … And what …? George: Rajiv and I have to prepare a presentation about the
            Romans and Celts in
        </gap>
        <gap>Britain. … Mrs Lambraki: George, I’m really …! …</gap>
        <exercise>b) Present some good dialogues in class and discuss what makes them good dialogues. Think of what they
            are about and the language they use.
        </exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventeen 17</footnote>
        <gap>that …</gap>
        <exercise>∙ … someone does not like something</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … someone knows that he/she did</exercise>
        <exercise>c) v Choose</exercise>
        <exercise>or</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='9'>
        <chapter>1/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C6 A few days later George and Rajiv write notes to each other in their English lesson. a) Put them in
            the right order. What are the notes about? Reading, p. 125  WB C7, C8, p. 14
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Hi, Rajiv. What do you think about what Mr Jackson said?</sentence>
        <sentence>OK. Maybe we can make the presentation a little bit more interesting than a normal lesson.</sentence>
        <sentence>Maybe Charlie can help us.</sentence>
        <sentence>You’re right. Let’s ask Charlie for help.</sentence>
        <sentence>He’s good at history.</sentence>
        <sentence>We can talk about it at lunch.</sentence>
        <sentence>No way, George. We should show him that we are not as stupid as he thinks we are.</sentence>
        <sentence>Romans and Celts? I don’t know anything about them.</sentence>
        <sentence>They both sound boring to me.</sentence>
        <sentence>Good idea, but we could ask Mr Jackson for some ideas, too.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was better than I thought.</sentence>
        <sentence>I think it was good that we said sorry again.</sentence>
        <sentence>He wasn’t as angry as last lesson. But a presentation about Romans and Celts … not so sure.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>That’s true. They sound really boring.</sentence>
        <sentence>Let’s go to the library after lunch.</sentence>
        <sentence>Maybe we can find something that is more interesting than ‘Roman cities in England’.</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Look at the notes again and complete the sentences.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Rajiv thinks that Mr Jackson wasn’t … 2 The boys think that the Romans and Celts … 3 They want to go
            to the library to …
        </exercise>
        <exercise>c) Look at the notes again. Make a grid to collect phrases (how to agree/how to disagree). Then add
            more words/phrases to the grid. P10
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C7 L 1/5</exercise>
        <exercise>4 Rajiv doesn’t want to ask Mr Jackson</exercise>
        <gap>because … 5 The boys think that Charlie … because …</gap>
        <exercise>d) Look at your grid. Mark phrases you can only use with friends but not with teachers.</exercise>
        <exercise>a) Listen to Charlie’s tips and note down the tip you like best. Say why. P13</exercise>
        <gap>Charlie’s tip for/about… is my favourite because …</gap>
        <exercise>b) Listen again and complete the sentences with as … as … or … than … . LiF 3: Steigerung von
            Adjektiven, p. 137/138  WB C9, p. 15
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 A presentation about Romans is … one about Celts. 2 It is … to find material on the Romans … on the
            Celts. 3 The BBC websites often have … information … other websites and some books. 4 In the Horrible
            Histories books you can find pictures that are … pictures from
        </exercise>
        <gap>normal history books. 5 A presentation with those pictures is … without the pictures. 6 But maybe Mr
            Jackson doesn’t find it … the pupils.
        </gap>
        <exercise>18 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>eighteen</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='10'>
        <chapter>1/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C8 L 1/6 George and Rajiv are in the library to prepare their history presentation when there is an
            announcement over the PA system.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>a) Listen to the announcement. b) What do you think about what the pupils did?</exercise>
        <exercise>What does the head teacher say?</exercise>
        <exercise>Listening, p. 124</exercise>
        <exercise>C9 Target task v " Project Portfolio P9</exercise>
        <exercise>P17  WB C10, p. 15</exercise>
        <gap>I think/don’t think it’s OK if you …</gap>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <gap>What they did was stupid/silly/clever/cool/… because …</gap>
        <exercise>Write a dialogue between the two pupils from Year 8 and Mrs Edwards, the head teacher.</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at pp.</exercise>
        <exercise>22/23.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Work in groups of three. Choose one role and read your role card.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ What kind of person is he/she? ∙ What does he/she say?</exercise>
        <exercise>Wordbank People, p. 153</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Plan your dialogue. Use words and phrases from C3b) and C6).</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ is not very clever or polite ∙ doesn’t understand why the ∙ thinks the sweets at school are too
            expensive so that pupils want to buy sweets from him.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 Present your dialogue to another group.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Did the group use the language from C3b) and C6? Speaking 2, p. 127</exercise>
        <gap>Support Giving feedback: Patrick was very good as Salman/Matt because he … I don’t think Vanessa acted like
            the role card says because …
        </gap>
        <exercise>∙ is very angry that the boys started their own</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ wants to find out about the details</exercise>
        <exercise>they did.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ understands that he did something wrong but doesn’t see why selling</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ saved the money for a new computer.</exercise>
        <gap>Jessica did not ask many questions as Mrs Edwards, but the role card says … Lisa’s questions as Mrs Edwards
            were very good because she asked about … I liked Jens as Salman/Matt because he said that it was …’s fault,
            too.
        </gap>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words nineteen 19</footnote>
        <exercise>Think about your character:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ How does he/she feel?</exercise>
        <exercise>Mrs Edwards</exercise>
        <exercise>Matt Hickman</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ is always in trouble</exercise>
        <exercise>business</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ wants to punish them for what</exercise>
        <exercise>head teacher is angry</exercise>
        <exercise>Salman Amin</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ is a good, polite pupil</exercise>
        <exercise>Give feedback.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Were the characters convincing?</exercise>
        <exercise>sweets is such a big problem</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='21'>
        <chapter>2/A</chapter>
        <sentence>Festivals around the year</sentence>
        <sentence>Chinese New Year</sentence>
        <sentence>Gung Hei Fat Choi! That is ’Happy New Year!’ in Chinese.</sentence>
        <sentence>Our New Year’s Day is not on January 1st but in late January or in February.</sentence>
        <sentence>Then we clean our houses, decorate them with fruit and flowers and put up red and gold banners with
            short poems in the house because they bring good luck.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Parents give their children red envelopes with money in them and we eat special food like dumplings or
            rice pudding.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Many people watch the famous dragon dance because we Chinese believe that dragons are friendly.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>We also have fireworks that make a lot of noise to keep the monsters and bad luck away.</sentence>
        <exercise>Diwali A1 a) Think of three special days that</exercise>
        <sentence>In October or November Hindu people celebrate Diwali – the Festival of Lights.</sentence>
        <sentence>My family and I often go to Diwali in Trafalgar Square.</sentence>
        <sentence>Many groups dance there and perform stories about Diwali.</sentence>
        <sentence>Diwali is also a celebration for Lakshmi, the goddess of good luck and wealth.</sentence>
        <sentence>We put diyas – small lamps – and candles around our houses to help the goddess Lakshmi find her way into people’s houses.</sentence>
        <sentence>We also give each other presents for Diwali, send cards and eat a lot of delicious sweets and cakes.</sentence>
        <sentence>But the best thing about Diwali is the fireworks!</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Talk about these special days with a partner. P1</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Make a list of the special days and celebrations in class. When do they take place over the year? 
            WB A1, p. 23
        </exercise>
        <exercise>d) v Extra: Do you know any special celebrations in Britain or other English-speaking countries? Say
            what you know about them and add them to the list from c).
        </exercise>
        <exercise>30 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>thirty</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='22'>
        <chapter>2/A</chapter>
        <sentence>Bonfire Night</sentence>
        <sentence>Remember, remember, the fifth of November!</sentence>
        <sentence>On November 5th 1605 Guy Fawkes and a group of men tried to blow up the Houses of Parliament in London
            to kill King James I.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>But their plan did not work.</sentence>
        <sentence>When people found out that the king was safe, they lit bonfires to celebrate.</sentence>
        <sentence>It is now a tradition to celebrate this event with fireworks and a bonfire.</sentence>
        <sentence>In the past, children made dummies of Guy Fawkes to ask people for ‘a penny for the Guy’.</sentence>
        <sentence>As it is usually cold in November, we have food that keeps us warm, like baked potatoes.</sentence>
        <sentence>But marshmallows and toffee apples are everyone’s favourite food on Bonfire Night!</sentence>
        <exercise>A2 The pupils at William Ellis present some celebrations for a school project. a) Mini jigsaw: Work in
            groups of three. Each group member reads about one of the festivals. Copy the grid and fill it in for ‘your’
            festival. Mini jigsaw, p. 130 Reading, p. 125
        </exercise>
        <gap>Chinese New Year Diwali Bonfi re Night When do people celebrate? What/Why do people celebrate? What do
            people do/wear/…?
        </gap>
        <exercise>b) Present what you know about the celebrations to your group. Complete your grid with information
            about the other celebrations.
        </exercise>
        <gap>Support … is a holiday that … celebrate every year at … The reason why they celebrate … is that … It is a
            holiday that is famous for …
        </gap>
        <exercise>c) Imagine you have the chance to take part in one of these celebrations. Which one would you choose?
            Why? P2, P3, P13  WB A2–A4, p. 23-25
        </exercise>
        <exercise>When you get the chance to go to these</exercise>
        <gap>celebrations, you should try … What is typical of that holiday is that …</gap>
        <exercise>A3 Target task v " Project Portfolio</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 40.</exercise>
        <exercise>Support</exercise>
        <exercise>Work with a partner.</exercise>
        <exercise>Design a page for a ‘special days’ calendar.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ a special day that you celebrate in your family or home town or</exercise>
        <exercise>celebrate, e.g.</exercise>
        <exercise>Hogmanay, St Patrick’s Day, Notting Hill Carnival.</exercise>
        <exercise>Find out as much as you can about your festival.</exercise>
        <exercise>Wordbank Festivals, p. 150 P8</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Plan your text so that your page answers ∙ If you use information from the Internet, make sure that
            your text is easy to read
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Include photos/pictures.</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-one 31</footnote>
        <exercise>Choose:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ a special day that British or other English-speaking people</exercise>
        <exercise>the questions from the grid in A2a).</exercise>
        <exercise>and understand.</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='23'>
        <chapter>2/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B1 L 1/11 Caroline and Emma are watching a video. It is of a celebration they had last year. Listen to
            the sounds. Which celebration is it? How did you find out? Listening, p. 124  WB B1, p. 26
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B2 L 1/12 a) Look at the card on Charlie’s desk. What is it about?</exercise>
        <exercise>b) There is a message on Charlie’s mobile phone. Listen to it and find out what his problem is.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B3 L 1/13 a) What do you have to organize before you can have a party? Wordbank Festivals, p. 150
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Close your books. Listen and find out what the girls are talking about.  WB B2, p. 26</exercise>
        <sentence>Caroline, Emma and Gillian are in Caroline’s room.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Let me just check our list.</sentence>
        <sentence>OK, I’m going to ask Mum and Dad to buy some fireworks for us.</sentence>
        <sentence>Some rockets and some bangers, of course.</sentence>
        <sentence>George is crazy about bangers – the noisier, the better.</sentence>
        <sentence>And we should get some sparklers for everyone.</sentence>
        <sentence>What do you think?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Well, it wouldn’t be much fun without the boys … so let them have their bangers.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Really, Emma. I didn’t know you were so interested in boys.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Well, some of them are quite OK, you know.</sentence>
        <sentence>Now, back to the list – we’re going to have a party next weekend, remember?</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: OK, Miss Bossyboots.</sentence>
        <sentence>So, what food are we going to have?</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Well, Emma is going to bring toffee apples.</sentence>
        <sentence>And I can ask Mum to make some of her delicious Greek snacks. What about you?</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: I’m going to go shopping with Mum on Friday so I can bring whatever you like.</sentence>
        <sentence>Why don’t we ask the others to bring some crisps and sweets, too?</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Great idea! But I already gave Charlie his invitation today.</sentence>
        <sentence>I know – we can text him about it.</sentence>
        <sentence>Now who else are we going to invite?</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Well, I don’t want to have a party with people I don’t like …</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: And I don’t want to have the same people all the time.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: I think the same people and that particular person Rick would be perfect!</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Stop it, Gillian!</sentence>
        <sentence>Mrs Lambraki: Caroline! Charlie’s on the phone.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Charlie? Are you sure he doesn’t want to talk to George?</sentence>
    </page>
    <page id='24'>
        <chapter>2/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B4 Read the dialogue in B3 again. Say how the girls feel and what they do. P9  WB B3, p. 27
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Emma Caroline Gillian</exercise>
        <exercise>seems is feels</exercise>
        <exercise>angry nervous annoyed nosy funny surprised bossy</exercise>
        <exercise>when because</exercise>
        <gap>she thinks of … she tells … she remembers … the other girls … Gillian … Caroline … …</gap>
        <exercise>B5 L 1/14 a) Close your books. Listen to Caroline and Charlie. How does Caroline react to Charlie’s
            news?
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Caroline: Hi, Caroline speaking.</sentence>
        <sentence>Charlie: Hi, Caroline, it’s Charlie.</sentence>
        <sentence>Thanks again for the invitation.</sentence>
        <sentence>It’s really great, but there’s a bit of a problem.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv just called and you’ll never guess what – he is planning a Diwali party the same night as your bonfire party.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Oh no! That’s awful.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m sure he’ll invite the same people as us.</sentence>
        <sentence>Charlie: Yeah, I think he’ll invite George, you, of course, and Emma and Gillian. Maybe Rick and a few others.</sentence>
        <sentence>I think he wants to show his non-Hindu friends what Diwali is about.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: That’s a great idea. I don’t know much about Diwali.</sentence>
        <sentence>But we have just finished planning our party. What a mess!</sentence>
        <sentence>Charlie: Yeah, well. I hope you’ll sort that problem out.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m sure both parties will be fantastic, but it won’t be possible for me to go to both of them.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Of course not. But maybe we can think of something.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma and Gillian are here, so I’ll talk to them first.</sentence>
        <sentence>Will you be at home later?</sentence>
        <sentence>Charlie: Yeah, you can call me here.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: OK then. Let’s talk later. Bye.</sentence>
        <exercise>3 Caroline hopes that she and the other girls will … 4 Caroline says that she will …  WB B4, B5, p.
            27, 28
        </exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-three 33</footnote>
    </page>
    <page id='25'>
        <chapter>2/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B6 Grammar card: will future You already know the going to future, but Caroline and Charlie use
            another tense to talk about the future – the will future . Start a grammar card for the will future .
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 Look at B5 on page 33 again. Note down examples of positive and negative sentences and questions.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 How do you form the will future ? Check LiF 6 on page 139.</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Look at B5 again and find phrases that introduce sentences with the will future . Example: I’m sure
            he’ll invite the same people as us. Now check LiF 6 on page 139 again. When do you use the will future ? P10
             WB B6, p. 29
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B7 a) What will happen next? Look at the pictures and write down if Caroline and Rajiv will do those
            things or not. Example: I guess Caroline will be angry and disappointed.
        </exercise>
        <gap>I think she’ll ask Rajiv if … LiF 6: will future, p. 139</gap>
        <gap>I guess she/he/they won’t … because …</gap>
        <gap>I don’t think she/he/they will … because …</gap>
        <gap>Maybe she/he/they … because …</gap>
        <exercise>b) Round Robin: Work in groups. What will happen next? Write a short statement. Round Robin, p. 130 
            WB B7, B8, p. 30
        </exercise>
        <exercise>34 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>thirty-four</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='26'>
        <chapter>2/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B8 a) Read Caroline’s email to Rajiv. Were you right in B7b)? Reading, p. 125</exercise>
        <sentence>Hi Rajiv, How are you?</sentence>
        <sentence>I don’t know if you already know, but we’ve got a problem.</sentence>
        <sentence>The girls and I are planning a party for November 5.</sentence>
        <sentence>We thought we could have a party at our house for Bonfire Night.</sentence>
        <sentence>But now Charlie tells me that you would like to have a Diwali party on the same night.</sentence>
        <sentence>I guess you’ll probably invite the same people as us.</sentence>
        <sentence>I talked to Emma and Gillian about it and we’ve got an idea, but I’m not sure that you’ll like it.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Don’t you think it would be a good idea to have just one party on that night?</sentence>
        <sentence>Why don’t we mix Bonfire Night and Diwali?</sentence>
        <sentence>There are fireworks for both festivals.</sentence>
        <sentence>What about one big party at our house?</sentence>
        <sentence>We’ve got enough room and Mum and Dad say it’s no problem.</sentence>
        <sentence>Let’s just celebrate in one place.</sentence>
        <sentence>I hope you won’t be upset about it.</sentence>
        <sentence>Please call or email back soon. Bye, Caroline</sentence>
        <exercise>b) What are Caroline’s arguments for a Diwali and Bonfire Night party? Note them down.</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Look at the structure of Caroline’s email. Where can you find the following parts?</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Saying hello 2 Introducing the email with a friendly question/sentence 3 Explaining why you are
            writing the email 4 Making suggestions 5 Finishing the email with a friendly statement 6 Saying goodbye P4,
            P5  WB B9, p. 31
        </exercise>
        <exercise>d) Find words and phrases for each part of the email. Example: Hi; How … Then collect more words and
            phrases in class.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B9 Target task v Portfolio Imagine you are Rajiv. Answer Caroline’s email.</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 40/41.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Before you start writing, decide how Rajiv feels about Caroline’s idea. What would he like to do?
            Note down your ideas.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 When you write the email, follow the structure from B8c).</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Use the will future when necessary. Wordbank Festivals, p. 150 Writing, p. 128 LiF 6: will future,
            p. 139
        </exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-fi ve 35</footnote>
        <exercise>∙ Use phrases from B8d) to write your email.</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='27'>
        <chapter>2/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C1</exercise>
        <gap>What makes a good party? There is good food. …</gap>
        <exercise>C2 L 1/15 a) Read the dialogue between Caroline and George. Find out what they and their friends
            expect of the party.
        </exercise>
        <sentence>George: Do we know how many people are actually coming to the party?</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Well, Emma’s coming, of course, and Gillian.</sentence>
        <sentence>And then some girls from my class, Sophie and Hamida.</sentence>
        <sentence>They’re really looking forward to it because there’ll be boys there!</sentence>
        <sentence>They haven’t got any brothers, you see!</sentence>
        <sentence>If you like, I’ll invite Denah, too.</sentence>
        <sentence>She’s really nice and she thinks you’re cool!</sentence>
        <sentence>George: If you invite her, I’ll never speak to you again!</sentence>
        <sentence>If she comes, she’ll follow me around all the time and she always wants to talk about football.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv thinks it’s really funny, but it’s just embarrassing.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: OK, OK, don’t worry. I won’t invite her. So which boys are coming?</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Well, Rajiv, of course. It’s his party, too. And Charlie will be there.</sentence>
        <sentence>They can’t wait for the fireworks!</sentence>
        <sentence>I must tell Dad to buy more bangers.</sentence>
        <sentence>If we have lots of bangers, we can scare the girls.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Very funny! But are only two boys coming, George? That’s not many.</sentence>
        <sentence>Did Rajiv ask Rick?</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Well, he asked him and Holden, but they’re not sure.</sentence>
        <sentence>Maybe they’ll go to Alexandra Palace to see the fireworks.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: But Rick must come! If he doesn’t come, Emma will be so unhappy.</sentence>
        <sentence>She’s got a big crush on him and she’s so excited about the party.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: So what do you want me to do?</sentence>
        <sentence>If I tell him about Emma, he’ll probably be too embarrassed to come!</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: That’s true. But why don’t you talk to Rick and Holden and tell them that they can come after the fireworks.</sentence>
        <sentence>If the party’s good, there’ll still be some people here.</sentence>
        <sentence>And it won’t be much fun if we don’t invite some more boys for my friends.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: What do you mean – if the party’s good? Of course it’ll be good.</sentence>
        <sentence>There’ll be a big bonfire and Mum says she’ll make some souflaki for the barbecue, and there’ll be hot dogs and …</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: But that’s only part of the fun, George.</sentence>
        <sentence>It’s not so important how much food and drink we have.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m really worried that not many boys will come.</sentence>
        <sentence>My friends can’t wait to meet your friends.</sentence>
        <sentence>They’ll be really disappointed if there aren’t many boys!</sentence>
        <sentence>Please talk to Holden and Rick on Monday.</sentence>
        <exercise>∙ … George will feel if Denah comes to the party. Why? ∙ … Rajiv and Charlie will feel if there are
            not enough bangers. ∙ … the girls will feel if the boys don’t come. P11  WB C1, p. 32
        </exercise>
        <exercise>36 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Say how …</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … Emma will feel if Rick doesn’t come. Why?</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … Rick will feel if George tells him about Emma.</exercise>
        <exercise>thirty-six</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='28'>
        <chapter>2/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C3 L 1/16 a) Listen to George’s conversation with Rick and Holden. Will they come to the party?
            Listening p. 124
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Listen again and make a list of reasons for</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ going to Rajiv and Caroline’s party</exercise>
        <exercise>c) v Extra: What would you do? Say why.</exercise>
        <exercise>C4 Grammar detective: conditional clauses, type 1</exercise>
        <exercise>Will future or simple present ?</exercise>
        <exercise>Can you solve the problem?</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Look at this sentence: If you invite her, I’ll never speak to you again.</exercise>
        <exercise>C5</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Find more examples from the dialogue</exercise>
        <exercise>in C2.</exercise>
        <exercise>3 What is the rule?</exercise>
        <exercise>How do you form conditional clauses, type 1?</exercise>
        <exercise>Start a grammar card.</exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 7: Bedingungssätze, Typ 1, p. 140 P12  WB C2, p. 33</exercise>
        <exercise>Mrs Lambraki is worried about the party preparations.</exercise>
        <exercise>So she talks to Caroline.</exercise>
        <exercise>Work with a partner.</exercise>
        <exercise>Ask and answer Mrs Lambraki’s questions.</exercise>
        <exercise>P7 LiF 7: Bedingungssätze, Typ 1, p. 140</exercise>
        <listing>help you · put up a tent · make some sandwiches · show them a film · run to the shop and buy more · ask
            our friends to be quiet · put him in George’s room
        </listing>
        <sentence>What will we do if the party is too noisy?</sentence>
        <exercise>If the party is too noisy, we’ll</exercise>
        <sentence>What will we do if we don’t have enough drinks?</sentence>
        <exercise>ask our friends to be quiet.</exercise>
        <sentence>What will happen if the weather is bad?</sentence>
        <sentence>What will we do if your friends get bored?</sentence>
        <sentence>What will happen if I don’t have enough time?</sentence>
        <sentence>What will we do if the dog gets scared of the fireworks?</sentence>
        <exercise>C6 v Extra</exercise>
        <sentence>What will happen if your friends don’t like the food?</sentence>
        <exercise>Work in groups.</exercise>
        <exercise>Play the chain fantasy game:</exercise>
        <gap>LiF 7: Bedingungssätze, Typ 1, p. 140 If I travel around the world, …</gap>
        <exercise>If I win a lot of money, I’ll travel around the world.</exercise>
        <gap>I’ll go to …</gap>
        <gap>If I go to …</gap>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-seven 37</footnote>
        <exercise>∙ going to the fireworks at Alexandra Palace</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='29'>
        <chapter>2/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C7 a) Look at the pictures and say what happens at the party.</exercise>
        <sentence>Mum gave me some food to bring.</sentence>
        <sentence>And I’ve got bangers!</sentence>
        <exercise>3 4 When can we start the fireworks, Mr Lambraki?</exercise>
        <sentence>Well, is everyone here?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma and I have made a guy.</sentence>
        <sentence>Where’s Rick? Isn’t he coming?</sentence>
        <sentence>George said he might come.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m sure he’ll be here soon.</sentence>
        <exercise>5 6</exercise>
        <sentence>Let’s just wait a little bit longer, Dad.</sentence>
        <sentence>I think some of George’s friends are still coming, aren’t they, George?</sentence>
        <gap>sure …</gap>
        <exercise>Mmm!</exercise>
        <sentence>Lovely hot dogs, Mrs Lambraki!</sentence>
        <sentence>These samosas are great, Rajiv.</sentence>
        <sentence>Did you make them?</sentence>
        <sentence>No, his mum did!</sentence>
        <sentence>Come on, Rajiv, let’s light some sparklers.</sentence>
        <sentence>Well, she’ll feel happier if she gets a sparkler!</sentence>
        <sentence>If Rick doesn’t come soon, I’ll die.</sentence>
        <sentence>What’s wrong with you, Emma?</sentence>
        <sentence>Here you are, Emma!</sentence>
        <sentence>I don’t want your stupid sparkler, Rajiv!</sentence>
        <exercise>9 10 I don‘t believe Is that</exercise>
        <sentence>What have I done?</sentence>
        <sentence>Come inside, everyone!</sentence>
        <sentence>This is dangerous!</sentence>
        <sentence>What a noise!</sentence>
        <exercise>it!</exercise>
        <sentence>You‘ve spoilt the party for everyone, Emma!</sentence>
        <exercise>the doorbell?</exercise>
        <exercise>38 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>Hi, everyone!</exercise>
        <exercise>Well, I’m not</exercise>
        <exercise>Wow!</exercise>
        <exercise>Oh no!</exercise>
        <exercise>thirty-eight</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='30'>
        <chapter>2/C</chapter>
        <exercise>b) Match the captions to the pictures.</exercise>
        <exercise>A</exercise>
        <exercise>B</exercise>
        <exercise>C</exercise>
        <exercise>D</exercise>
        <exercise>E</exercise>
        <sentence>George is really angry with Emma and so she starts to cry.</sentence>
        <sentence>This party is really horrible for Emma.</sentence>
        <sentence>The boys don’t understand why Emma isn’t having fun.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline isn’t very pleased that Hamida seems to be too friendly towards Rajiv.</sentence>
        <sentence>The sparkler lands in the box of fireworks and they all start going off at once.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline feels very nervous because Emma is so unhappy.</sentence>
        <sentence>She hopes Rick will come soon.</sentence>
        <exercise>F</exercise>
        <exercise>G</exercise>
        <exercise>H</exercise>
        <exercise>I</exercise>
        <exercise>J</exercise>
        <sentence>Emma is unhappy.</sentence>
        <sentence>She still hopes that Rick will come although it’s getting quite late.</sentence>
        <sentence>The friends eat hot dogs and samosas around the bonfire.</sentence>
        <sentence>The boys can’t wait to start the fireworks.</sentence>
        <sentence>Charlie and Rajiv try to cheer Emma up.</sentence>
        <sentence>The friends all bring things with them.</sentence>
        <sentence>The girls carry a guy.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma, Gillian, Charlie and Rajiv come to the party together.</sentence>
        <exercise>C8 a) Now read the picture story. Compare the atmosphere at the beginning (picture 1) and the end
            (pictures 8–10). Wordbank People p. 153
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Dramatic reading: Read the story in groups of 8.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Try to learn your role by heart.</exercise>
        <sentence>Dramatic reading, p. 130 P6</sentence>
        <exercise>C9 Look at the story again. Say what happens in the story. Example: First, the doorbell rings. Emma,
            Gillian, … Then … After that … Later … P14
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C10 Target task v " Project Portfolio Write the end of the story. Writing, p. 128</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Work in groups.</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 41.</exercise>
        <exercise>Speculate on what happens next.</exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 7: Bedingungssätze, Typ 1, p. 140 Use a grid to organize your ideas.</exercise>
        <exercise>Support</exercise>
        <gap>I think the friends will … If it’s Rick, Emma will …</gap>
        <exercise>∙ Use connectives (but, so, because, …)</exercise>
        <gap>When? Where? What? Who? …</gap>
        <exercise>∙ Add speech bubbles.</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Agree on what happens.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Write a picture story. Draw pictures and write captions. or</exercise>
        <exercise>4 Find another group, present/read your stories and give feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127  WB C3, p. 33
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Support</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Add structure words (first, then, after that, …).</exercise>
        <exercise>to make your story more interesting.</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words thirty-nine 39</footnote>
        <exercise>∙ Think about how your character feels.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Now read the story together.</exercise>
        <exercise>Writing a picture story:</exercise>
        <exercise>for the captions.</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Choose:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Write a story.</exercise>
        <exercise>Writing a story:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Use connectives (but, so, because, …).</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Use adjectives, comparatives and superlatives</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='39'>
        <chapter>3/A</chapter>
        <exercise>Around London</exercise>
        <exercise>A1 Round Robin: Collect ideas in class: ‘When I think of London I think of …’ Round Robin, p. 130
        </exercise>
        <exercise>A2 L 1/19</exercise>
        <exercise>a) Listen to the CD. Note down the sights in the correct order.</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Listen again and note down what is special about the sights.</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Look at the photos. Can you name the sights? Tell a partner what you know about them.</exercise>
        <listing>London Eye · Big Ben · Madame Tussauds · Trafalgar Square · Tower Bridge · Buckingham Palace · Covent
            Garden · Science Museum · Imperial War Museum · Sherlock Holmes Museum · Tate Modern · Emirates Stadium
        </listing>
        <gap>I think this is …</gap>
        <exercise>P1, P12  WB A1, A2, p. 41 This must be the …</exercise>
        <exercise>1 2</exercise>
        <exercise>famous Royal Opera House is Covent</exercise>
        <exercise>spend some time and watch acrobats</exercise>
        <exercise>once a fruit and vegetable market</exercise>
        <exercise>second-hand books here.</exercise>
        <exercise>Have a snack and enjoy</exercise>
        <exercise>for pickpockets!</exercise>
        <exercise>London Film Museum attraction is waiting for you.</exercise>
        <exercise>At the costumes, props and film sets from Find out how films are made and</exercise>
        <exercise>yourself in a film as you race</exercise>
        <exercise>48 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <sentence>Just around the corner from the famous Royal Opera House is Covent Garden.</sentence>
        <sentence>This is a fantastic place to spend some time and watch acrobats and musicians.</sentence>
        <sentence>Covent Garden was once a fruit and vegetable market but now you can buy clothes and second-hand books here.</sentence>
        <sentence>Have a snack and enjoy the fun.</sentence>
        <sentence>But watch out for pickpockets!</sentence>
        <sentence>Right across the Thames from the Houses of Parliament a special attraction is waiting for you.</sentence>
        <sentence>At the London Film Museum you can see costumes, props and film sets from famous films and TV programmes.</sentence>
        <sentence>Find out how films are made and see the cartoons.</sentence>
        <sentence>Get into a car and see yourself in a film as you race through London.</sentence>
    </page>
    <page id='40'>
        <chapter>3/A</chapter>
        <exercise>A3 a) Which sights would you like to visit? Imagine what you can see or do there. P2</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Look at some tips on what to do in London at the bottom of these pages.</exercise>
        <exercise>I’d like to visit</exercise>
        <exercise>Covent Garden because there are ...</exercise>
        <gap>Read the texts and collect adjectives and phrases from the texts that make a place sound interesting.
            Example: It’s worth a visit; a special attraction; …  WB A3, p. 42
        </gap>
        <exercise>A4 Target task v " Project Write about a London tourist attraction and present it.</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 58.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Choose a place in London you would like to visit and find out more about it. Try to find information
            that is interesting for young people.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 Use your phrases from A3b) and the information you have collected to write a text about your tourist
            attraction. Include information about prices and things to see or do. Use adjectives (e.g. the most exciting
            / ideal / perfect / best place to … ).
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 Work in groups of six. Present your tourist attraction to the group. Each group chooses their top
            three attractions. Compare your results: What are the top three attractions in class? Wordbank City, p. 151
            Speaking, p. 126/127 LiF 3: Steigerung von Adjektiven, p. 137
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Visit one of the world’s greatest stadiums.</sentence>
        <sentence>This is the ideal place to visit if you’re into football.</sentence>
        <sentence>The spectacular Arsenal Museum is open every day.</sentence>
        <sentence>But you can also do a fascinating tour of the stadium and the media centre.</sentence>
        <sentence>Do the virtual tour on the Internet.</sentence>
        <sentence>If you’re into science, this museum is an absolute must.</sentence>
        <sentence>See stunning science films in 3D, explore the universe and find out about how technology is changing our world.</sentence>
        <sentence>And the best thing is: it’s for free.</sentence>
        <sentence>Check the website to plan your visit.</sentence>
        <sentence>OK, so you’re not interested in art, but you should still visit the Tate Modern.</sentence>
        <sentence>The building was a power station until 1981.</sentence>
        <sentence>It’s worth a visit just to see the building.</sentence>
        <sentence>Go to the seventh floor to get an amazing view of London for free.</sentence>
    </page>
    <page id='41'>
        <chapter>3/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B1 a) Read the chat messages to find out who wants to visit London. What are the friends planning to
            do?
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Caro: Hi Sophie + Rob. It’s cool that you can come for the weekend.</sentence>
        <sentence>George and I have already made plans to show you around London! :-)</sentence>
        <sentence>SOPHEE: Can’t wait to see you again.</sentence>
        <sentence>A weekend in London is just so cool.</sentence>
        <sentence>You know I’ve never been to London before, so I’m really looking forward to it.</sentence>
        <sentence>Hope it’s not only sightseeing though. ;-)</sentence>
        <sentence>Caro: Don’t worry. We haven’t planned too much sightseeing although the Science Museum and the Natural History Museum are
            worth a visit.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>There are also some interesting places you haven’t heard about, yet – like the Film Museum next to the
            London Eye.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Is there anything you especially want to see?</sentence>
        <sentence>SOPHEE: I’d love to go to Buckingham Palace.</sentence>
        <sentence>And what about Notting Hill, where all the film stars live?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: No way! Sophie has read about all the film stars in London and she hasn’t talked about anything else since.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>I don’t want any more of that!!!</sentence>
        <sentence>Caro: Hmm, we could do Buckingham Palace. But you can’t go in. I’ve checked the Internet.</sentence>
        <sentence>It’s only open to visitors in the summer … And if you’re into film stars, then what about Madame Tussauds?
        </sentence>
        <sentence>SOPHEE: Sounds great!</sentence>
        <sentence>I’ve always wanted to go there.</sentence>
        <sentence>My friend Cherry has just been there.</sentence>
        <sentence>She said there is a Chamber of Horrors.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Great idea! Anyway, I guess the London Eye is a must.</sentence>
        <sentence>And I think the Emirates Stadium sounds great.</sentence>
        <sentence>Georgie: The Emirates Stadium? You must be joking!</sentence>
        <sentence>Have you turned into an Arsenal fan, Rob?</sentence>
        <sentence>;-)) To be honest, it doesn’t sound that exciting.</sentence>
        <sentence>If you want to do a stadium tour, I think the Wembley Stadium would be more interesting.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Don’t worry – I haven’t changed my mind about Manchester United!!!</sentence>
        <sentence>Wembley is OK with me, but it’s not that high on my list.</sentence>
        <sentence>What I’d really like to do is to go to a big music store.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caro: Buckingham Palace, Madame Tussauds, the London Eye … Cool! Sounds like a busy weekend.</sentence>
        <sentence>Why don’t we go on a sightseeing tour?</sentence>
        <sentence>We’ll find out more about it … Mum and Dad have offered to pay for tickets! :-)</sentence>
        <sentence>Looking forward to seeing you!!!
        </sentence>
        <exercise>b) Read the chat again and complete the sentences.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 ??? have made plans for Sophie and Rob. 4 ??? has always wanted to go to Madame Tussauds. 2 ??? has
            never been to London before. 5 ??? hasn’t changed his mind about 3 ??? has checked the Internet about
            Manchester United. Buckingham Palace. 6 ??? have offered to pay for the tickets.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>c) Read the chat again and collect phrases the friends use …</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … to say what they would like to do (e.g. I’d love to go to … ) ∙ … to disagree (e.g. You must be
            joking! )  WB B1–B3, p. 43, 44
        </exercise>
        <exercise>50 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … to make suggestions (e.g. And what about …? )</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … to agree (e.g. Sounds great! )</exercise>
        <exercise>fi fty</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='42'>
        <chapter>3/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B2 Grammar card: present perfect (statements) 1 Look at these sentences from the chat: George and I
            have already made plans …
        </exercise>
        <gap>Sophie hasn’t talked about anything else … This is a new tense: the present perfect. Find more examples
            from B1.
        </gap>
        <exercise>2 How do you form the present perfect? When do you use it? Check LiF 8 on page 140 and start a grammar
            card. P3, P8  WB B4, B5, p. 45
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B3 Sophie and Rob have a lot to do before the weekend. Look at their checklist and say what they have
            already done and what they haven’t done yet. P9, P10 Example: Sophie has already bought … Rob and Sophie
            haven’t … yet.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>– buy a present for Caroline (Sophie) 3 – pack bags (Rob and Sophie) – get a Manchester United T-shirt
            from fan shop (Rob) – look up the train times on the Internet (Rob) 3
        </exercise>
        <exercise>– check batt eries for cameras (Rob and Sophie) 3 – think of present for Mrs Lambraki (Rob and Sophie)
            – fi nd photo CD from last school year (Rob) 3 – email Caroline about tour (Sophie)
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B4</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Now describe the brochure. He/She has to draw it.</exercise>
        <exercise>at the top ∙ in the middle ∙ in big letters ∙ at the bottom ∙ below the heading</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Do you want to go on the tour? Say why/why not.</exercise>
        <exercise>B5 a) Read the brochure and try to puzzle out the meanings of these words and phrases.</exercise>
        <exercise>live guide ∙ commentary ∙ fantastic offers wide choice ∙ great value ∙ river cruise</exercise>
        <exercise>Support</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Does it sound/look like a German/French/… word?</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Now check a dictionary to see if you were right. How to work with a dictionary, p. 129</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words fi fty-one 51</footnote>
        <exercise>a) Look at the brochure about a London bus tour.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Work with a partner. He/She closes his/her book.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Compare the picture with the brochure.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Can you puzzle it out from the context?</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Do you know a similar adjective or a similar word?</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='43'>
        <chapter>3/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B6 …</exercise>
        <exercise>a) Go through pages 48-51 and collect words to make CITY</exercise>
        <exercise>a word web for ‘city’.</exercise>
        <exercise>Wordbank City, p. 151</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Make a word search with city words for your partner.</exercise>
        <exercise>activities</exercise>
        <exercise>places</exercise>
        <exercise>B7 L 1/20 a) Close your books and listen to George and Rob. Find out what the friends decide in the
            end. What are their reasons?
        </exercise>
        <sentence>George: Hi Rob, how are you?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Well, we’ve packed our bags so we’re almost ready.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Cool, I just need to know a few things before you come.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline and I have looked at different tours.</sentence>
        <sentence>She wants to do the Hop-on Hop-off tour.</sentence>
        <sentence>Have you ever done one of those tours?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: You mean the open doubledecker buses?</sentence>
        <sentence>Well, they’re all over the place – even here in Manchester.</sentence>
        <sentence>Could be fun on a sunny day …</sentence>
        <sentence>George: OK, then.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Hey, have you been to this famous battleship yet?</sentence>
        <sentence>George: You mean the HMS Belfast? No, I haven’t. But Caroline would hate it.</sentence>
        <sentence>It sounds OK to me, but it’s not that high on my list.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: I think the girls want to do their own little tour anyway.</sentence>
        <sentence>Shopping and Shakespeare’s Globe …</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Has Sophie already talked to Caroline about this?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: I don’t know, they text each other all the time …</sentence>
        <sentence>Have you booked anything yet?</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Not yet. Why?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Well, it would be really cool to see the Emirates Stadium even if I’m not an Arsenal fan.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’ve just gone on a virtual tour on the Internet and I must admit I’d like to see the real thing …</sentence>
        <sentence>Hey, have you seen the new Sherlock Holmes film?</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Yes, I have – it’s fantastic!</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: I haven’t seen it yet. But isn’t there a Sherlock Holmes Museum in London?</sentence>
        <sentence>I know tickets can be quite expensive, but maybe we could …</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Hasn’t Mum phoned your mum?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: I think she’s talked to Dad. But I’m not sure what the phone call was about.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: She wants to give us some money for our sightseeing …</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Cool! Sounds great!</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Right, see you at the weekend, then!</sentence>
        <exercise>1 No, I haven’t. But Caroline would hate it. 2 I think she’s talked to Dad. 3 You mean the open
            double-decker buses?
        </exercise>
        <exercise>4 I don’t know, they text each other all the time … 5 Not yet. Why? 6 Yes, I have – it’s fantastic.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>c) Read the dialogue between George and Rob again and add phrases to your list from B1c). P5  WB B6,
            B7, p. 46
        </exercise>
        <exercise>52 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>b) v Choose:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Write an acrostic about your favourite city. or</exercise>
        <exercise>fi fty-two</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='44'>
        <chapter>3/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B8 Grammar card: present perfect (2) (questions) 1 Write down questions in the present perfect from
            the dialogue and use different colours like this: Have you booked anything yet? Has Caroline already talked
            to Sophie?
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 How do you form the questions? Check LiF 8 on page 142 and add the rule to your grammar card. P4 
            WB B8, p. 47
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B9</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Look at the list and choose five activities.</exercise>
        <listing>· have tea with the Queen · go on a boat trip on the Thames · take photos of London from the London Eye
            · buy souvenirs in Covent Garden · climb the 199 steps up inside Tower Bridge · feed squirrels in Green Park
        </listing>
        <exercise>∙ Your partner asks questions to find out which activities you have chosen.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ If your answer is ‘yes’, your partner can go on. If your answer is ‘no’, it’s your turn.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ The person who has found out all five activities first is the winner.</exercise>
        <listing>· be on a double-decker bus · go shopping in Bond Street · visit Madame Tussauds</listing>
        <exercise>LiF 8: Present perfect, p. 142</exercise>
        <exercise>Yes, I have.</exercise>
        <exercise>· do a tour of the Emirates Stadium Have you had tea</exercise>
        <exercise>No, I haven’t.</exercise>
        <exercise>B10 Target task v Portfolio Write a dialogue between Caroline and George and act it out.</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at pp.</exercise>
        <exercise>58/59.</exercise>
        <exercise>The friends want to see many different sights, but there isn’t enough time.</exercise>
        <exercise>George and Caroline have to decide what to do.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Work with a partner. Go through pages 50-52 and note down what sights/places Sophie, Rob, Caroline
            and George want to see. Wordbank City, p. 151
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 Sophie and Rob will arrive on Friday afternoon. They have to get back to Manchester on Sunday
            afternoon. Think about how many sights/places they could visit in that time.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 Now plan a dialogue between Caroline and George. You have to agree on some sights and places. One of
            you is Caroline, one of you is George.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>4 Write your dialogue. Use statements and questions in the present perfect when necessary. The phrases
            from B1c) and B7c) can help you. LiF 8: Present perfect, pp. 141/142
        </exercise>
        <exercise>5 Practise your dialogue and present it to another pair. Then give feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127
        </exercise>
        <gap>Support Have you seen/been to …? I’ve never seen/been to … I’ve already visited …, but I haven’t …</gap>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words fi fty-three 53</footnote>
        <exercise>with the Queen?</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='45'>
        <chapter>3/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C1 Have you ever been lost? Talk to a partner and tell him/her about your experiences.</exercise>
        <listing>Support When I was small … · On a trip to … · Last year I got lost · I lost my way when … · I lost
            sight of … · I could not see/find … · I did not know where … · I was scared/worried/frightened/…
        </listing>
        <exercise>C2 L 1/21 a) Read the text and find out why George says: “We’re not very well-organized today …”.
        </exercise>
        <sentence>A week later.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob and Sophie are in London.</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: It’s past four o’clock.</sentence>
        <sentence>Where are the boys?</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: It’s only five past, Sophie.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m sure they will be here soon.</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: Well, Rob is always late.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: I’ll phone George. … No answer.</sentence>
        <sentence>Let’s just wait a few more minutes.</sentence>
        <sentence>Five minutes later.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Look, there’s George. But where’s Rob?</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Hi girls, have you seen Rob? I’ve lost him.</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: What do you mean, you’ve lost him?</sentence>
        <sentence>I thought you went to the HMS Belfast together.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Well, of course we did.</sentence>
        <sentence>Then we took the Tube to Baker Street.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was really full and when we got off I suddenly couldn’t see Rob anymore.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: I don’t believe it! It’s only a short way from the station to here.</sentence>
        <sentence>How can anyone get lost?</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: You don’t know Rob!</sentence>
        <sentence>He’s lost his way between his room and the bathroom before.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Sounds like Caroline!</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m surprised she found her way here!</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Very funny, George!</sentence>
        <sentence>Have you tried to phone Rob?</sentence>
        <sentence>George: No, I haven’t, my mobile’s dead. I forgot to charge it.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Oh great! That’s why I couldn’t phone you.</sentence>
        <sentence>What’s Rob’s number, Sophie?</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: Erm … 0775 6488318. … And I’ve left my mobile at home.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: We’re not very well-organized today, are we? …</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Hello!</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Hi Rob, it’s Caroline!</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Caroline, where are you all?</sentence>
        <sentence>I’ve rung George and Sophie again and again but they aren’t answering.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: We’ll explain that later. Where are you?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: I don’t really know.</sentence>
        <sentence>I came out of the Underground and started walking down the road …</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Have you seen any sights or road signs?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Well, I walked past a building on the left. There was a huge queue.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: That was Madame Tussauds.</sentence>
        <sentence>So you walked along Marylebone Road.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Yes, well, then I turned right because I thought I saw George, but it wasn’t him.</sentence>
        <sentence>So I walked straight on to the next street and turned left.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Can you see a street name? I’ve got a map here.</sentence>
        <sentence>I can tell you how to get to the museum then.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Well, I’ve just crossed a main street.</sentence>
        <sentence>Just a minute, it says Marylebone High Street and right in front of me is Nottingham Street …</sentence>
        <exercise>54 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ How did you feel?</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ What happened?</exercise>
        <exercise>fi fty-four</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='46'>
        <chapter>3/C</chapter>
        <exercise>b) Read the text again and collect information about Rob.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Where is he now? Find the place on the map below. P13  WB C1, C2, p. 48</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Find words and phrases in the text for giving/talking about directions and write them down in a
            list.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C3 L 1/22 a) Listen to Caroline’s directions and follow them on the map. Listening, p. 124</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Listen again and add any new words or expressions to your list from C2c).</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Match the expressions to the symbols. There are more symbols than you need. P6  WB C3, p. 49
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 walk straight on 2 turn left</exercise>
        <exercise>3 turn right 4 walk past … 5 walk on till you get to … 6 on your right 7 on your left</exercise>
        <exercise>A</exercise>
        <exercise>B C</exercise>
        <exercise>D</exercise>
        <exercise>E</exercise>
        <exercise>8 cross the street</exercise>
        <exercise>C4 v Extra</exercise>
        <exercise>Play a game: Use the map and say where you are.</exercise>
        <exercise>F</exercise>
        <exercise>G</exercise>
        <exercise>H</exercise>
        <exercise>I</exercise>
        <exercise>J</exercise>
        <exercise>Your partner gives you directions, but he/she doesn’t say where you are going.</exercise>
        <exercise>Wordbank City, p. 151</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</footnote>
        <exercise>fi fty-fi ve</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Where and how did he lose George?</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='47'>
        <chapter>3/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C5 L 1/23 a) Look at the picture and describe the man in it. What do you know about him? Note down
            your ideas. Wordbank People, p. 153
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Support Mütze mit Ohrenklappen = deerstalker</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Read about the friends’ visit to the Sherlock Holmes Museum and add any new information about
            Holmes to your notes from a).
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Pfeife = pipe Lupe = magnifying glass</exercise>
        <sentence>George: Look, there he is. Hi Rob!</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: So you’ve found us! Well done!</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Well, you two didn’t answer your mobiles!</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Let’s forget about it now, and go into the museum.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: So this is the house which belonged to Sherlock Holmes!</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Don’t be stupid! Sherlock Holmes isn’t a real person.</sentence>
        <sentence>Sir Arthur Conan Doyle is the writer who created Sherlock Holmes.</sentence>
        <sentence>He lived at 221b Baker Street.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: But in the film, Sherlock Holmes and Dr Watson live in Baker Street.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’ve seen it! It’s the film that Jude Law stars in. He plays Dr Watson and …</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: I think you’re both right.</sentence>
        <sentence>Why don’t we go in and look around?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Wow, these stairs are really dark and narrow.</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: The lights aren’t very strong. They’re like the gaslights that they had in the 19th century!</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: This looks like Sherlock Holmes’ study.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Yeah – and this must be the medical bag which Watson used.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: And here’s the bedroom.</sentence>
        <sentence>Look at all these photographs of the criminals who lived at that time!</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Come upstairs! You must look at the man who has got a snake around his head.</sentence>
        <sentence>And there’s a woman who is shooting someone.</sentence>
        <sentence>Wow! And all these weapons.</sentence>
        <sentence>This is better than the London Dungeon!</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: Ugh! That’s horrible.</sentence>
        <sentence>Look at this poor man in a cage! And this one is falling through a trapdoor.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: They are all people who Sherlock Holmes met in the stories.</sentence>
        <sentence>Look! It says so in the brochure.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: I don’t remember them from the film.</sentence>
        <sentence>Sophie: Let’s go and have a look in the shop.</sentence>
        <sentence>Perhaps we can find some presents for our parents.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Haven’t you done enough shopping for one day?</sentence>
        <sentence>Rob: Come on George! Perhaps I can get a DVD which we can watch when we get home.</sentence>
        <exercise>c) Match the sentence halves about Sherlock Holmes and the museum.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Sherlock Holmes is the detective A which shows criminals from that time. 2 The house in Baker Street
            is now a museum B who played Dr Watson in the film. 3 There is a photo gallery C that they had in the 19th
            century. 4 Jude Law is an actor D which shows how Sherlock Holmes lived. 5 The lights are like the ones E
            who is falling through a trapdoor. 6 On one of the photos there is a man F that lived at 221b Baker Street.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>56 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>fi fty-six</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='48'>
        <chapter>3/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C6 v Extra: Grammar detective: relative clauses</exercise>
        <exercise>Who , which or that ?</exercise>
        <exercise>Can you solve this puzzle?</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Find examples of relative clauses with who , which and that from C5 (e.g. So this is the house which
            belonged to Sherlock Holmes. ).
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 When do you use who ? When do you use which ? When can you use that ? Look at LiF 9 on page 142 for
            help. Write a grammar card for relative clauses. P7  WB C4, p. 50
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C7 v Extra a) Puzzle out the answers. You can find the answers in the dialogue from C5.</exercise>
        <sentence>This is a person who writes stories.</sentence>
        <sentence>This is the man who was Holmes’ assistant and best friend.</sentence>
        <sentence>This is something which a doctor often carries.</sentence>
        <sentence>These are people that do bad things.</sentence>
        <sentence>This is something that you can keep animals in.</sentence>
        <sentence>This is something which you can buy for your friends.</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Make five new puzzles for your partner. Use who, which and that . Example: This is the boy in our
            class who … This is the room in our school that … LiF 9: Relativsätze, p. 142  WB C5, p. 50
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C8 Target task v " Project Portfolio Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Write an English guidebook of your home town/area in class.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Collect places/sights/people that could be interesting for visitors.</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Find out about the places/sights/people:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ What is special about them?</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Choose one place/sight/person and write a paragraph for the guidebook. Describe the
            place/sight/person and note down directions, too. Wordbank City, p. 151
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Extra: Gallery walk: Hang up your paragraphs and read them.</exercise>
        <exercise>Choose the top three sights/places/people in your home town/area.</exercise>
        <exercise>Gallery walk, p. 130 P14, P15  WB C6, p. 51</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 60.</exercise>
        <exercise>Support You can add pictures, too.</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words fi fty-seven 57</footnote>
        <exercise>∙ Where are they? / Where did they live?</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='59'>
        <chapter>4/A</chapter>
        <exercise>Fun at school</exercise>
        <exercise>A1 Look at the posters 1-3 at Camden School for Girls. Which event would you like to go to? Which one
            would you like to take part in? Which one would you hate to go to? Say why.  WB A1, p. 59
        </exercise>
        <exercise>A2 a) Make a list of events and activities that take place at your school. Then compare the events and
            activities to the ones at Camden School for Girls. Include places, prices, dates, classes/age groups.
        </exercise>
        <gap>At our school we also have/perform …</gap>
        <gap>We organize … every year.</gap>
        <gap>We don’t have … There is no …</gap>
        <exercise>b) What is your favourite event/activity at your school? Say why. Wordbank Entertainment, p. 152 P15,
            P16
        </exercise>
        <exercise>we leave for our concert tour to Croatia!</exercise>
        <exercise>Vaughan Williams – The Lark Ascending</exercise>
        <exercise>plus a selection of popular songs Tuesday 13 July | Main Hall | 6:30pm Tickets: £ 4 adults | £ 2
            pupils
        </exercise>
        <exercise>68 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>Camden School for Girls</exercise>
        <exercise>Pre-Tour Concert</exercise>
        <exercise>Come to hear fantastic music before</exercise>
        <exercise>Choir and Symphony Orchestra</exercise>
        <exercise>Purcell – Come Ye Sons of Art</exercise>
        <exercise>de Falla – Seven Popular Spanish Songs</exercise>
        <exercise>Stravinsky – The Firebird</exercise>
        <exercise>from our Jazz Band</exercise>
        <exercise>Buffet included</exercise>
        <exercise>sixty-eight</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='60'>
        <chapter>4/A</chapter>
        <exercise>A3 a) Read the article from the Camden School Friday News below. Who gets a lot of praise?</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Collect words and phrases you can use to praise someone. P1</exercise>
        <exercise>A4  S 11, L 1/28 a) Listen to the friends and look at the posters to find out which event they are
            talking about. Listening, p. 124
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Use the correct poster to note down information in a grid ( who, when, what, where? ). Then listen
            again and add more information to your grid. P2  WB A2, p. 59
        </exercise>
        <exercise>A5 Target task v  Portfolio Write an article about the event from A4 for the Camden School Friday
            News. 1 Plan your article and think about
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ an introduction: say what your article is ∙ the main part: describe the details and ∙ the ending:
            say something positive about the event.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 78.</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Collect words and phrases for your article. Your list from A3b) can help you.</exercise>
        <exercise>Wordbank Festivals, p. 150 3 Write your article.</exercise>
        <exercise>Writing, p. 128 4 Give your article to a partner.</exercise>
        <exercise>Check your articles and give each other feedback.</exercise>
        <exercise>Speaking 2, p. 127 P9 LiF 2R: Simple past, p. 135  WB A3, p. 60</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Camden S C hool Friday n ew S</exercise>
        <sentence>CSG at Step Live! – a real success!</sentence>
        <sentence>On Sunday, 110 girls from CSG performed in the Step Live! show at Sadler’s Wells Theatre.</sentence>
        <sentence>Step Live! is the famous dance show for schools across London.</sentence>
        <sentence>As a reward for their hard work, the girls performed at Sadler’s Wells – the dance theatre in London.</sentence>
        <sentence>The CSG Dance Company and Year 7 represented our school.</sentence>
        <sentence>The CSG Dance Company performed in the first half with their ‘Bad Romance’ piece.</sentence>
        <sentence>They were the best act of the night, and received neverending applause.</sentence>
        <sentence>Almost all of Year 7 were on the stage with their ‘Mamma Mia’ piece.</sentence>
        <sentence>The girls looked brilliant in their costumes and their dancing was excellent!</sentence>
        <sentence>So it was no surprise that they received the biggest applause of the night from the audience.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was the perfect end to the show.</sentence>
        <sentence>Well done to everyone who took part – the show was a real success</sentence>
    </page>
    <page id='61'>
        <chapter>4/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B1  L 1/29 a) Read these sentences from the dialogue below. Speculate on what the girls are talking
            about.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 “Don’t you think we should do something totally different this year?” 2 “Don’t worry, we can
            practise together.” 3 “I just love auditions!”
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Read the dialogue. What is it about? What are the girls’ suggestions? Say which one you like best
            and why.
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Gillian: Hey, remember that Ms Walsh asked us to make suggestions for the next school play?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: What about a Shakespeare comedy? We haven’t had one for a while.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Oh, yes. Let’s do Shakespeare!</sentence>
        <sentence>I haven’t had a big role for ages and I want to play Juliet!</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: ‘Romeo and Juliet’ isn’t a comedy, silly …</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Oh no, not another classic.</sentence>
        <sentence>We did ‘A Christmas Carol’ by Charles Dickens last year, remember?</sentence>
        <sentence>Don’t you think we should do something totally different this year?</sentence>
        <sentence>Look, I’ve done some research on the Internet and I’ve found a comedy that sounds fantastic.</sentence>
        <sentence>It’s called ‘Invasion from Planet Zorgon’.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: So it’s about aliens? I’m not sure Ms Walsh would like that.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: But just think about it – it’s really cool!</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Let me see. There are only six proper roles.</sentence>
        <sentence>That means not many people can take part.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: That’s true. What do you suggest then?</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Hmm, I don’t know.</sentence>
        <sentence>We haven’t had a musical since ‘The Lion King’. And that was two years ago!</sentence>
        <sentence>I loved ‘The Lion King’. Maybe we could do ‘Cats’ or ‘Starlight Express’?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Great idea! But the auditions … I would be super-nervous.</sentence>
        <sentence>I haven’t sung on stage since our last Christmas play.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Don’t worry, we can practise together. I love auditions!</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: A musical? Oh no, not such boring, girly stuff again, please!</sentence>
        <sentence>Can’t we find something that’s more interesting than a story about cats or trains?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Like what?</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: A really exciting story or an adventure maybe.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Like Sherlock Holmes?</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: No, something like ‘Twilight’!</sentence>
        <sentence>I’ve read all the books, and last weekend I watched the DVD ‘New Moon’ with Dad.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: But that’s not a play.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: I know. But it’s just a first idea. Well, we could change it into a play.</sentence>
        <sentence>Why don’t we try it?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: OK, OK.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: A play about vampires? Great idea!</sentence>
        <sentence>Just think about the amazing costumes and the decoration for the stage.</sentence>
        <sentence>We could even have some music.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Fantastic idea! Come on, girls, let’s find Ms Walsh and ask her now!</sentence>
        <exercise>c) Read the dialogue again and note down phrases to persuade someone about something (e.g. Let’s … ).
            P3  WB B1, p. 61
        </exercise>
        <exercise>70 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>seventy</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='62'>
        <chapter>4/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B2</exercise>
        <exercise>Write down five exercises.</exercise>
        <exercise>Some can be wrong.</exercise>
        <exercise>Then show them to a partner.</exercise>
        <exercise>He/She must say if they are right or wrong and correct the wrong exercises.</exercise>
        <exercise>Gillian Emma Caroline The girls</exercise>
        <exercise>has hasn’t have haven’t</exercise>
        <exercise>sung on a stage done a Shakespeare play read all the ‘Twilight’ books talked about their idea had a
            big role
        </exercise>
        <exercise>since Christmas.</exercise>
        <exercise>for a while.</exercise>
        <exercise>for a short time only.</exercise>
        <exercise>for ages.</exercise>
        <exercise>B3 Grammar card: present perfect with for/since 1 Look at these exercises from B1: I haven’t had a big
            role for ages. I haven’t sung on stage since our last Christmas play.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 In English you can use two words for the German word ‘seit’: for and since . When do you use since ?
            When do you use for ? Check LiF 10 on page 143 and add the information to your grammar card for the present
            perfect.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 Think of four more exercises with for and since and add them, too. P8  WB B2, B3, p. 62</exercise>
        <exercise>B4 Work with a partner and talk about your hobby.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … have known the teacher/the other children in the group ∙ … have been interested in your hobby
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … have had/taken lessons ∙ … have practised …</exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 10: Present perfect: for/since, p. 143  WB B4, B5, p. 63, 64</exercise>
        <exercise>B5 Target task v  Portfolio</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 78.</exercise>
        <exercise>Write a dialogue between Emma, Gillian, Caroline and Ms Walsh.</exercise>
        <exercise>The girls tell Ms Walsh about the vampire play, but she is not sure about it.</exercise>
        <exercise>So they try to persuade her.</exercise>
        <exercise>In the end, Ms Walsh says yes.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Collect ideas about why Ms Walsh doesn’t like the idea of a vampire play.</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Write your dialogue. You can use the phrases from B1c).</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Practise your dialogue and perform it in front of another group. Give feedback. Wordbank
            Entertainment, p. 152 Speaking 2, p. 127
        </exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventy-one 71</footnote>
        <gap>Say since when or for how long you …</gap>
        <exercise>∙ … have dreamed of a horse/boat/prize/…</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … have wanted to …</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Work in groups of four.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Find arguments to persuade Ms Walsh.</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='63'>
        <chapter>4/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B6 v Extra Design a poster for the vampire play. You can look at the posters on pages 68/69 for
            help.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B7 Grammar card: present perfect or simple past? 1 Look at these sentences from the dialogue in B1: We
            haven’t had a musical since ‘The Lion King’. And that was two years ago!
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 You can use the present perfect or the simple past for things that happened in the past. But when do
            you use the present perfect? When do you use the simple past? Check LiF 11 on page 143 and write a grammar
            card. Add four examples. P10  WB B6, p. 64
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B8 The girls have persuaded Ms Walsh, and she has written a play about vampires. The next day there is
            an audition for pupils who want to take part in the play. There are lots of things to do. LiF 11: Present
            perfect or simple past, p. 143
        </exercise>
        <gap>Caroline has got the to-do list and is checking with Ms Walsh to see if everything is ready. Look at the
            checklist and write their dialogue. You can start like this: Ms Walsh: “Caroline, has Emma ...?” Caroline:
            “Yes, she has. She copied the script two weeks ago.” …
        </gap>
        <exercise>∙ copy the script (Emma) (two weeks ago)</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ make a list of the pupils who are interested (Emma) (yesterday)</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ find music for the play (Caroline) (–)</exercise>
        <exercise>B9  L 1/30 Read Caroline’s text message to Rajiv. Then listen to the telephone conversation and find
            out what the text message is about. Listening, p. 124
        </exercise>
        <exercise>72 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ buy vampire teeth (Gillian) (Friday)</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ make posters for the auditions (Gillian) (last week)</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ book assembly hall for the audition (secretary) (two days ago)</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ send the script to the pupils who are interested</exercise>
        <exercise>(Caroline) (yesterday afternoon)</exercise>
        <exercise>seventy-two</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='64'>
        <chapter>4/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B10 Look at these words and organize them in a word web. In class find more words to describe music.
            How to work with a dictionary, p. 129 melody text/lyrics
        </exercise>
        <listing>melody · text/lyrics · happy · sad · quiet · rhythm · fast · slow · scary · cheerful · atmosphere ·
            dark
        </listing>
        <exercise>MUSIC</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>B11  S 12, L 1/31</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <sentence>Last week I couldn’t get to sleep the house was dark and eerie.</sentence>
        <sentence>And I had the strangest feeling something bad was near me.</sentence>
        <sentence>I crept down to the basement and guess what I found there?</sentence>
        <sentence>A vampire lurking in the shadows!</sentence>
        <sentence>It gave me such a scare.</sentence>
        <sentence>He had ghostly skin and pointy teeth but he didn’t bite.</sentence>
        <sentence>He said ,‘Please, I just want a friend to hang out with at night.’</sentence>
        <sentence>Since then I haven’t slept at all.</sentence>
        <sentence>I can’t wait for the day to end.</sentence>
        <sentence>I just want to go down to the basement to see my vampire friend.</sentence>
        <exercise>a) Close your books and listen to the song. What is it about?</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Listen again and describe the music. How does it make you feel?</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Imagine you are the vampire. Write about a night in your life.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Write a different last verse for the song.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Collect information about the singer/band.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … how long he or she has been a singer/they have been a band ∙ … since when they have been
            interested in music
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Write a profile about the singer/band.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … the kind of music (rock, pop, hip hop, …)</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … what you think of when you hear it</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Present your favourite song to your class. Speaking 1, p. 126  WB B7, p. 65</exercise>
        <exercise>Support The word web from B10 can help you.</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventy-three 73</footnote>
        <exercise>L</exercise>
        <exercise>c) v Choose:</exercise>
        <exercise>but he didn’t bite.</exercise>
        <exercise>or</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 79.</exercise>
        <gap>Find out …</gap>
        <exercise>∙ … since when the singer/band is/are famous</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … if they have won any prizes</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Makes notes about …</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … why you like the song</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … how it makes you feel</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='65'>
        <chapter>4/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C1  L 1/32 a) Read the story. What happens at the audition?</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Write down two true sentences and one false sentence about the story. Your partner must say which
            sentence is wrong and must correct it.  WB C1, p. 65
        </exercise>
        <sentence>It was the day of the audition and all the girls were very excited.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline was happy, but she was nervous, too.</sentence>
        <sentence>She really wanted the leading role, but there were Anastasia and Moira, who also wanted the role.</sentence>
        <sentence>“It would be OK for me if Anastasia got the role,” Caroline said to Emma.</sentence>
        <sentence>“She’s fascinating on stage, she speaks clearly and she acts convincingly – when she laughs, she laughs happily or nervously, just as the stage directions say.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“She’s just a very good actress,” Emma agreed admiringly.</sentence>
        <sentence>“But Moira …?” Caroline rolled her eyes and Emma pulled a face.</sentence>
        <sentence>At the audition, Anastasia was first.</sentence>
        <sentence>When she went on the stage, her face was sad.</sentence>
        <sentence>“OK, let’s hear your part, then!” Ms Walsh said kindly.</sentence>
        <sentence>All the girls were quiet.</sentence>
        <sentence>Anastasia started, but she spoke very slowly: “Will I have to … stay in … the shadows forever? ...”</sentence>
        <sentence>“Come on, Anastasia! You know your words, don’t you?”</sentence>
        <sentence>“I do, Miss, but …” Anastasia whispered and then she began to cry.</sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian ran to the stage and put her arms around her.</sentence>
        <sentence>“What’s wrong?” Ms Walsh asked worriedly, but Anastasia couldn’t answer.</sentence>
        <sentence>The girls went ouside.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Tell me what’s wrong,” Gillian said quietly.</sentence>
        <sentence>“I’ve mucked it up,” Anastasia said sadly.</sentence>
        <sentence>“My mum had to go to hospital yesterday. And I’m so worried …”</sentence>
        <sentence>“Don’t worry – if we tell Ms Walsh, you’ll get another chance!” Gillian said cheerfully and smiled at her.</sentence>
        <sentence>“I’m not sure I even want it now,” Anastasia said and started to cry again.</sentence>
        <sentence>Inside, Moira was next.</sentence>
        <sentence>There was loud applause from her friends when she went on stage.</sentence>
        <sentence>She turned around like a star.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Can I begin, Miss?”, she asked arrogantly, but didn’t wait for an answer.</sentence>
        <sentence>She knew the words and spoke clearly: “Will I have to stay in the shadows forever? …”</sentence>
        <sentence>“Word, words, words,” Emma said quietly, “but no emotion!”</sentence>
        <sentence>But Moira’s friends clapped excitedly.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline watched them. “You’re right,” she answered nervously.</sentence>
        <sentence>On stage Caroline wanted to be the best actress.</sentence>
        <sentence>She really liked the role and she knew she could be better than Moira.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Will I …,” Caroline started loudly, but then she looked at Moira and her friends.</sentence>
        <sentence>They gave her the thumbs down behind Ms Walsh’s back.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline started to stammer.</sentence>
        <sentence>She tried to remember the words, but suddenly she couldn’t remember anything.</sentence>
        <exercise>74 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>seventy-four</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='66'>
        <chapter>4/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C2 a) Copy the grid. Note down all the</exercise>
        <exercise>character what she says/asks how she says/asks it</exercise>
        <exercise>characters in the story, what they say/ask and how they say/ask it.</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Dramatic reading:</exercise>
        <gap>Emma Ms Walsh …</gap>
        <gap>“She’s just a very good actress.” “OK, …” …</gap>
        <gap>admiringly … …</gap>
        <exercise>∙ Remember how the characters feel. Use your notes from a) and show the feelings of the different
            characters.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 Work in groups of four and have a reading competition. Find the best reader. You can use your grid
            from a) and a checklist to find out who read best. Dramatic reading, p. 130
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C3 Grammar detective: adverbs of manner</exercise>
        <exercise>Clear or clearly ?</exercise>
        <exercise>Can you solve this puzzle?</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Look at these exercises from C1:</exercise>
        <exercise>adjective adverb Caroline was happy.</exercise>
        <exercise>When she laughs, she laughs happily.</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Copy the grid and add more examples with nervous/nervously , worried/worriedly , quiet/quietly ,
            excited/excitedly and loud/loudly from the story.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 What do you describe with an adjective? What do you describe with an adverb? Look at LiF 12 on page
            144 for help.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>4 Start a grammar card. Look at LiF 12 on page 144 and find out about the spelling. When do you have
            to be careful? Add the information to your grammar card. P11-P13  WB C2, p. 66
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Support There is an extra rule about look and feel and adjectives – read it on page 144!</exercise>
        <exercise>C4</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Write down these verbs on ten cards:</exercise>
        <exercise>eat ∙ walk ∙ dance ∙ sing ∙ jump ∙ talk ∙ smile ∙ move ∙ laugh ∙ play ∙ Now note down ten adverbs on
            ten different cards. Example: angrily, happily,
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Now one player takes a card from each pile and acts out what the cards say.</exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 12: Adverbien der Art und Weise, p. 144  WB C3, C4, p. 66, 67</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventy-five 75</footnote>
        <exercise>1 Practise reading the story:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Read the story quietly twice.</exercise>
        <exercise>Work in groups and play this game:</exercise>
        <gap>scarily …</gap>
        <exercise>∙ Make two piles (verbs and adverbs). Turn the cards upside down.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ The others must guess what the player is doing and how he/she is doing it.</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='67'>
        <chapter>4/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C5  L 1/33 a) Think – pair – share: Speculate on how the story about the audition goes on. Think –
            pair – share, p. 130
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Read the story to find out if you were right. Reading, p. 125  WB C5, p. 68</exercise>
        <sentence>Caroline was really upset.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma tried to calm her down but Caroline didn’t want to listen.</sentence>
        <sentence>“You know why I mucked it up?” she shouted angrily.</sentence>
        <sentence>“It was just because of Moira’s friends – they pulled faces at me and now they’ve won.” “We should
            talk to Ms Walsh,” Emma suggested.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>“And tell her I was tricked out?”, Caroline said.</sentence>
        <sentence>“No way! Then she’ll think I’m just telling a sob story because I want to get the leading role.</sentence>
        <sentence>Anyway, Ms Walsh has offered me another job – she said I could be the prompter.</sentence>
        <sentence>That’s OK.” Caroline tried to sound cool, but Emma knew that her friend was hurt.</sentence>
        <sentence>On Friday it was drama group again.</sentence>
        <sentence>That evening Caroline wrote in her diary: Dear Diary, I feel awful.</sentence>
        <sentence>At least I don’t have to be on stage with Moira.</sentence>
        <sentence>The way she acts just makes me sick.</sentence>
        <sentence>She ruins everything!!!</sentence>
        <sentence>All week Caroline was very gloomy.</sentence>
        <sentence>When George asked her what was wrong, she didn’t answer.</sentence>
        <sentence>So George asked Emma.</sentence>
        <sentence>“That audition was just so unfair,” Emma said angrily.</sentence>
        <sentence>“The first night with Moira will be a nightmare for Caroline.” George felt sorry for his sister.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>He wasn’t that interested in drama, but he still thought it was unfair.</sentence>
        <sentence>“We must do something to cheer her up,” he suggested.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Hey, there’s a Popsicles concert on the day of the first performance.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“Maybe I can get some tickets for Caroline and me.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“What a great idea!” Emma answered.</sentence>
        <sentence>“But I don’t think she can go.</sentence>
        <sentence>You know she’s the prompter.</sentence>
        <sentence>She has to be there like everyone else.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“But her job is backstage, so anyone can do it.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m sure someone else can do it for her.”</sentence>
        <sentence>A few days later, Caroline found an envelope in her room.</sentence>
        <sentence>Inside there were tickets for the Popsicles concert. Caroline couldn’t believe it …
        </sentence>
        <sentence>It was the last week before the play started.</sentence>
        <sentence>The girls tried on their costumes.</sentence>
        <sentence>The boys in the band were ready.</sentence>
        <sentence>Everything was prepared.</sentence>
        <sentence>But Ms Walsh was a bit worried.</sentence>
        <sentence>Moira wasn’t very good.</sentence>
        <sentence>She spoke clearly and knew her words, but she didn’t say them with feeling.</sentence>
        <sentence>But it wasn’t only that.</sentence>
        <sentence>Moira was often difficult and the other girls on the stage were often tense when Moira was around.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>But it was too late now.</sentence>
        <sentence>Finally, everyone was ready.</sentence>
        <sentence>But where was Moira?</sentence>
        <sentence>Ms Walsh was annoyed.</sentence>
        <sentence>She was really fed up with Moira, who always pretended to be a star.</sentence>
        <sentence>Finally, Moira arrived.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Oh, Ms Walsh,” she whispered sweetly, “I need a microphone.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“What are you talking about?” Ms Walsh asked.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Well, you can hear – I’ve lost my voice. But maybe I can act my part with a microphone.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“The drama group always works without microphones – and if you have one, everyone will need one. I’m afraid we can’t do it.”</sentence>
        <sentence>Moira looked at Ms Walsh coldly.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Then we’ll have to postpone the play.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“Postpone the play?” Ms Walsh was shocked. “We can’t!”</sentence>
        <exercise>76 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>seventy-six</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='68'>
        <chapter>4/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C6 Choose a title for each part of the story and explain your choice. You can find different titles,
            too. P14  WB C6, p. 68
        </exercise>
        <listing>The idea · Keeping cool · Dear Diary · Hard times · Lost voice · Real friends · Moira wins · The
            surprise · A new chance? · Winners and losers · A difficult choice
        </listing>
        <gap>For part no. … I chose the title … because …</gap>
        <exercise>C7</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … after the next meeting of the drama group ∙ … when Moira can’t act in the play</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Caroline has got tickets for her favourite pop group – and she has the chance to take over Moira’s
            role. What would you do if you were Caroline and why? P6  WB C7, p. 69
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C8 Look at the story again. Collect different words for say and adjectives/adverbs that show how a
            character feels.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C9 Target task v " Project  Portfolio P7 Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Write your ending to the story from C5.</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 80.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 2 3 4</exercise>
        <exercise>Boo!</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Look at the pictures and choose the ending you like best. Then write your ending to the story.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ What happens exactly? How will the characters in the story react? ∙ Collect words and phrases for
            your story. Wordbank Entertainment, p 152; People, p. 153
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 Write the ending. Remember to …</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … include adjectives/adverbs to describe the characters’ feelings and their actions. ∙ … use
            different words for say . You can use your results from C8.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>4 Work in groups and read your stories to your group. Then correct them and choose the one you like
            best. Present the story to the class. Writing, p. 128  WB C8, p. 69
        </exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words seventy-seven 77</footnote>
        <exercise>a) Say how Caroline feels …</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … when she talks to Emma after the audition</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … when she finds the tickets</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Plan your ending:</exercise>
        <exercise>How will they feel?</exercise>
        <exercise>What will they say?</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … use the simple past.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … use direct speech (e. g. “OK, I can do it,” Caroline said.).</exercise>
        <exercise>Your list from C8 can help you.</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='77'>
        <chapter>5/A</chapter>
        <sentence>Green Week or the Mill?</sentence>
        <exercise>A1 In class talk about special events, trips and activities that take place at your school and note
            them down. LiF 1R, p. 133, LiF 2R, p. 135, LiF 8, p. 140/141  WB A1, A2, p. 77
        </exercise>
        <gap>Every year we have a project week. Then we …</gap>
        <gap>Last year we went to …/ organized …/ took part in …</gap>
        <gap>I have already acted in the school play/played for the school team/…</gap>
        <gap>There are always concerts/ music shows/dance shows/ … at our school in …</gap>
        <exercise>A2</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Group A reads the report about Green Week.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … who? ∙ … what? ∙ … where? ∙ … when? ∙ … why? Reading, p. 125</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Work with a partner who read the other report. Use your notes from a) to explain what your report
            is about.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>c) Which report do you find more interesting? Say why.</exercise>
        <sentence>Great success for the first Green Week at Camden School for Girls</sentence>
        <sentence>“What’s going on at CSG? Why are there so many people in green?”</sentence>
        <sentence>That is what many people asked when they walked past CSG last
            week in the first Green Week at our school.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Although there were a lot of pupils in green clothes, Green Week was not about fashion.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was a very informative experience about the world that we live in and what we can do to save it.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Every day of the week, all the teachers and pupils did something different to learn more about the environment.</sentence>
        <sentence>Each day had a different motto.</sentence>
        <sentence>On Monday, for example, we all watched the excellent film “The Age of Stupid” to see what our planet will look like in 40 years.</sentence>
        <sentence>On Wednesday we talked about recycling waste.</sentence>
        <sentence>Some of our pupils collected four boxes of plastic bottles when they walked around Camden.</sentence>
        <sentence>On Friday, we used green handprints to form a tree.</sentence>
        <sentence>Teachers and pupils made their green pledges for a better future – a future with more wind and solar energy!</sentence>
        <sentence>Thank you to everyone who took part in the projects.</sentence>
        <sentence>Please remember your green pledges.</sentence>
        <sentence>We still have great plans for the money that you and others donated to buy solar panels for our school.</sentence>
        <sentence>There is always more that we can do – but we have taken the first big step and the first Green Week at our school was a great success.</sentence>
        <exercise>86 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>a) Divide the class into two groups.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Group B reads the report about the Mill.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Make notes on …</exercise>
        <exercise>eighty-six</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='78'>
        <chapter>5/A</chapter>
        <exercise>A3  L 1/35 a) The Lambrakis talk about George’s trip to the Mill and Caroline’s Green Week. Listen to
            them and find out what George and Caroline are going to do at the Mill/Green Week. Take notes. Listening, p.
            124
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) v Extra: Would you like to have a Green Week at your school or go to the Mill? Say why/why not.
            Your notes from a) can help you.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>A4 Look at the elements of a report below. Read the reports again and find examples of them.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 a headline 2 an entertaining beginning 3 a person’s statement 4 details of an activity/event 5 a
            sentence that refers back to the title
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Example: details of an activity/event:</exercise>
        <gap>On Monday, for example, we all watched …  WB A3, A4, p. 78, 79</gap>
        <exercise>A5 Target task v P1, P7 Need help? Look at p. 96. ∙ Choose an event at your school and write a report
            about it for the English version
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Prepare a school radio report in English about an event at your school. Present it to the class.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Support ∙ Look at your list from A1 and choose one event ∙ Look at the reports in A2 again. Collect
            words and phrases that you can use with your report.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Your report should answer the questions who, what, where, when and why .</exercise>
        <sentence>The magic of the Mill</sentence>
        <sentence>It is just one hour and a half on the motorway, but for many pupils it is like a fascinating trip into
            another world.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Last week our Year 8 pupils spent a week at our field studies centre, the Mill, in Forest Green
            again.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>“First I thought, ‘Oh no, boring walks and lots of biology and geography exercises.’</sentence>
        <sentence>But it turned out to be lots of fun,” Jeremy Fowler said when he came back.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Mr Scott, one of the teachers who organized the stay at the Mill, agreed: “It’s the combination of fieldwork and sport and adventures that makes
            it a fantastic trip.”</sentence>
        <sentence>The Mill is a great place for pupils to study birds and learn more about wildlife and
            plants.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>During the week, the pupils made posters about the birds which you can find at the Mill.</sentence>
        <sentence>With football and other games, there was a lot of exciting entertainment – even if some boys were not
            happy that there were no supermarkets or shops nearby.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>But this is what makes the Mill so special.</sentence>
        <sentence>“I haven’t really thought much about birds and other wild animals – we don’t see them much in
            Camden.”
        </sentence>
        <sentence>“But it’s almost magic to be away from the traffic and the noise of London for a few days,” Manish
            Malik said about his experience.
        </sentence>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words eighty-seven 87</footnote>
        <exercise>Choose:</exercise>
        <exercise>of your school’s website.</exercise>
        <exercise>or</exercise>
        <exercise>you want to write/talk about.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ To structure your report, you can use A4.</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='79'>
        <chapter>5/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B1 Think – pair – share: What can you do to protect the environment? Think – pair – share, p. 130
            Wordbank Environment, p. 152
        </exercise>
        <exercise>a) Write down as many ideas as you can. You have got one minute.</exercise>
        <listing>recycle paper · turn off … when … · use …, not … · go by bike when …</listing>
        <exercise>b) Compare your list with a partner’s and add new words. … …</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Work in groups and share your ideas.</exercise>
        <exercise>d) In class group your ideas like this: go by bike</exercise>
        <exercise>B2  L 1/36 a) Listen to Caroline and her mother and find out what the pupils do for Green Week that
            day. Listening, p. 124
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Listen again and complete the sentences.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 All pupils at Camden School for Girls have to …</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>when you travel</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>when you are at home</exercise>
        <exercise>HOW TO PROTECT THE ENVIRONMENT</exercise>
        <exercise>when you go shopping</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>2 Mrs Lambraki doesn’t understand why Caroline doesn’t … 3 When Caroline goes by bike, she can … 4 Mrs
            Lambraki doesn’t know if Caroline’s bike … 5 The bike doctor … 6 Caroline doesn’t want to take Mrs
            Lambraki’s bike because …
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B3 a) In art class that morning, Caroline and her classmates design new signs that tell people how to
            protect the environment. Look at the posters and write down the tips/rules.
        </exercise>
        <gap>Example: You should turn off the lights when you leave the room. You mustn’t/shouldn’t …</gap>
        <listing>turn off · recycle leave on standby go by … · throw away</listing>
        <exercise>b) Use your ideas from B1 to design your own poster. Show it to a partner. He/She must say what your
            poster is about. Wordbank Environment, p. 152 P8  WB B1, p. 80
        </exercise>
        <exercise>88 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>eighty-eight</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='80'>
        <chapter>5/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B4  L 1/37 a) Close your books and listen to Caroline and Emma and their teacher, Mrs Perry. Find out
            which two topics they are talking about. Listening, p. 124  WB B2, p. 80
        </exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … Caroline feels angry ∙ … George is happy ∙ …the girls are excited</exercise>
        <sentence>Caroline: I can’t stand George these days.</sentence>
        <sentence>He can’t stop telling me how fantastic his trip to the Mill will be.</sentence>
        <sentence>He thinks he’ll be able to do whatever he wants there.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Really? That’s just not fair! Yesterday we weren’t even allowed to take a break until we finished our
            projects … and they can relax and enjoy their holiday!</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: At the Mill they don’t even have to do the washing-up after dinner.</sentence>
        <sentence>He’s just so lazy!</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Ssh, there’s Mrs Perry.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mrs Perry: Good morning, girls.</sentence>
        <sentence>Before we go on with our Green Week projects, there’s something I have to tell you.</sentence>
        <sentence>You probably all know the TV station ‘CamdenTV’.</sentence>
        <sentence>Well, they would like to interview some pupils about our Green Week for tomorrow’s evening news.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Wow, cool!</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Will we all be allowed to talk to them?</sentence>
        <sentence>Mrs Perry: I’m sorry, no. Just two of you will be able to
            talk to the reporter.</sentence>
        <sentence>So who wants to take part in the interview?</sentence>
        <sentence>… OK … There are six of you.</sentence>
        <sentence>So now we have to choose the two girls who’ll represent the class.</sentence>
        <sentence>Let’s have a vote.</sentence>
        <sentence>A few minutes later:</sentence>
        <sentence>Mrs Perry: OK, so it’s you two, Caroline and Emma. Congratulations!</sentence>
        <exercise>B5 Grammar card: modal verbs and their substitutes 1 You already know the modal verb can . You can
            only use it in the present tense. For other tenses, you need a substitute verb. Look at line 3 in B4 and say
            what the substitute verb is.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 Check LiF 13 on page 145 and find out about the substitute verbs of must/mustn’t, may and needn’t .
            Write a grammar card. P9  WB B3, p. 81
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B6 The reporter gives Caroline and Emma some advice for the interview.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ they will be allowed to do/won’t be allowed to do</exercise>
        <exercise>Example:</exercise>
        <sentence>Caroline and Emma will have to speak slowly and clearly.</sentence>
        <exercise>LiF 13: Modal verbs, p. 145 P10  WB B4, B5, p. 81, 82</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ speak slowly and clearly ∙ no “hello” to friends</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ no white or striped shirt</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words eighty-nine 89</footnote>
        <exercise>b) Listen again and explain why …</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at the notes and say what</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ they will have to do/won’t have to do</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ use short sentences</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ be polite</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ no chewing gum</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ normal clothes OK</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='81'>
        <chapter>5/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B7  L 1/38 After the lesson, Caroline calls her mother to tell her about the TV interview. a) Read
            Caroline’s answers and find out what Mrs Lambraki’s questions are. LiF 6: will future, p. 139, LiF 2R:
            Simple past, p. 135
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Caroline: Hi, Mum!</sentence>
        <sentence>Guess what! I’ll be on TV tomorrow!</sentence>
        <gap>Mrs Lambraki: Oh! What will you …?</gap>
        <sentence>Caroline: We will have to answer some questions.</sentence>
        <gap>Mrs Lambraki: …?</gap>
        <sentence>Caroline: The interview will be about Green Week.</sentence>
        <gap>Mrs Lambraki: …?</gap>
        <sentence>Caroline: The TV people didn’t choose me. My class voted for me. But I won’t be the only
            one.
        </sentence>
        <gap>Mrs Lambraki: …?</gap>
        <sentence>Caroline: Emma will be with me. Isn’t that cool?</sentence>
        <gap>Mrs Lambraki: Yes, but …?</gap>
        <sentence>Caroline: We will have to answer some questions about Green Week – if we like it … erm, you know.</sentence>
        <sentence>We are super excited! We’ll be on TV!!!</sentence>
        <sentence>Mrs Lambraki: …?</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: I’m not sure. I think it will be on at six o’clock.</sentence>
        <sentence>Oh, I have to go, Mum.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma wants to talk to me now. Bye!</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Now listen to the conversation and check if your questions are correct. P2</exercise>
        <exercise>B8  L 1/39 a) Read the interview. Who is more nervous – Caroline or Emma? Say why you think so.
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Emma: Oh no, I’ll make a fool of myself.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Emma, you needn’t worry.</sentence>
        <sentence>The TV people can cut out the bits where we say something wrong.</sentence>
        <sentence>It won’t be live.</sentence>
        <sentence>TV reporter: Ready, girls? Then let’s start …</sentence>
        <sentence>We’re here at Camden School for Girls today, where we will find out more about their Green Week.</sentence>
        <sentence>There are two girls from Year 8 with me – Caroline Lambraki and Emma Butler – who can tell us what is going on at their school at the moment.</sentence>
        <sentence>So, why is it called Green Week, Emma?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: It’s called Green Week … because we do a lot of projects about the environment.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Yes, we cover topics like energy, wildlife, recycling, transport and much more.</sentence>
        <sentence>Every day has a different motto.</sentence>
        <sentence>TV reporter: That sounds interesting. Can you give us an example of one of those days, Caroline?</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Today our topic is waste.</sentence>
        <sentence>We throw away so much … erm … plastic …erm … We throw away so much … erm … plastic and …</sentence>
        <sentence>TV reporter: Do you mean paper and other materials, too?</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: Yes, yes, so we produce a mountain of rubbish every year.</sentence>
        <sentence>So it’s better if we collect paper and … paper … I mean, paper and …</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: … plastic and glass and other materials so that we can recycle them.</sentence>
        <sentence>TV reporter: Are you trying to say that everything will be OK if we recycle as much as we can?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: No, recycling isn’t enough.</sentence>
        <sentence>We should buy products with less packaging and compost organic waste.</sentence>
        <sentence>TV reporter: As you’ve mentioned organic waste, I’ve heard that some pupils have made something very special and delicious for you.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline: That’s right. Some Year 10 students went to the shops and supermarkets yesterday and collected all the fruit that the shops wanted to throw away.</sentence>
        <sentence>They used them to make smoothies for us in the lunch break.</sentence>
        <sentence>TV reporter: It sounds as if you liked the smoothies, but how do you feel about Green Week as a whole?</sentence>
        <exercise>90 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>ninety</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='82'>
        <chapter>5/B</chapter>
        <sentence>Caroline: I wasn’t sure at the end, I mean, at the beginning.</sentence>
        <sentence>We had a Green Week last year and it means a lot of work, but it’s more fun than … erm … normal lessons.</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: Caroline’s right.</sentence>
        <sentence>There are so many interesting activities this year that most of us really love it – and we also
            learn something about the environment.</sentence>
        <sentence>TV reporter: You say Green Week is about learning.</sentence>
        <sentence>If I understood your head teacher correctly, Green Week is also about changing your behaviour.</sentence>
        <sentence>Do you agree?</sentence>
        <sentence>Emma: That’s true.</sentence>
        <sentence>Everyone had to walk to school or go by bike yesterday.</sentence>
        <sentence>A lot of pupils usually go by bus.</sentence>
        <sentence>I noticed that it’s faster for me to go by bike.</sentence>
        <sentence>So I’ll do it more often in the future.</sentence>
        <sentence>TV reporter: Thank you very much, Emma and Caroline.</sentence>
        <sentence>That was it. You did a very good job.</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Guess how Caroline and Emma feel after the interview.</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Say what happened at Green Week. What do you think of the activities? How would you like them?
        </exercise>
        <exercise>d) Note down words and phrases that show that you want to understand/ are interested in/are listening
            to what the other person says. P3  WB B6, B7, p. 83 Example: That sounds interesting; Do you mean …
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B9 Target task v Write an interview and act it out.</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 97.</exercise>
        <exercise>Work with a partner.</exercise>
        <exercise>One of you is a TV reporter and the other is a pupil at CSG.</exercise>
        <exercise>The reporter interviews the pupil about Green Week.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Together think about what you are going to talk about. Here are some ideas:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ go to a supermarket and find out where the fruit and vegetables come from</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Read your role cards and prepare your roles.</exercise>
        <exercise>Role card: TV reporter</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ the reason why pupils do them</exercise>
        <exercise>Role card: pupil at CSG</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ what you have done ∙ if you liked it and why</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Take turns to write down your questions and answers. The phrases from B8d) can help you.</exercise>
        <exercise>4 Practise your interview, then act it out for another pair. Give feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127 P13
        </exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words ninety-one 91</footnote>
        <exercise>∙ wear warm pullovers to show that you can keep warm without central heating</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ plant vegetables in the school garden</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … Wordbank Environment, p. 152</exercise>
        <exercise>Ask about</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ the activities</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ if the pupils like them and why</exercise>
        <exercise>Talk about</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ the reasons</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='83'>
        <chapter>5/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C1 Remember your last class trip: what were you allowed/not allowed to do? Write down the rules.  WB
            C1, p. 84
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C2 Before George’s class go to the Mill, the parents get a letter from the school. Read the letter and
            find out more about the Mill. P14
        </exercise>
        <sentence>William Ellis School</sentence>
        <listing>Highgate Road · London NW5 1RN</listing>
        <sentence>Dear parents, In two weeks Year 8 will be off to the Mill.</sentence>
        <sentence>I’m sure they’ll have a great week.</sentence>
        <sentence>Please make sure that your child brings camping things (a sleeping bag, a small rucksack, a plastic
            cup and plate, a knife, fork and spoon), enough clothes for a week, toothbrush/soap, a hat and an exercise
            book or diary.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>There are some games at the Mill, but pupils may also bring their own cards, games or books.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>The children do not need to bring any extra food.</sentence>
        <sentence>There will be three meals a day.</sentence>
        <sentence>Pupils who are not able to eat certain foods or pupils who take medicine must bring a note with them
            and talk to Mr Glover before the trip.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>The pupils are not allowed to bring radios, MP3 players, alcohol, computer games, mobile phones or
            pocket knives with them.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>If your child breaks the rules, we will ask you to come to the Mill and pick up your child
            immediately.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>The pupils can walk to Forest Green, a small village near the Mill.</sentence>
        <sentence>There are no shops in Forest Green.</sentence>
        <sentence>As you know, teachers have already collected pocket money (£ 20/child), so pupils shouldn’t bring any
            extra money.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>They will be able to buy food, drinks, pens, pencils, etc. at a small shop at the Mill.</sentence>
        <sentence>Many thanks for your help.</sentence>
        <sentence>Yours sincerely, M. Edwards</sentence>
        <exercise>C3 C4  S 14, L 1/40 a) Make a list of rules for the trip and compare a) The boys are not very happy
            about the rules. them to the rules for your class trips. Listen to them and note down their arguments.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Listening, p. 124 P15 b) Work with a partner.</exercise>
        <exercise>Discuss which rules you find sensible, too strict or silly.</exercise>
        <exercise>b) The boys want to bring MP3 players with them.</exercise>
        <exercise>P12 Write a short dialogue in which they try to convince Mr Glover.</exercise>
        <exercise> WB C2, p. 84</exercise>
        <exercise>92 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>ninety-two</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='84'>
        <chapter>5/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C5  L 2/1 a) Close your books and listen to the boys. Find out where they are.</exercise>
        <sentence>Holden: Hey, George, give me back my MP3 player.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: But this isn’t yours.</sentence>
        <sentence>Holden: But it looks like mine!</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Well, it’s Sam’s.</sentence>
        <sentence>Holden: It can’t be his. He never gives his MP3 player away.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: I know, but he brought his sister’s.</sentence>
        <sentence>Holden: What? He pinched his sister’s player?</sentence>
        <sentence>It’s hers? Oh, she’ll go mad.</sentence>
        <sentence>Holden: OK, but the music must be awful.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: It’s not that bad.</sentence>
        <sentence>… Hey, Rajiv, give us one of those bags of crisps. Whose are they anyway?
        </sentence>
        <sentence>George: He says she won’t miss it – she’s on a class trip, too, and her teachers don’t want any MP3
            players on the trip.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv: They’re not mine.</sentence>
        <sentence>John and Leo are sitting here. The bags are theirs.</sentence>
        <sentence>They’ve gone to the front to talk to Stephen. … Oh, there they are.</sentence>
        <sentence>Hey, Leo, those crisps – are they yours?</sentence>
        <sentence>Leo: Yes, but we mustn’t eat them on the coach.</sentence>
        <sentence>Let’s have them later in the tents.</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Read the dialogue. Find out which words the boys use for the following expressions:</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Look at LiF 14 on page 146 and</exercise>
        <listing>your MP3 player · my MP3 player · Sam’s MP3 player · his sister’s MP3 player · my crisps · their bags ·
            those crisps
        </listing>
        <exercise>note down all the possessive pronouns and their German meanings.</exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 14: Possessivpronomen, p. 146 P11  WB C3, p. 85</exercise>
        <exercise>C6  L 2/2</exercise>
        <exercise>a) Look at the pictures on this page and page 94. Speculate about what might happen at the Mill.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Read the story to find out if you were right. P4</exercise>
        <sentence>At the Mill</sentence>
        <sentence>It was a quiet night at the Mill.</sentence>
        <sentence>The boys were all very tired after the long trip and a day full of activities.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv was in a tent with George.</sentence>
        <sentence>There were two boys in every tent.</sentence>
        <sentence>Only Jason, who slept next to George and Rajiv, was alone in his tent.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv and George didn’t know Jason very well because he was very quiet.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv and George were asleep in their tent.</sentence>
        <sentence>Suddenly, they woke up.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Get off, get off!!” somebody screamed.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was Jason.</sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv and George got up and looked out of their tent.</sentence>
        <sentence>Then they laughed.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Hey Jason, it’s only the tent! It’s fallen down.” The boys started to put it up again.</sentence>
        <sentence>Then they heard an angry voice outside.</sentence>
        <sentence>“What are you doing?” It was their teacher, Mr Glover.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Come on, Jason. You know the rules – no fun and games after 10pm.</sentence>
        <sentence>We haven’t been here for 24 hours and you’re already breaking the rules!”</sentence>
        <sentence>The next morning, Jason got up early.</sentence>
        <sentence>He wanted to do everything right that day.</sentence>
        <sentence>First he wanted to have a shower and then go to breakfast.</sentence>
        <sentence>He didn’t want to be late.</sentence>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words ninety-three 93</footnote>
    </page>
    <page id='85'>
        <chapter>5/C</chapter>
        <sentence>Rajiv and George got up later.</sentence>
        <sentence>They didn’t have time to take a shower and got dressed quickly.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Hurry up,” Rajiv said to George.</sentence>
        <sentence>They saw Jason a few metres away.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Come on, Jason. We’ll be late for breakfast,” George said.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Hey, where are your shoes?”</sentence>
        <sentence>“I don’t know,” said Jason. “I can’t find them.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“Oh, Jason. Here, you can wear my brown shoes,” Rajiv said.</sentence>
        <sentence>At breakfast, Mr Glover stood up.</sentence>
        <sentence>“This morning I found these shoes by the river,” he said and held up a wet pair of shoes.</sentence>
        <sentence>“You all know you’re not allowed to go down there without a teacher.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“The owner should come and see me after breakfast.” Everyone knew whose shoes they were and Jason felt
            terrible again.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Rajiv and George felt sorry for him, but they saw a few boys laugh.</sentence>
        <sentence>And the day only got worse for Jason.</sentence>
        <sentence>When the boys did a quiz, Jason lost.</sentence>
        <sentence>And he was late for lunch.</sentence>
        <sentence>Finally, he couldn’t find his exercise book for his geography project.</sentence>
        <sentence>When one of the pupils found it and gave it to Mr Glover, it looked terrible.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was very dirty and Mr Glover said, “This looks like it has come straight from the bin.”</sentence>
        <sentence>Jason went red in the face when all the other boys laughed.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Later, Jason sat near the tents.</sentence>
        <sentence>George saw him and said, “Hi Jason, I guess you’ve had quite a bad day.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“Yeah,“ said Jason. “Mr Glover is really angry with me. But you know what? I didn’t really …”
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Just then two other boys walked up to them.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was Michael and Matt.</sentence>
        <sentence>They were the class clowns.</sentence>
        <sentence>They often played tricks on other boys and were always in trouble.</sentence>
        <sentence>Matt had something small and red in his hands.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Hey, Jason, are you having a bad day?” he said.</sentence>
        <sentence>“You should go home to your mum!”</sentence>
        <sentence>“Why don’t we help you go home?” Michael said with a strange laugh.</sentence>
        <sentence>Jason looked frightened.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Leave me alone,” he said and ran away.</sentence>
        <sentence>In the evening Jason and Mr Glover weren’t at dinner.</sentence>
        <sentence>At about 7 o’clock Mr Glover came into the games room.</sentence>
        <sentence>He was upset.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Now, you may have noticed that Jason isn’t here,” he said to the boys.</sentence>
        <sentence>“When we checked the tents, we found this red pocket knife under Jason’s sleeping bag.”</sentence>
        <sentence>“We told you that you mustn’t bring knives to the Mill. So we are going to send Jason home.”</sentence>
        <sentence>George looked at the red knife, then he looked at Matt and Michael.</sentence>
        <sentence>They were smiling.</sentence>
        <sentence>Suddenly George knew where he had seen the knife before – in Matt’s hand that afternoon!</sentence>
        <sentence>George knew it wasn’t Jason’s knife and now he knew why Jason was so frightened and unhappy.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>“Matt and Michael are bullying him!” he thought.</sentence>
        <sentence>But George didn’t know what to do.</sentence>
        <sentence>Should he tell Rajiv?</sentence>
        <sentence>Should he tell Mr Glover?</sentence>
        <sentence>But Jason’s parents were on the way already.</sentence>
        <sentence>Should he talk to Matt and Michael?</sentence>
        <sentence>What was the right thing to do?</sentence>
        <exercise>c) What should George do? I think he should/ shouldn’t … What shouldn’t he do?</exercise>
        <exercise>d) Hot seat: Write down questions you would like to ask the different characters in the story. Choose
            pupils to be the characters and interview them. You can make up the answers. Hot seat, p. 130 P5
        </exercise>
        <gap>George, why Mr Glover, did you notice …? didn’t you …?</gap>
        <gap>Matt and Jason, did you think you Michael, why…? could …?</gap>
        <exercise>94 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>ninety-four</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='86'>
        <chapter>5/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C7 Mr Glover has phoned Jason’s parents. But before they arrive he talks to Jason. Read what he says
            to him. How does Jason react? Can you think of a reason?
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Mr Glover: Jason, I’m really disappointed in you.</sentence>
        <sentence>I always thought you were a nice, quiet boy. But you were late for meals.</sentence>
        <sentence>The shoes I found at the river were yours … And the geography project you gave me was a mess – but you had done some work, so I thought I would give you another chance.</sentence>
        <sentence>But when we found the knife you hid in your tent – that was the limit, boy.</sentence>
        <sentence>You read the letter that explained the rules before the trip, didn’t you?</sentence>
        <exercise>C8 v Extra: Grammar card: contact clauses</exercise>
        <sentence>Jason: Yes, sir.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mr Glover: So you know this means you’re going home.</sentence>
        <sentence>Jason: Yes.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mr Glover: Well, what do you have to say for yourself, boy?</sentence>
        <sentence>Jason: I’m sorry, sir.</sentence>
        <sentence>Mr Glover: Well, so am I. I’ve phoned your parents, who are very upset.</sentence>
        <sentence>And I’m sure your classmates will be very disappointed, too.</sentence>
        <exercise>1 You know relative clauses with the relative pronouns who, which and that . Here is an example from
            C7: You read the letter that explained the rules before the trip.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 Now look at this sentence from C7: The shoes I found at the river were yours. This relative clause
            doesn’t have a relative pronoun. It is called a contact clause . Look at C7 again and find more examples of
            contact clauses.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 Check LiF 15 on page 147 to find out when you can leave out the relative pronoun. Write a grammar
            card for contact clauses. Add your examples. P6  WB C4, p. 85
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C9 v Extra a) How much do you remember about the story? Match the sentence halves.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 The school sent a letter with rules 2 Matt and Michael are the boys 3 Mr Glover found the shoes 4 Mr
            Glover found the knife 5 Matt and Michael often play tricks 6 Mr Glover talked to Jason’s parents,
        </exercise>
        <exercise>A that Michael and Matt threw in the river.</exercise>
        <exercise>B which Michael and Matt put in Jason’s tent.</exercise>
        <exercise>C that everybody knew about.</exercise>
        <exercise>D which the others don’t like.</exercise>
        <exercise>E that bullied Jason.</exercise>
        <exercise>F who were very upset.</exercise>
        <exercise>b) Look at the sentences again. Where can you leave out the relative pronoun? Note down these
            sentences.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C10 Target task v  Portfolio Write a letter.</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at pp.</exercise>
        <exercise>98/99.</exercise>
        <exercise>George has decided to write a letter to Mr Glover.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ what really happened at the Mill</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ what should happen to Jason, Matt, Michael</exercise>
        <exercise>2 This is a letter to a teacher. Be polite. Start with “Dear Mr Glover, …” and finish with “Yours
            sincerely, George Lambraki” . Writing, p. 128 Then give your letter to a partner and read his/ her letter.
            Give feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127  WB C5, C6, p. 86
        </exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words ninety-five 95</footnote>
        <exercise>1 Plan the letter. Think about</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ whose fault it was</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ why George didn’t say anything at the Mill</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='95'>
        <chapter>6/A</chapter>
        <sentence>Are you fit?</sentence>
        <exercise>A1  L 2/3 Listen to the CD. What are the different sports? Write them down.  WB A1, p. 95</exercise>
        <exercise>A2 Charles Cousins is a British rowing star. He is visiting William Ellis School to talk about fitness
            and health. To find out how fit the pupils are, they do a fitness test.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>a) Are you fit? Do the fitness test with a partner. Note down your results on a piece of paper.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Check your results on page 105.</exercise>
        <sentence>Jump up and down for 30 seconds. Are you out of breath?</sentence>
        <exercise>No, not at all.</exercise>
        <exercise>A little bit.</exercise>
        <exercise>c Yes, I am!</exercise>
        <sentence>Can you touch the floor like this?</sentence>
        <exercise>Yes, I can. I can, but it is difficult. No, I can’t. It’s too
            hard.
        </exercise>
        <sentence>Walk up and down 20 stairs quickly. Are you out of breath?</sentence>
        <exercise>No, I’m not.</exercise>
        <exercise>That’s easy.</exercise>
        <exercise>b Just a little.</exercise>
        <exercise>c Yes, I am!</exercise>
        <sentence>Can you balance like this for 15 seconds?</sentence>
        <exercise>Yes, I can.</exercise>
        <exercise>b Not quite.</exercise>
        <exercise>Sorry, I can’t do it.</exercise>
        <sentence>Do press-ups. How many can you do?</sentence>
        <exercise>More than 5. b 2–5 I can hardly do one</exercise>
        <exercise>104 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>one hundred and four</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='96'>
        <chapter>6/A</chapter>
        <exercise>A3 Find words and phrases about sport and fitness in A2 and organize them in a word web. You can add
            more words and phrases you know.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>press-ups</exercise>
        <exercise>exercises</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>get outside</exercise>
        <gap>Wordbank Sport and health, p. 153 P1  WB A2, p. 95 … SPORT + FITNESS actions</gap>
        <exercise>A4 v Extra: Viewing: Cha cha slide  Dancing is a great way to get fit! Watch the “Cha cha slide” and
            dance along. Have fun!
        </exercise>
        <exercise>A5  L 2/4 a) Listen to Rajiv and George and find out what they are talking about. Listening, p. 124
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Listen again and make notes. What did Rajiv/ George like? What didn’t they like?  WB A3, p. 96
        </exercise>
        <exercise>A6 Target task v " Project  Portfolio P2, P3 Write a dialogue between George and Caroline.</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>Rajiv George</exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 114.</exercise>
        <exercise>jump</exercise>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>In the evening, George tells his sister about the day with Charles Cousins.</exercise>
        <exercise>Writing, p. 124</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ What happened? What did George think about Charles Cousins? Collect words and ideas.</exercise>
        <exercise>Support The sports words from A3 and your notes from A5 can help you.</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Write the dialogue, then show it to a partner. Writing, p. 128 Read his/her dialogue and give
            feedback. Speaking 2, p. 127
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 Choose one of your dialogues and act it out. P9</exercise>
        <exercise>A B C</exercise>
        <sentence>Congratulations! You’re as fit as a fiddle!</sentence>
        <sentence>Keep up the good work!</sentence>
        <sentence>You can share your love for sport with your friends: you could organize a class football match, for
            example.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Not bad! You did quite well on most exercises but you can do better.</sentence>
        <sentence>If you get out of breath quickly, try to run or play tennis or football more often.</sentence>
        <sentence>If you are not very flexible, try stretching exercises every day.</sentence>
        <sentence>Oh dear! You need to get off the couch!</sentence>
        <sentence>If you are in front of a computer or TV for more than an hour, turn it off and get outside.</sentence>
        <sentence>Cycling to school, playing football with friends or dancing are great fun!</sentence>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and five 105
        </footnote>
        <exercise>1 Plan your dialogue:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ What will Caroline say?</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='97'>
        <chapter>6/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B1 a) Read the two poems. Which poem do you like better? Say why.</exercise>
        <sentence>I dreamt I played for England, I dreamt I scored each goal, I dreamt I left the players standing as I
            took the team on whole, I dreamt the fans all cheered, I dreamt they called my name, before Mum pulled me out
            of bed to end my greatest ever game.
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Fifty thousand football fans shout “Shoot, shoot, shoot!” – all around the football ground – “Shoot,
            shoot, shoot!”</sentence>
        <sentence>Thirty yards out and I get set, kick the ball straight in the net, hear the roar I can’t
            forget: “Goal, goal, goal!”
        </sentence>
        <exercise>b) Find titles for the poems and compare them in class. P10</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Extra: Add more sport words to your word web from A3. Wordbank Sport and health, p. 153  WB B1, p.
            96
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B2  L 2/5 Last weekend, there was a football match between William Ellis School and Acland Burghley.
            On Monday, George meets Lewis, a boy from Acland Burghley.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>a) Close your books and listen to them. Why are the boys arguing about the match?</exercise>
        <sentence>George: You don’t really think that Oliver played fairly, do you?</sentence>
        <sentence>Just look at my nose!</sentence>
        <sentence>Lewis: Well, I can see your nose is hurt.</sentence>
        <sentence>But it wasn’t Oliver’s fault, was it?</sentence>
        <sentence>You pushed him and when he fell down, his elbow caught your nose.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was your own fault, wasn’t it?</sentence>
        <sentence>George: What??? The fact is that Oliver was pushing me!</sentence>
        <sentence>And while he was chasing the ball he hit me on the nose with his elbow.</sentence>
        <sentence>And it sure wasn’t an accident!</sentence>
        <sentence>Lewis: You are only saying that because your team lost the match.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Well, Oliver fell down while he was running.</sentence>
        <sentence>I didn’t push him, did I?</sentence>
        <sentence>Lewis: Well, I only know what I saw …</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Then you know that Oliver also shouted at me while I was running towards the ball.</sentence>
        <sentence>And when I shouted back he pushed me.</sentence>
        <sentence>Lewis: That’s a great story, Georgie-boy.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: Let’s ask someone else, then.</sentence>
        <sentence>There’s Gillian – hey Gill, can you tell Lewis here what happened to my nose during the match?
        </sentence>
        <sentence>Gillian: Well, when the accident happened I was talking to Emma and we weren’t really watching the game.</sentence>
        <sentence>But I have to go home now, sorry, George.</sentence>
        <sentence>George: But – Gillian … ?</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Read the dialogue and say what happened while …  WB B2, B3, p. 97</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … Oliver was chasing the ball</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … George was running towards the ball</exercise>
        <gap>While Oliver was chasing the ball, he hit George …</gap>
        <exercise>106 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … Oliver was running</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … Gillian was talking to Emma</exercise>
        <exercise>one hundred and six</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='98'>
        <chapter>6/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B3 Grammar card: past progressive 1 Look at B2 again and find examples like this:</exercise>
        <sentence>While Oliver was chasing the ball he hit George on the nose.</sentence>
        <exercise>past progressive simple past</exercise>
        <exercise>The past progressive is often used in exercises where one action takes place while something else is
            going on.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>You form it with was/were + infinitive + -ing .</exercise>
        <exercise>Oliver hit George on the nose</exercise>
        <exercise>Oliver was chasing the ball</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Check LiF 16 on page 147 and start a grammar card on the past progressive. P4  WB B4, p. 98
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B4</exercise>
        <listing>Work with a partner. Look at the pictures to find out what really happened at the match. Write the
            story. Use the past progressive when necessary. LiF 16: Past progressive, p. 147 Wordbank Sport and health,
            p. 153 audience · stick out her tongue · flag · hold a sign ·
        </listing>
        <gap>Example: Oliver and George chased the ball. While George was running to … Oliver saw …</gap>
        <listing>shout at · get angry · chase the ball · hit · bleed · fall to the ground · hurt</listing>
        <exercise>1 2 3</exercise>
        <exercise>4 5 6 7</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and seven
            107
        </footnote>
    </page>
    <page id='99'>
        <chapter>6/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B5 George and Oliver went to the doctor’s after the football match. Look at the other patients in the
            waiting room.
        </exercise>
        <sentence>The girl was playing hockey when she hurt her foot.</sentence>
        <exercise>What happened to them?</exercise>
        <exercise>Wordbank Sport and health, p. 153 LiF 16: Past progressive, p. 147 P13  WB B5, p. 99</exercise>
        <exercise>B6  L 2/6 On Sunday Gillian and Oliver speak to each other on the phone. Listen to them, then read
            these exercises. Are they right or wrong? Correct the wrong exercises. Listening, p. 124 P14  WB B6, p. 100
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 Oliver is calling Gillian. 2 Gillian wants to say sorry. 3 Oliver knows many girls who are
            interested in football.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>4 Alex Scott is a man. 5 Oliver is still angry with Gillian. 6 Charlie is at Oliver’s school.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>B7 v Extra  L 2/6 a) Listen to the phone call again. Note down useful words and phrases for a
            telephone conversation. Example: Hello; Is that …?; …
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Write a telephone conversation between George and Oliver about the match.</exercise>
        <exercise>B8 Grammar card: question tags 1 When George and Lewis were arguing about the match, they used some
            questions like these: You don’t really think that Oliver played fairly, do you ? But it wasn’t Oliver’s
            fault, was it ?
        </exercise>
        <exercise>The blue part of each exercise is called a question tag .</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at B2 (page 106) again and find more examples.</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Then check LiF 17 on page 148 and write a grammar card on question tags. P5  WB B7, p. 100
        </exercise>
        <exercise>108 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>one hundred and eight</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='100'>
        <chapter>6/B</chapter>
        <exercise>B9 How much do you remember about the match?</exercise>
        <exercise>No, he didn’t.</exercise>
        <exercise>Work with a partner and ask him/her about the match.</exercise>
        <exercise>Use question tags.</exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 17: Question tags, p. 148</exercise>
        <sentence>George hit Oliver, didn’t he?</sentence>
        <exercise>B10 Target task v " Project  Portfolio Write a mystery. Another group has to solve it later.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 115.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Work in groups of four. Choose a mystery or make up your own.</exercise>
        <exercise>A</exercise>
        <sentence>After a football match, one player lies unconscious in the changing rooms.</sentence>
        <sentence>The only thing that is missing are his/her football boots.</sentence>
        <exercise>B</exercise>
        <sentence>At a swimming competition one of the swimmers is locked in the toilets and misses the race.</sentence>
        <exercise>C</exercise>
        <sentence>During a race a famous cyclist suddenly falls off his bike and breaks his right arm.</sentence>
        <sentence>The bike mechanic notices that someone must have done something to the bike before the race.
        </sentence>
        <exercise>∙ the victim · witness 1 · witness 2 · the person who did it</exercise>
        <exercise>Examples:</exercise>
        <exercise>The victim</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ the best football player in the team</exercise>
        <exercise>The person who did it</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ he hurt the football player because …</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Read your role cards carefully. Discuss if there is anything that needs to be added/changed. Tip:
            Don’t make it too easy for the police!
        </exercise>
        <exercise>4 Get together with another group. They are the police and will ask each member of your group about
            the mystery.
        </exercise>
        <gap>What were you doing when …?</gap>
        <sentence>Where were you at 5:30?</sentence>
        <gap>How long have you known …?</gap>
        <sentence>You weren’t at home last night, were you?</sentence>
        <sentence>Is there anything you saw?</sentence>
        <gap>I was eating a sandwich when I heard a loud noise in …</gap>
        <gap>I have known him for … years.</gap>
        <gap>…</gap>
        <exercise>5 When “the police” have solved the mystery, it’s your group’s turn to ask questions about their
            mystery. Wordbank Sport and health, p. 153 Speaking 1, p. 126 P15
        </exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and nine 109
        </footnote>
        <exercise>2 Now prepare role cards for each member of your group together:</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ man</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ 20 years old</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ man</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ 22 years old</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ …</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ …</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='101'>
        <chapter>6/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C1 Think – pair – share: What do you like most about a sports competition? What do you dislike? Note
            down your ideas. Think – pair – share, p. 130
        </exercise>
        <gap>I enjoy … most.</gap>
        <gap>I like … best.</gap>
        <gap>I can’t stand …</gap>
        <gap>The thing I dislike most about sports competitions is …</gap>
        <exercise>C2 Every year Camden School for Girls has a Sports Day. Each girl belongs to a house and the houses
            compete against each other. a) Read about the Sports Day that took place last year and answer the questions
            in a few words.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>1 Which years take part in the Sports Day? 2 What are the names of the Houses? 3 Who was most
            successful in the long jump?
        </exercise>
        <exercise>4 Who won the 200m sprint? 5 Who won the House Cup? 6 What took place in the afternoon?</exercise>
        <sentence>Battling to break the records</sentence>
        <sentence>Last week Camden School for Girl’s Sports Day took place at Finsbury Park.</sentence>
        <sentence>As always years 7-9 battled it out for the house cups.</sentence>
        <sentence>The day started with the long jump.</sentence>
        <sentence>Meredith Lambert (Year 9) jumped the furthest.</sentence>
        <sentence>She broke the school record and put Red House in the lead.</sentence>
        <sentence>However, Rachel Cullen (Year 8) and Alex Eastman (Year 9) of Yellow House did fantastically well in the high jump.</sentence>
        <sentence>So the Yellows took the lead.</sentence>
        <sentence>In the afternoon there were some really exciting races.</sentence>
        <sentence>Ronke Yussuf (Year 8) won the 100m and 200m sprints.</sentence>
        <sentence>Great running, Ronke!</sentence>
        <sentence>Alex Eastman was the fastest in Year 9.</sentence>
        <sentence>Both girls scored points for Yellow House.</sentence>
        <sentence>In the relays it was neck and neck between the Yellows and the Reds.</sentence>
        <sentence>A lot depended on the result of the relay races.</sentence>
        <sentence>After the Year 7 relay, the Yellows were in the lead.</sentence>
        <sentence>After the Year 8 relay, the Blues overtook the Greens and gained third place.</sentence>
        <sentence>But it was clear that the winning house was going to be Red or Yellow.</sentence>
        <sentence>The atmosphere in the stadium was tense.</sentence>
        <sentence>Finally, it was the Year 9 relay that decided everything.</sentence>
        <sentence>The Yellows came in first, and they won the House Cup!</sentence>
        <sentence>The audience cheered for ages.</sentence>
        <sentence>In the afternoon everyone enjoyed the fun and games.</sentence>
        <sentence>As usual the fun relay against the teachers was a highlight.</sentence>
        <sentence>The teachers won narrowly.</sentence>
        <sentence>Well done to all!</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Compare the Sports Day with the sports day at your school. Example: There are more events at CSG
            than at our school.
        </exercise>
        <gap>We only … The girls at CSG are more competitive than … LiF 3: Steigerung von Adjektiven, p. 137/138 P6  WB
            C1, p. 101
        </gap>
        <listing>exciting · boring · many · successful · competitive · funny · serious · outstanding</listing>
        <exercise>110 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>one hundred and ten</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='102'>
        <chapter>6/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C3  L 2/7 a) Caroline and Emma are both looking forward to this year’s Sports Day. They are in Red
            House. Listen to them and find out why they are excited about Sports Day. Listening, p. 124
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) How will Caroline and Emma feel if they don’t win the races? Say why.</exercise>
        <exercise>c) Listen again and take notes. Find out what will happen if …</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … the Reds win the House Cup this year? ∙ … the Reds come last in the House competition?</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … Caroline promises not to be so bossy?</exercise>
        <exercise>C4  L 2/8 It’s a week after Sports Day. Emma wrote a story about it for her English class.</exercise>
        <exercise>a) Read the story and choose the best title for it. Give reasons.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Victory for the Reds ∙ Friends forever</exercise>
        <sentence>Caroline and I were really excited about Sports Day.</sentence>
        <sentence>The weeks before the big day we trained for at least half an hour after school every day.</sentence>
        <sentence>I took the race more seriously now.</sentence>
        <sentence>Thanks to Caroline I was running much more confidently and was getting so much better.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline wanted to come first in one of her races so she trained very hard and she ran faster from
            week to week.</sentence>
        <sentence>Finally the big day arrived.</sentence>
        <sentence>We all met at Finsbury Park Stadium where the sports events were taking place.</sentence>
        <sentence>The stadium was full of us, all wearing our house colours.</sentence>
        <sentence>Of course, my classmates and I were all wearing red.</sentence>
        <sentence>We were chanting excitedly:</sentence>
        <sentence>Nothing can stop the Reds!</sentence>
        <sentence>Nothing can stop the Reds!</sentence>
        <sentence>We’ll never give up!</sentence>
        <sentence>We’ll never give in!</sentence>
        <sentence>We’ll fight to the end, we’ve come here to win!</sentence>
        <sentence>On the field Navina from our class was just doing the high jump.</sentence>
        <sentence>It was a fantastic jump and the Reds all cheered enthusiastically.</sentence>
        <sentence>Then a voice came over the loudspeaker: “The 200 metres will take place in 5 minutes!”</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline looked rather pale and went to join the others at the starting line.</sentence>
        <sentence>Suddenly I had an idea.</sentence>
        <sentence>There was still time to send a message over the microphone.</sentence>
        <sentence>I ran to Mrs Shimmin, who was doing the “shout-outs” and wrote mine down quickly.</sentence>
        <sentence>Then I went back to my seat to watch the race.</sentence>
        <sentence>I crossed my fingers for luck.</sentence>
        <sentence>I knew how much Caroline wanted to win.</sentence>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and eleven
            111
        </footnote>
        <exercise>∙ … the Reds don’t win the Cup?</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ … Emma trains a bit harder?</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Emma’s big day</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='103'>
        <chapter>6/C</chapter>
        <sentence>Now it was time for the race.</sentence>
        <sentence>Just then the loudspeaker came on: “This is a message for Caroline Lambraki from her friend, Emma: ‘You can do it, Caroline! Go! Go! Go!’”</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline smiled at me.</sentence>
        <sentence>Then the race started: “On your marks, get set, go!”</sentence>
        <sentence>We all cheered madly.</sentence>
        <sentence>The girls just flew along the track.</sentence>
        <sentence>Caroline’s main rival, Kadhija, was on her left.</sentence>
        <sentence>She ran faster than Caroline.</sentence>
        <sentence>I could see that Caroline was trying hard to keep up, but there was no way she could catch her.</sentence>
        <sentence>At the finishing line, Caroline fell on the ground dramatically.</sentence>
        <sentence>“Great race, Caroline!” I said. “Well done!”</sentence>
        <sentence>“But I only came second,” she answered.</sentence>
        <sentence>Typical Caroline. She hates to lose.</sentence>
        <sentence>“But your time was fantastic! Kadhija broke the school record, and you were just behind her!”</sentence>
        <sentence>But that didn’t help much. Caroline was very disappointed.</sentence>
        <sentence>Then it was time for my race.</sentence>
        <sentence>I was nervous, too. But I could only do my best.</sentence>
        <sentence>And in the end all that training helped – I came in third.</sentence>
        <sentence>Even Caroline felt better after my race.</sentence>
        <sentence>I hugged her. “That’s all thanks to you, Caroline!” I said.</sentence>
        <sentence>After the competitions there was an afternoon of fun.</sentence>
        <sentence>We all felt relaxed now and even Caroline joined in.</sentence>
        <sentence>At the end of the day we all waited impatiently to hear the results of the house competitions.</sentence>
        <sentence>When Mrs Shimmin announced the results, the Reds clapped more wildly than ever.</sentence>
        <sentence>For the first time in years we won the House Cup. What a day!</sentence>
        <exercise>b) Find headings for the different paragraphs. Example: Paragraph 1 – Excited about Sports Day;
            paragraph 2 – … P7, P12
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C5  L 2/9 a) Find examples of adverbs with -ly in Emma’s story and write them down. Example:
            excitedly, …
        </exercise>
        <exercise>b) Do you know how to pronounce the words? Where is the stress? Check the CD to see if you were right.
            P8  WB C2, C3, p. 102, 103
        </exercise>
        <exercise>112 A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words</exercise>
        <exercise>Now it was time for the race.</exercise>
        <exercise>Just then the</exercise>
        <exercise>one hundred and twelve</exercise>
    </page>
    <page id='104'>
        <chapter>6/C</chapter>
        <exercise>C6 Grammar card: comparison of adverbs 1 Look at these sentences to find out about comparisons of
            adverbs: I was running much more confidently. She ran faster than Caroline.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>2 Look at LiF 18 on page 148 and add the rules to your grammar card for adverbs.</exercise>
        <exercise>3 Write down two sentences with -er/-est , two sentences with more/most and four sentences with a
            comparison of well, badly and much . P11  WB C4, p. 103
        </exercise>
        <exercise>C7</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at these verbs and adverbs and write down five exercises about your classmates.</exercise>
        <exercise>Example: Leon swims faster than Ben.</exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 18: Steigerung von Adverbien, p. 148  WB C5, p. 104</exercise>
        <listing>swim/fast · run/quickly · sing/well · write/clearly · draw/beautifully ·</listing>
        <exercise>C8 v Choose Wordbank Sports and health, p. 153  WB C6, p. 104</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Use rhyming words. Describe your hobby and use the words and phrases from A3.</exercise>
        <exercise>We’re cool!</exercise>
        <exercise>We’re crazy!</exercise>
        <exercise>We’ll beat you!</exercise>
        <exercise>Defeat you!</exercise>
        <exercise>Gooooo (put the name of your class here) !</exercise>
        <exercise>C9 Target task v  Portfolio Write Caroline’s story about Sports Day.</exercise>
        <exercise>1 Look at Emma’s story in C4 again. What are her thoughts, feelings and opinions?</exercise>
        <exercise>2 Compare Caroline to Emma. What do you think Caroline’s thoughts, feelings and opinions might be?
        </exercise>
        <gap>Support I love basketball because … My favourite sport/team is … I’m really good at … / I could improve my
            … I play in a team/at a club/… I have been training since … / I started when I was … I (don’t) take it very
            seriously.
        </gap>
        <exercise>Need help?</exercise>
        <exercise>Look at p. 116.</exercise>
        <exercise>Support These words can help you: nervous, excited, upset, disappointed, ambitious, confident,
            frustrated, angry, determined, relaxed, jealous, emotional
        </exercise>
        <exercise>3 Now write Caroline’s story. Describe what happens from her point of view.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Use adjectives and adverbs (and comparisons when necessary) to make the story more interesting.
        </exercise>
        <exercise>LiF 18: Steigerung von Adverbien, p. 148 Writing, p. 128  WB C7, p. 105</exercise>
        <footnote>A | B | C | Personal Trainer | Photo page | Optional • Skills • LiF • Words one hundred and thirteen
            113
        </footnote>
        <exercise>∙ Write your own class chant.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Write your sports profile.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Repeat words or sounds.</exercise>
        <sentence>We’re never ever lazy!</sentence>
        <sentence>We’ll even try to eat you!</sentence>
        <exercise>∙ Include Caroline’s thoughts, feelings and opinions.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Add direct speech.</exercise>
        <exercise>∙ Add connectives (e.g. and, but ) and structure words (e.g. first, then ).</exercise>
    </page>
</document>